<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Military</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/military-0</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>A Taunton vicar&#039;s letters from the front</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/taunton-vicars-letters-front</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A remarkable correspondence had begun by 1915 between parishioners and the vicar of Taunton St Mary Magdalene and other church officers. Although the originals are missing many were copied into the parish magazine or extracts were printed. There were letters about killed and missing men, appeals for food from prisoners of war and sometimes quite graphic accounts of life in the trenches. There were letters from France, Burma and naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 13:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25527 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Norton Fitzwarren in the Second World War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/norton-fitzwarren-second-world-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norton Fitzwarren was an important military site in the Second World War which left a  lasting legacy to the parish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 10:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25510 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Military History of Norton Fitzwarren</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/military-history-norton-fitzwarren</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norton Fitzwarren on the outskirts of Taunton was a site of national importance during the Second World War with several miltary sites&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 11:41:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25503 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dummer War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wooden lychgate at the entrance to the church yard from the street was erected in 1919 as a memorial to the 13 men of the parish who lost their lives in the First World War. It was designed by Lady Emily Rycroft, second wife to Sir Richard Nelson who lived in the village from the time of his marriage in 1911 until his death in 1925.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The memorial was based on the style of a wooden porch at Boxford church in Suffolk. Although she was born in London to a military family, Lady Emily at one time lived at Edwardstone Hall (demolished in 1952), with her parents and siblings so would have known the nearby Boxford church well.[1] The timbers for the lychgate were donated by Robert Miller of Dummer Grange where an old barn was being demolished.[2] Wording on the cross beams reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To those fallen in the service of their country 1914-1918.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My flesh also shall rest in hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plaque bearing the names of eight men who lost their lives in the Second World War was later added as a memorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link below gives details of the men remembered on the WWI plaques displayed on the gate. No records have as yet been found for Frederick Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a roll of honour inside the church and a stone plaque remembering the dead of WW2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] 1901 Census; www.lostheritage.org.uk/houses (accessed 3 May 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] HRO, 65M72/PZ3 &lt;em&gt;Dummer parish magazine&lt;/em&gt; Jun. 1968.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 11:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25391 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Thornycroft in Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thornycroft-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thornycroft, the commercial vehicle manufacturer, was the biggest employer in Basingstoke for much of the 20th century. Therefore the fluctuations in its fortunes had a considerable impact on the economy of the town. There was a dramatic drop in trade in the early 1920s when 700 men were discharged and the weekly wage bill fell from just under £8,000 to a little over £4,000. Employment peaked during the two world wars when Thornycroft diversified into munitions work and over 30 per cent of its workforce were women. During the Second World War Thornycroft was employing 2,500 people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a more detailed history see the link below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 07:14:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25388 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bishops Hull War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bishops-hull-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The war memorial for Bishops Hull stands in a prominent position in the centre of the village. There are plaques around the plinth replacing the originals. In 2017 it was planned to replace that for the First World War, which contains errors and omissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The war memorial is naturally a focal point for remembering those in the community who died in conflict but of course men from Bishops Hull had served and died in the military services long before there was any thought of war memorials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 10:20:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25183 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Probate Material 1651-1660</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-probate-material-1651-1660</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One inventory and thirteen wills survive for this period, only one document is held in the Hampshire Record Office (HRO), the remainder are held at The National Archives (TNA).  All bishoprics were abolished in 1646 following Parliament’s victory in the First Civil War 1642-6 and wills were proved in the Prerogative Court of Canterbury (PCC), archived in The National Archives, until the Restoration of 1660. Unusually, in Winchester, officials kept the probate service going in the late 1640s. Some of the wills reflect the difficult times of religious dissent and Civil War whilst others indicate considerable wealth with property held in Basingstoke, Berkshire and London. In fact at any time wills with property in more than one diocese had to be proved at the PCC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document but which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire. Links to all of the transcriptions are below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-roger-weston-senior-yeoman-1653&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roger Weston, senior, yeoman (Will and Inventory), 1653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-thomas-south-elder-clothier-1653&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas South, the elder, clothier (Will), 1653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-holmes-yeoman-1653&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Holmes, yeoman (Will), 1653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-aylwyn-gent-1654&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Aylwyn, Gent (Will), 1654&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-richard-george-woollen-draper-1656&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard George, woollen draper (Will), 1656&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-tempule-farmer-1656&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Tempule, farmer (Will), 1656&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-herne-clothier-1657&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Herne, clothier (Will), 1657&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-pell-gent-1657&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Pell, Gent (Will), 1657&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-jane-dovey-widow-1657&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jane Dovey, widow (Will), 1657&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-james-wyther-gent-1658&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;James Wyther, Gent (Will), 1658&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-stephen-webb-minister-1660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stephen Webb, minister (Will), 1660&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-richard-everadevered-tanner-1660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Everad/Evered, tanner (Will), 1660&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-kew-haberdasher-and-soldier-1660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Kew, haberdasher and soldier (Will), 1660&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 09:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25055 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Burials in Bishops Hull during the Civil War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/burials-bishops-hull-during-civil-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the Civil War Taunton because of its castle was frequently the scene of military activity. The castle actually lay in Bishops Hull parish, which is probably why several soldiers were taken there for burial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 13:35:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24650 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Captain John Aidan Liddell VC MC (1888-1915)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/captain-john-aidan-liddell-vc-mc-1888-1915</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;John Liddell was the son of John and Emily Liddell who lived at Sherfield Manor, Sherfield on Loddon, just outside Basingstoke. He was awarded the MC and VC in 1915 and died of wounds received whilst flying over Belgium. He is buried in Basingstoke (South View) Cemetery along with other members of his family.  His VC citation reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘For most conspicuous bravery and devotion to duty on 31 July 1915. When on a flying reconnaissance over Ostend-Bruges-Ghent he was severely wounded (his right thigh being broken), which caused momentary unconsciousness; but by a great effort he recovered partial control after his machine had dropped nearly 3,000 feet and, notwithstanding his collapsed state, succeeded, although continually fired at, in completing his course, and brought the aeroplane into our lines half an hour later after he had been wounded. The difficulties experienced by this officer in saving his machine and the life of his observer cannot be readily expressed, but as the control wheel and throttle control were smashed, and also one of the under-carriage struts, it would seem incredible that he could have accomplished his task.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 17:36:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23129 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>New war memorial Watchet</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/new-war-memorial-watchet</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The town of Watchet did not have its own war memorial recording the names of those killed in the First World War until 2014. As in some other communities it had been decided to create a recreation ground instead, the Memorial Ground. A sports pavilion and stand were dedicated to the memory of the fallen in July 1929.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, with the approach of the centenary of the start of the First World War the Watchet Remembrance Project began to create a memorial to the men of the town killed in both the First and Second World Wars. It was unveiled on the 28 June 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appropriately it stands in a small paved garden beside the library facing the railway station from which most of the men would have left the town, never to return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 08:40:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23110 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
