<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Cheltenham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/cheltenham</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Cheltenham Early Modern Wills</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cheltenham-early-modern-wills</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;These wills from the Gloucestershire Archives for Cheltenham and adjoining parishes have been transcribed by Judy Kimber on behalf of VCH Gloucestershire.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2017 12:46:40 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JBroadway</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25192 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Hundred Roll</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/hundred-roll</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Hundred Roll for Cheltenham was not included when the series was published in the early 19th century. Although researchers have consulted and quoted from the surviving membrane, it has not previously been fully transcribed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 16:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23101 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cheltenham medieval wills</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cheltenham-medieval-wills</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Very few medieval wills are known for Cheltenham. Four survive in the PROB11 series at the National Archives, and will be added here as transcription proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another 6 copy wills survive at Worcestershire RO. They have been trancribed from microfilm, with the loss of occasional words towards the edge of the image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pious bequests are a marked feature of these pre-Reformation wills, and give clues as the contemporary arrangement of the parish church in Cheltenham.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2014 21:36:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22726 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cheltenham: medieval manorial rentals</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cheltenham-medieval-manorial-rentals</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Included here are transcriptions of several &lt;strong&gt;rentals&lt;/strong&gt; mostly of the 15th century, held at the National Archives (SC 11/216 to 227). Most of them can be linked to the period when the manor was owned by the Abbess of Syon, Middlesex.  They are probably best described as stray survivors rather than as a set (several are damaged or incomplete), and there is no obvious logic to the cataloguing order. Only 3 pieces have internal dates, but by comparison of tenants&#039; names, and other clues, a relative chronology can be established.  Transcriptions were done by members of the Cheltenham Local History Society&#039;s Latin Group, working from images taken by &lt;strong&gt;Dr Beth Hartland&lt;/strong&gt;, who is researching medieval Cheltenham (and Cirencester) for the Victoria County History of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/gloucestershire&quot;&gt;Gloucestershire&lt;/a&gt;.  A further related item, a survey of c1440, has been transcribed from D855/M68, held at Gloucestershire Archives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The likely sequence is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/220 - C14th?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/221 - 1420?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/218 - 1430 (dated)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/225 - 1430?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/222 and 223 - 1440?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/217 - 1450 (dated)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/219 - 1450 and 1452 (dated)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/216 - 1470&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11/227 - late Elizabethan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 21:45:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22708 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cheltenham Probate Inventories, 1587-1783</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cheltenham-probate-inventories-1587-1783</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This set of 32 inventories has been transcribed by volunteers at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gloucestershire.gov.uk/archives/article/107703/Archives-Homepage&quot;&gt;Gloucestershire Archives&lt;/a&gt; as a building block for the planned VCH volume covering Cheltenham and district.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2013 09:42:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21474 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rentals of rectory lands of Cheltenham and Charlton Kings</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rentals-rectory-lands-cheltenham-and-charlton-kings</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the 17th century, the rectory lands and tithes of Cheltenham and the associated &#039;chapel&#039; of Charlton Kings descended from Sir Baptist Hicks of Chipping Campden through his younger daughter and eventually to the Essex family, with whom they remained until sold to the developer Joseph Pitt in the late 18th century. Three rentals are known to survive, one in Essex papers preserved at Gloucestershire Archives, and two in the Hertfordshire Record Office.  (The Hicks/Capel/Essex families held many lands in Gloucestershire; their descent is detailed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=66393&quot;&gt;VCH Glos Vol 8 section on Tewkesbury manors and estates&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2012 13:51:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20972 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cheltenham Manorial Records</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cheltenham-manorial-records</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cheltenham has a rich series of manor records, starting in the 1300s. The surviving 18th century records were published by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bgas.org.uk&quot;&gt;Bristol and Gloucestershire Archaeological Society&lt;/a&gt; in 2010, and other records are now being worked on by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cheltlocalhist.btck.co.uk/&quot;&gt;Cheltenham Local History Society&lt;/a&gt;&#039;s Latin Group.  We are working forwards from 1597, adding a year at a time - currently up to 1611.  We have also posted a collated set of records (1645-60) from the Commonwealth period, and coverage of Restoration records from 1660 to 1669. Transcripts for certain other years may be added in due course.  The transcription/translation methodology is generally &#039;modified verbatim&#039; - verbatim where the details clearly matter, but with some suppression of repetitive legal phraseology. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to add transcriptions of any other surviving records for the medieval period (certain isolated years) to support the current work on a new VCH Glos volume for Cheltenham. There is also a good run of Tudor records at Gloucestershire Archives, but these are rough minutes in a particularly difficult hand, and will take some time to process.  Volunteers welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2012 12:38:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20938 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
