<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Staffordshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/ancient-county/staffordshire</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Parish Officers of Haughton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parish-officers-haughton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Haughton is a Village approximately 4 miles west south west of Stafford, 8 miles from Newport in Shropshire, and about 137 miles from London. It is in the Cuttlestone West Hundred of Staffordshire and in the Diocese of Lichfield lying on the A518 road from Stafford to Newport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From an early date the Parish was organised to look after most communal and financial needs. Each year the parish elected officials, which included Parish Constables, Overseers of the Poor, and Surveyors of the Highways.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 09:08:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20853 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Landscape of the Prebendal Manor of Gnosall</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/landscape-prebendal-manor-gnosall</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The earliest surviving record of Gnosall is in the Domesday Book of 1086, where the name is written as&lt;em&gt; Geneshale.&lt;/em&gt; However, it is likely that Gnosall had been in existence for a long time prior to this date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The place-name ‘Gnosall’ incorporates both native British and Old English elements describing the local topography. The place may have been originally called Geneu by the British, referring to the narrowing of a valley, of which there are several possible examples in the immediate vicinity. To this name was added the element halh; in this instance probably indicating ‘low-lying land by a river’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of the Domesday survey, Gnosall was a modestly sized settlement consisting of 8 ‘villein’ households - tenants who held land in return for labouring on behalf of their lord, and 4 ‘bordars’ or smallholders. Domesday records that there was sufficient arable land to keep two ploughs in work and that these local people had two ploughs. However, there seems to have been some over-capacity in this respect, because there were another four ploughs owned by the lords of the manor, presumably the nine priests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a water mill for grinding corn. Gnosall seems to have been a fairly poor, but improving, community; its value had increased from 2 shillings in 1066 AD to 15 shillings in 1086 AD. However, this higher value only placed Gnosall in the middle of the range for the county as a whole, and Staffordshire was a relatively poor county.&lt;br /&gt;
	The Domesday Book gives only a partial account of local agriculture, making no reference to other resources, such as pasture, meadow or woodland, yet it is clear that livestock farming was probably as important to the area as growing crops. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 08:09:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20845 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Population trends in the Parish of Biddulph, 1700-1800</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/population-trends-parish-biddulph-1700-1800</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;My aim was to study the parish registers of St. Lawrence, Biddulph, from 1700 until 1800, to transcribe and collate the information gleaned – adding it to a very simple spread sheet. From this, I hoped that I would be able to draw conclusions as to general population trends (as extrapolated from baptisms and burials) and to look at such trends in greater detail by using family reconstitutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 11:53:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20842 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Working Class Housing in the Cross Street, Stringer Street and Duke of York Square area of Biddulph</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/working-class-housing-cross-street-stringer-street-and-duke-york-square-area-biddulph</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are no maps earlier than 1876 detailed enough to show property in the surveyed area, but we do know that a Charles Stringer in 1851 lived in Stringer Street, (hence its name). He was a miller and provision dealer owning the water powered mill at nearby Gillowshaw Brook. This mill was later powered by a steam engine, whose foundations still exist. We feel that most of the original houses shown on the 1876 map were built c1840/50.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three streets known locally as the “Square&quot; are located between High Street and Station Road in an area mentioned on the 1876 map of Bradley Green (the original name of present day Biddulph) a mainly working class residential area in that period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This area in 1876 comprised of about 45 homes; many small two up and two down cottages, with a few larger houses - home to about 10% of the population of Bradley Green at that time. By 1890 approximately 14 cottages had been demolished in order to cater for the increase in the demand for fustian velvet, when in 1892, a two storey mill was built for fustian cutting. The first mill owner was Henry Mitchell. Later the Platt family took over the business, followed by the United Velvet Cutters in 1912-16. Census of the time show many fustian workers lived in the “Square”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Second World War the ARP used part of the mill as their Headquarters and stores; there was also a stage inside where concerts were performed for locals and troops. Between 1959/87 William Standards &amp;amp;Co were to manufacture clothing in the mill. Today it has a non-textile use. Presently there are less than twenty cottages in the area- mostly well kept. Two businesses, one a furniture retailer and funeral director (Est. 1856) and the other a hairdresser are still active. There are also plots of waste land and out of use industrial buildings all awaiting redevelopment in the area.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 11:54:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20802 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Clifton Campville: lordship and community</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/clifton-campville-lordship-and-community</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A study of lordship as reflected in the church at Clifton Campville &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 14:16:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20572 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Croxden Abbey</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/croxden-abbey</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water Colour painting of Croxden Abbey.  Showing the west wall of the chapter house, the interior and the high transept wall, exterior, from the south east. Anonymous, [L. J. Wood.]&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2010 14:59:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20267 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
