<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Arts &amp; Leisure</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/arts-leisure</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Men’s Own Brotherhood Movement in Basingstoke: 1899-1929</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/men%E2%80%99s-own-brotherhood-movement-basingstoke-1899-1929</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For 30 years a Pleasant Sunday Afternoon (hereafter P.S.A.) Society, also known as the Men’s Own Brotherhood, was attached to London Street Congregational Church in Basingstoke. Although a number other Free Churches introduced something similar in the early years of the 20th century they were relatively short lived by comparison with London Street’s P.S.A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originating in the West Midlands, the P.S.A. Movement had been started in 1875 by John Blackham, a Sunday school teacher and deacon of the Ebenezer Congregational Church, West Bromwich. It quickly spread and societies were established in many parts of the country, including Hampshire. As expressed in a work published at the height of the Movement in 1912, ‘the attempt … [was] nothing less than to teach a “democratic religion” leading to a “practical Christianity” full of love and good works.’ Sunday afternoon meetings were designed to be ‘brief, bright and brotherly’ with lively hymn singing, musical contributions and ‘helpful and often eloquent addresses’, thereby appealing, in particular, to working men who would not otherwise have attended church services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inaugural meeting of London Street P.S.A. was held in May 1899 and the final one in October 1929. To symbolise its close links with the Church, the first President was the minister of London Street, the Revd Capes Tarbolton (see image). His successors were also closely associated with the P.S.A. which at its height during the first decade of the 20th century had around 300 members. Following its launch, the P.S.A. quickly took on a life of its own with half yearly book distributions, a slate club and a coal club inaugurated in 1901, open air meetings and picnics, the introduction of Pleasant Saturday Evening entertainments and later outings and philanthropic enterprises. Notwithstanding the phrase ‘men’s own’, women were by no means excluded from the activities of the Brotherhood. Although meetings were intended primarily for men, on occasions women were invited to attend. Known as ‘open meetings’, they proved to be very popular. Women were also involved through their musical contributions and occasionally giving talks. The London Street P.S.A networked with similar societies through various groupings, which changed over the years, and was associated with the National Brotherhood Movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the autumn of 1929, by a small majority, members resolved that meetings be ‘discontinued forthwith’. What prompted this decision is not entirely clear, but in all probability it was declining numbers and a feeling that the P.S.A. had outlived its usefulness. However, the winding up of London Street’s Brotherhood did not mark the end of the Movement in Basingstoke. Four years later, in 1933, a branch of the Post-War Brotherhood was established in the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;June 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 06:51:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25406 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Jane Austen, Basingstoke Balls and Wicked William Willson</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/jane-austen-basingstoke-balls-and-wicked-william-willson</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;William Willson was, in the words of &lt;em&gt;Lloyd’s Evening Post&lt;/em&gt; for February 15, 1804, &#039;an Innkeeper at Basingstoke [who] eloped with a girl of fifteen, and was afterwards traced to a brothel in Covent-Garden.&#039; He kept the Crown Inn in Winchester Street, one of the two most prestigious inns in Basingstoke. He organised the balls that Jane Austen attended and hosted the Hants Club whose members included many of her acquaintances, as well as her brother James. Jane would have known William Willson in his prime, and would have been aware of his downfall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 09:44:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24540 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Milestones: Hampshire&#039;s Living History Museum, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/milestones-hampshires-living-history-museum-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1968 Hampshire County Council took possession of the Tasker Collection of traction engines relating to the Waterloo Ironworks in Andover which closed in 1937. During the 1970s they acquired more redundant agricultural machinery, lorries, steam rollers, wagons etc from Hampshire’s industrial past, including Basingstoke manufacturers Thornycroft and Wallis &amp;amp; Steevens. Looking for a suitable site to display the items, HCC and Basingstoke &amp;amp; Deane Borough Council went into partnership and in 1994 made land available at West Ham Leisure Park. Two years later a £6M Heritage Lottery Fund grant enabled the project to start.[1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A competition was held to name the proposed museum and work commenced in March 1997 by contractors John Sisk &amp;amp; Son Limited. The building is of concrete, aluminium, stainless steel, glass and slate. It is two storeys high but unusually the floors have been sunk 7m into the ground, which involved the removal of 43,000 cubic metres of chalk to create the 102m long arena.[2] The natural insulation provided by the chalk maintains a stable temperature for exhibits and virtually eliminates the need for heating or cooling. The hangar-style roof consists of 17 steel trussed arches of 55m spans. The glazed walls at either end have sealed-in blinds which react to changes in brightness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some 21,000 objects in the museum have been laid out in Victorian and 1930s-40s working street scenes, although some household items date back to the early 1700s. Photographic evidence helped to create the façades, and an appeal was made at the beginning of the build for donations of any old bricks, cobbles, slates and tiles as well as street furniture, shop and advertising signs. The Basingstoke Willis Museum Archaeological Group rescued door furniture and fireplaces from houses which were demolished in the late 1960s as part of the town’s redevelopment. Salvage was recycled from Reading bus depot and the demolished Thornycroft factory in Basingstoke; granite kerb stones came from Aberdeen; several hundred feet of unwanted tramrail was purchased from Blackpool and wooden blocks from St Mary’s Gas Works in Southampton.[3] The material was collected by the County’s Museums Services based in Winchester where staff and volunteers collated, cleaned and restored exhibits, finally fitting out the completed buildings in February 2000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visitors, aided by costumed guides, can enter fully stocked shops, purchase Milestones Ale in the pub, enter the station booking office and get up close to cars, horse drawn carts and commercial vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final cost of the project rose to £11M which was raised by substantial donations from local companies, HCC and B&amp;amp;DBC. The Basingstoke based Sony company donated audio visual equipment.[4] The official opening was carried out by HRH the Duke of Edinburgh on 1st December 2000 with 175,000 visitors in the first year although it has been difficult to maintain this level of interest.[5] In addition to the museum space there is also a restaurant, facilities for school parties and corporate events and an exhibition area. The complex won the Best Social and Industrial Museum of the year award in 2002.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Text based on &lt;em&gt;The Making of Milestones&lt;/em&gt;, compiled by Mark Fenton, Hampshire County Council Museums Service, 2000; Hampshire Record Office HPUB/MU1/1/1/3 unless otherwise stated.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, 8 Jan 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;em&gt;Milestones News&lt;/em&gt;, Issue 2, July 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, 18 June 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, 23 Nov 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Observer&lt;/em&gt;, 29 Aug 2002.&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 15:29:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23103 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Ancient Mariner</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ancient-mariner</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fictional Ancient Mariner is among the most well-known English seamen and it is fitting that he should be rembered in the town that inspired his creation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:27:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22103 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Triumphal Gateway, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/triumphal-gateway-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Basingstoke Triumphal Gateway&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By various means including direct commissions from the Council, the town of Basingstoke has accumulated an exceptional collection of modern outdoor public art work for a town of its size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest is the ‘Triumphal Gateway’ commissioned by the Council and erected in 1992 at the eastern end of the pedestrianised London Street where it meets New Road at right angles and looks towards the end of London Road opposite. Once London Road and London Street were part of a main traffic artery through the town; this function has been taken over by ring roads, but the spot still has the air of a point of transition between the outskirts and the town centre, and it was here, or near here, that a number of temporary triumphal arches have been erected in the past to mark coronations and other royal occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gateway was designed by Hampshire ‘artist blacksmith’ Peter Parkinson as a ‘modern complement’ to the old buildings nearby, and to frame the ‘powerful sense of perspective’ one gets when looking from it along the straight London Street towards the Market Place at its other end. A line of closely spaced vertical flat steel bars on either side of the open gateway gives a vertical emphasis to the structure which is angled at the top to match the roof profile of nearby historic buildings such as the 1608 Sir James Deane almshouses on its southern side and Goldings a short distance away in London Road. Some of the bars extend above this profile to convey a suggestion of organ pipes and triumphal music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is part of Peter Parkinson’s design philosophy to combine large structures with small pictorial images ‘to draw people in and encourage them to explore the piece’. Thus he and his assistant, Trevor Forester, produced designs for sixteen boldly executed low relief bronze panels fixed to the Gateway on which are images that reflect aspects of the town’s history and culture. Some images are thematic such as those that draw attention to Basingstoke as a transport hub, and as a centre for shopping, sport and entertainments, whilst others refer to particular episodes in the town’s history such as the siege of the royalist stronghold, Basing House, by the forces of Oliver Cromwell. One panel depicts Basingstoke’s entry in Domesday Book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bronze panels were cast by the lost wax process at the world renowned Morris Singer Foundry which was located in Basingstoke at that time, whilst the steelwork was fabricated by a firm of craftsmen run by ‘art blacksmith’ Richard Quinnell with whom Peter Parkinson has undertaken a number of joint commissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gateway has had its admirers from the start, but when it was first erected it provoked fierce criticism on account of its size, its modernity, its £50,000 cost and what some saw as its unsuitability for a conservation area. However when Lord Palumbo, the Chairman of the Arts Council, saw it soon after it had been put up, he commented that ‘in the course of time, critics will come to terms with it and it will become a natural part of the landscape’. Many local people – though not all – now appear to have accepted it as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 14:55:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21664 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Anvil, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/anvil-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Anvil concert hall has firmly established itself as one of the South’s leading venues with acoustics which are among the finest in the country. It has excellent lighting and outside broadcast provision in the technical gallery sited below the roof void. A comprehensive programme is provided with high quality live music specialising in big name soloists, conductors and composers – the Bournemouth Symphony Orchestra and London Mozart Players are regulars - as well as opera, ballet, jazz, country, folk, popular music and comedy acts.  Local organisations are not excluded; choral concerts, dance competitions, school performances and community events all take place at the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a civic centre in Basingstoke was first raised in 1966, but it took 25 years of campaigning, debate and rejected schemes before a feasibility study was carried out by architects Renton Howard Wood Levin in 1991. The site between Alençon Link and Churchill Way was selected as the best location. £6.5M was raised towards the total cost of £12.4M for the build when the Council prematurely paid back debts to the Public Works Loans Board, thus qualifying for complex interest rate discounts – a loophole quickly closed by the government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work started on site in July 1991. However, not everyone approved of the design and an appeal was sent to Prince Charles to intervene against the ‘gunboat’ shape but with no success. The complex went on to win a commendation in the Civic Trust Awards in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The building is made up of eight separate elements. The 1400-seat auditorium has flexible seating and staging formats which create a multi-purpose space while fixed circle seats wrap around on three sides; a simple proscenium arch can be introduced for theatrical performances. The stall seats are fully retractable to give a completely flat floor suitable for sporting events, banquets, exhibitions and trade launches. An area in front of the stage can be lowered to give an orchestra pit. The Forge offers a small, flexible studio space for 80-150 suitable for film screenings or business presentations; the circular Linden room is ideal for small receptions and meetings whilst there are bars on two floors and a café bistro with outdoor terrace seating and a booking office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of The Anvil was chosen to represent the town’s industrial heritage and to reflect the fire and energy that would be forged inside. Sir Andrew Lloyd Webber is its patron and a Gala Concert was held on 3rd May 1994 to celebrate the opening with performances by Julian Lloyd Webber and a world première of Taverner’s Theophany. The Bournemouth Symphony Orchestra with Basingstoke Choral Society appropriately performed &lt;em&gt;The Anvil Chorus&lt;/em&gt; and the event was broadcast on BBC Radio 3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2013 12:23:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21620 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Maisemore in the 19th century press</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/maisemore-19th-century-press</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Volunteers supporting the editorial work on Maisemore for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/gloucestershire/work-in-progress&quot;&gt;VCH Gloucestershire Volume 13&lt;/a&gt; have used the newly available &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk&quot;&gt;British Library British Newspapers online site&lt;/a&gt; to extract relevant references.  For a small village, references in national and regional titles are surprisingly frequent.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2012 19:16:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20970 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Drill Hall, Sarum Hill, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/drill-hall-sarum-hill-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This building at the top of Sarum Hill, Basingstoke, was erected in July 1883 by Colonel John May of May’s Brewery as a Drill Hall for K Company, 1st Hants Rifle Volunteers. It was the largest hall in town, 100 ft deep by 50 ft wide at the front, with a capacity of 250 dancing couples. In 1884 Colonel May also built the Masonic Hall next door, which had communicating doors to the Drill Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colonel May allowed the hall to be used for many public meetings, entertainments and dinners and for events like a grand “Reformation Times bazaar” under the auspices of London Street Congregational Church in 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1925 the theatrical entrepreneur Edwin George Casey opened the hall as the Pavilion dance hall and in 1937 he converted it to become the Plaza Theatre (a cinema).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this closed in 1955 it was taken over as the Co-operative Furnishing Store and later the Masonic Hall was incorporated into the store for hardware, both continuing in use until 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both buildings were pulled down when there were plans to make a roundabout, which never happened. The new building there is now the offices of Sovereign Kingfisher, who retained the foundation stone of the Masonic Hall in a garden feature.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 10:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20812 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ashwick Theatre, Dulverton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ashwick-theatre-dulverton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ashwick Theatre, also known as the Green Room or Music Room, was built by Yorkshire businessman Frank Green (d. 1953) in the grounds of Ashwick House. He was said to have moved to Ashwick House on medical advice to escape the polluted air of the industrial north. He was a wealthy bachelor who gave his house in York, the Treasurer’s House, to the National Trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He possibly missed the cultural life of York and so &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;.1930 he had a music room or theatre built. Frank Green’s relations and staff were entertained there. The timber-clad building had a tiled roof and stood on staddle stones near the drive. It had a stage and a green room and was decorated with paintings, most famously the trompe d&#039;oeil boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After falling into decay it was restored with new roof and cladding and is part of the Moorland Mousie Trust’s lease of Ashwick stables and grounds and not normally open to the public. The building can be seen from the outside when visiting the Exmor Pony centre.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2012 10:55:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20805 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Phyllis Court</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/phyllis-court</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The present-day Phyllis Court is a stuccoed, Italianate mansion house on Henley&#039;s northern edge, built in the early 1840s. Set amidst sloping lawns which sweep attractively down to the Thames, it has been an up-market country club since 1906.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the site itself is much older. Circumstantial evidence suggests that there may have been a small royal manor house or lodge here in the 12th century before the planned town of Henley was laid out, with grounds extending southwards into what is now Countess Gardens. From the 14th century there was a house here called Fillets Court, whose name was gradually corrupted to Phyllis Court - the name Fillets derives from an Old English name for hay, and may originally have referred to the nearby meadows. This was the manor house for a sizable medieval estate called Fillets, which was merged with Henley manor in the 1650s.   The ancient house continued in use until the 1780s, when most of it was demolished. Fifteenth- and 16th-century owners who lived there included members of the Marmion, Hales and Masham families, and in the early 17th century Sir John Miller, who served as sheriff of Oxfordshire (1633-4), and also owned Henley Park. James I&#039;s consort Anne of Denmark briefly stayed there in August 1604. From the 1650s to 1768 it was home to the Whitelocke family and their successor Gislingham Cooper, owners of Henley manor. In its last days it was leased to gentry and aristocracy, among them Elizabeth, Countess Grandison, whose son Viscount Villiers organised the famous Henley Gala Week of January 1777.   In the Civil War the house became a Parliamentarian garrison, and was fortified with earthworks, a moat, and a wooden draw bridge. For a time it was commanded by its owner Sir Bulstrode Whitelocke, a prominent (though moderate) Parliamentarian, who personally supervised the fortifications&#039; demolition in 1646 and re-landscaped the grounds. During the &#039;Glorious Revolution&#039; of 1688 (which ousted the Catholic King James II), Sir William Whitelocke welcomed the future William III to Phyllis Court on 13 December, where he was greeted by a deputation of peers, bishops and London aldermen.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 1861 the rebuilt house was leased to Hugh Mair, who entertained lavishly around Regatta time, when picnic parties frequently viewed the races from its lawns. It became a club in 1906, and by 1928 was &#039;one of the principal motoring and sports centres in the south of England&#039;, with aspirations to become &#039;the most luxurious and entertaining Club rendezvous outside London ... comparable with the best of the great Country Clubs of America and the East&#039;. The Phyllis Court Club still continues there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more&lt;/strong&gt; about Phyllis Court and the Fillets estate on the VCH Oxfordshire website. .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12579 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
