<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Wiltshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/wiltshire</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Codford&#039;s Domesday Reckoning</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/codfords-domesday-reckoning</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Domesday Book, the most famous record in England’s national archive, and one of the oldest, has been available in printed form since 1783. Here is a facsimile copy of the original manuscript entry for Codford St Mary, and beneath it the 1783 printed transcript of the same entry, which copies as faithfully as possible the form and abbreviations of the original. There have been four published editions of the Wiltshire portion of Domesday Book since 1783, and two are widely available in libraries, so researchers have no problem in finding out what it records for any Wiltshire community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 13:09:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20685 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Turnpike Trusts</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/turnpike-trusts</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two important turnpike trusts, based in Amesbury and Fisherton Anger (Salisbury), were authorised in 1761 to take responsibility for long stretches of major roads (including what are now known as the A36, A303 and A360), and both impinged on Codford. The Fisherton trust in 1761 turnpiked the Wylye valley road all the way from Salisbury, via Wilton and along Codford’s main street, to Heytesbury, where an earlier trust continued the route to Warminster. The Amesbury trust, as well as controlling the main Exeter road from near Andover to the hill above Mere, also turnpiked the road from Shrewton, through Chitterne, to Heytesbury, which crosses Codford’s downland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12705 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
