<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Sunderland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/sunderland</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Customs duties and the Sunderland coal trade</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/customs-duties-and-sunderland-coal-trade</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1700 Sunderland was &#039;noted for its sea coal trade&#039;, supplying a &#039;great quantity of coals&#039; and employing &#039;great numbers of ships yearly in carrying coals...&#039; Most was transported along the east and south coasts of England and some to Scotland.  Customs duties were collected on all coal shipped out of Sunderland, so quantities were recorded. Some of the lists survive, from which these graphs have been draw.  Even though incomplete and sometimes unclear, the graphs show a dramatic rise in total coal sales over the century, and a matching increase in overseas exports.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12667 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sunderland Wills and Inventories</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sunderland-wills-and-inventories</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost 500 wills and inventories, pertaining to Sunderland in the period 1549-1700, have now been identified and transcribed thanks to the sterling work of our Washington volunteers, led by John Smith. The probate records range across a broad section of local society – from the Hilton family at the top of the social scale down to labourers and poor widows at the lower end. As such this material provides a wealth of information regarding the occupations, living standards and communal and family relationships of the inhabitants of Sunderland during the period under consideration.   Most of the wills and inventories identified were proved in the Durham diocesan probate court, which had jurisdiction where the deceased’s entire estate fell within the diocese of Durham. The records of these are held in Durham University Library, Archives and Special Collections section. See the Library’s online probate project, North East Inheritance,  for further detailed information on these sources. In a small number of cases however, where the estate of the deceased encompassed more than one diocese, probate was granted in the Archdiocesan Prerogative courts of Canterbury or, on occasion, York. The probate records of the former are held in The National Archives and the latter in the Borthwick Institute, York.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12252 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Medieval Hendon</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/medieval-hendon</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The foreshore at Hendon where, acording to 14th century records, ships were moored.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12251 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>North Prospect of the town of Sunderland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/north-prospect-town-sunderland</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rteleft&quot;&gt;Samuel Buck&#039;s North Prospect of the Town of Sunderland, engraved about 1720, presents a lively and vivid image of the town and port and provides an insight into the development of the port and town of Sunderland from the late 16th to the early 18th centuries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12250 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Ballast Hills</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ballast-hills</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;  Disposing of sand ballast was a problem which grew with trade. At first, ships shed their ballast at the quays, before filling up with coals and salt. As vessels and commerce increased in volume, so too did harbour congestion, worsened all the while by the mountains of ballast. After a time, as access deteriorated for larger ships, keels and lighters had to carry sand from them to the quayside, and take coal out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12249 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The River Wear Commission</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/river-wear-commission</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1700 it was only too clear that a new approach towards the river and harbour was essential. The bishop, coal trade, quay-owners and an assortment of local and central government officials could not manage and police the bustling port with its shifting sands, illegal ballast dumping, poorly maintained wharves and lack of deep water.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12248 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Nonconformity In Sunderland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nonconformity-sunderland</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sunderland’s religious diversity, after the Restoration of the monarchy in 1660,  is illustrated by the presence a number of nonconformist  groups. These included  Baptists, Catholics and Quakers amongst others..&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12247 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A New Parish</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/new-parish</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the early 1700s the wealthy urban élite of Sunderland were complaining that  most pews in Bishopwearmouth were owned by local landowners. Well-placed seats in St Michael and All Angels were at a premium, valued so much that rights to them appeared in a marriage contract, that of Richard Richardson jun. of Sunderland and Thomasine Holmes in 1704. St Michael’s could accommodate only a quarter of parishioners. When Stockton was given a new parish in 1712, Sunderland was prompted to lobby for its own. An appeal for funds raised pledges of £1,000, and land on the town moor was allocated for Holy Trinity church and graveyard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12246 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Sunderland Quayside</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sunderland-quayside</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The changing face of the Sunderland quayside&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12245 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A Growing Town</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/growing-town</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;With some 6,00 or so people living around the mouth of the Wear in 1719, Sunderland now stood within the middle rank of English towns, although still much smaller than its near neighbour Newcastle. Within the borough, the population crowded around High Street and Low Street although the built-up area was expanding west to the Panns and southwards towards the Town Moor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12244 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
