<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Public</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/public</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Dummer Water Supply</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-water-supply</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dummer village benefitted from a clean and reliable water supply due to its location on chalk with clear springs and also from the generosity and innovation of the lord of the manor living in Dummer House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wells, standpipes and taps were situated in the two main streets for general use fed by a system of pipes leading from underground tanks. One well is of particular interest as it is protected by a Grade II Listed well house and contains a large treadwheel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately wells were dangerous places and there are two reports of children falling down the shafts and one of an adult who committed suicide by lowering himself into a well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed report on the Dummer water supply with photographs and maps, click the link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 15:53:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25651 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Campaign for Women’s Suffrage in Basingstoke: 1908-1914</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/campaign-women%E2%80%99s-suffrage-basingstoke-1908-1914</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the years leading up to the First World War the impact of the campaign for women’s suffrage was as evident in Basingstoke as in every other part of the country. The campaign aroused strong feelings on both sides of the argument as to whether or not women should be granted the right to vote in parliamentary elections. Moreover, amongst supporters there was a clear divide between the moderate suffragists of the National Union of Women’s Suffrage Societies (NUWSS) and the militant suffragettes of the Women’s Political and Social Union (WPSU). In the absence of opinion polls, it is difficult to judge the balance of views in Basingstoke or the extent to which residents engaged with the issue. What can be said is that few in the town, if any, could have been unaware of the campaign and the arguments advanced by supporters and opponents alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From November 1908, when a local branch of the NUWSS was established, until the outbreak of War there were frequent meetings, held in various locations, both indoors and outdoors, by both advocates and opponents. These were faithfully reported, often in considerable detail, in the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, national figures from both sides of the campaign were sometimes the principal speakers. Those advocating the cause of women’s suffrage included, in October 1910, Mrs Millicent Fawcett, the President of the NUWSS, and in November 1912, Miss Margaret Ashton, Manchester’s first female city councillor. Of the opponents, the most renowned were Miss Mary Angela Dickens (grand-daughter of Charles Dickens) of the Women’s National Anti-Suffrage League, who spoke in February 1909, and Leo Maxse, editor of the &lt;em&gt;National Review&lt;/em&gt;, in February 1911. Among the local leadership, who chaired and spoke at meetings, were Mrs Conran, Mrs Isabella Raynbird and Miss Dorothy Edwards. The last two were members of a deputation which met Arthur Clavell Salter, the Conservative MP for Basingstoke from 1906 to 1917, in July 1912. He can best be described as being moderately sympathetic towards the cause of women’s suffrage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main, it would seem that most local supporters of women’s suffrage were moderates. Indeed, the WPSU Newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Votes for Women&lt;/em&gt;, gives the impression that there were few suffragettes in the town. There are no reports of any ‘direct action’ in Basingstoke, such as seeking to blow up letter boxes, and only one incident of any notoriety. This occurred at an open air meeting held in the Market Place in the summer of 1911, at which the speaker was a leading suffragette, Mrs Leigh. While speaking ‘a boy, without any warning, threw a stone at her, hitting her on the head … Without an instant’s hesitation, Mrs Leigh leapt from the wagonette, caught the boy by the collar, held him until he humbly apologised before the crowd, released him, and was back in the wagonette finishing her last sentence before the astonished audience realised what a narrow escape she had had.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotation please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 09:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25625 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Census 1881</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-census-1881</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The whole of the 1881 census for Basingstoke parish has been transcribed by the New VCH Hampshire volunteers, based in the town. This information will be used for a detailed analysis of the population, households, age, occupations and migration etc. Because of the large number of inhabitants a complete spreadsheet is rather unwieldy so the data has been recorded on separate sheets, one for each of the 11 Districts enumerated. A link to the spreadsheet is below together with the enumerators’ descriptions of their walks around the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total number of people counted on 3rd April 1881 is 6,769 which can be compared with 4,262 residents recorded in 1851, also on line together with comments and analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-census-1851&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has to be remembered that this is just a snapshot of one night and many inhabitants may have been visitors, lodgers or even away from the town. Further work on the analysis of this data will be published in the future but it is interesting to note the inns (many of which are no longer in existence), employees in the clothing trade, iron foundry, breweries and railway but farmers and agricultural labourers are still evident presumably providing supplies to the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 13:08:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25588 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dummer War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wooden lychgate at the entrance to the church yard from the street was erected in 1919 as a memorial to the 13 men of the parish who lost their lives in the First World War. It was designed by Lady Emily Rycroft, second wife to Sir Richard Nelson who lived in the village from the time of his marriage in 1911 until his death in 1925.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The memorial was based on the style of a wooden porch at Boxford church in Suffolk. Although she was born in London to a military family, Lady Emily at one time lived at Edwardstone Hall (demolished in 1952), with her parents and siblings so would have known the nearby Boxford church well.[1] The timbers for the lychgate were donated by Robert Miller of Dummer Grange where an old barn was being demolished.[2] Wording on the cross beams reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To those fallen in the service of their country 1914-1918.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My flesh also shall rest in hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plaque bearing the names of eight men who lost their lives in the Second World War was later added as a memorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link below gives details of the men remembered on the WWI plaques displayed on the gate. No records have as yet been found for Frederick Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a roll of honour inside the church and a stone plaque remembering the dead of WW2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] 1901 Census; www.lostheritage.org.uk/houses (accessed 3 May 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] HRO, 65M72/PZ3 &lt;em&gt;Dummer parish magazine&lt;/em&gt; Jun. 1968.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 11:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25391 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Post Offices 1808-1971</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-post-offices-1808-1971</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first Post Office in Basingstoke was run by Robert Cottle, Chief Magistrate, from 1808. The Penny Post was introduced in 1840 which coincided with the arrival of the railway to the town. The postal service thus became accessible to the general public with regular collections and deliveries at an affordable price. On Cottle’s retirement the business transferred to premises in Wote Street and as the service grew, a bespoke building was erected in New Street in 1925.  This served as the town’s main Post Office until 1971 when a larger office was built in London Street and the sorting office transferred to Priestley Road in 1978.  (See the asset below for a full history.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 17:07:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25052 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Volunteer Fire Brigade</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-volunteer-fire-brigade</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The arrangements for fire-fighting in the town before the creation of Basingstoke Volunteer Fire Brigade are unclear. An inventory of the goods inside Basingstoke church taken by the churchwardens in May 1728, listed a fire engine with 16 buckets. Also potentially of use in fire-fighting was the “cradle for mending the tower” and two ladders. This indicates that the cost of purchasing and maintaining the engine might have been met from church rates. An account of a fire in the town later that year refers to “the playing of two Engines” and the use of firehooks. It is not clear whether the second engine was owned by the town, or by a Fire Insurance Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fire brigade was established in 1838 to serve Basingstoke and the surrounding villages. It was resolved that the engine would be sent to any parish in the vicinity of Basingstoke in the event of fire if the messenger brought a written undertaking signed by a responsible inhabitant of the parish confirming they would pay £2 for each engine required and all the expenses attending the conveyance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 19:07:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24929 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Street Lighting in Minehead and Dunster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/street-lighting-minehead-and-dunster</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We take street lighting for granted but it was slow to reach many parts of Britain and some communities have never had street lighting and do not desire it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the mid 19th century the area’s growing popularity with visitors, often from towns where street lighting was commonplace, probably fuelled demands for lighting in the area. One of the main reasons for creating the Minehead Gas Light and Coke Company in 1868 was to provide street lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minehead is fortunate is having many preserved early street lamp standards both gas and electric.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 10:22:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23045 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fires and Fire Engines in Minehead and Dunster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fires-and-fire-engines-minehead-and-dunster</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minehead suffered greatly from fires, mostly caused by reckless behaviour. The parish community maintained a fire engine and in the 1890s both Minehead and Dunster established local fire brigades.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 09:25:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22086 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Park Prewett Hospital, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/park-prewett-hospital-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Victorian Asylum to Psychiatric Hospital&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Park Prewett Hospital has an interesting history, initially planned as an overspill for the Victorian asylum Knowle Hospital in Fareham. It took several years to get going from its original idea in 1898, and then nearly ground to a halt in 1914 due to war-induced lack of resources, finance and manpower. However, the Army took over and the buildings were in use as a military hospital, with its own railway spur from the town, by 1916.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the wars Park Prewett reverted to a mental hospital, enhancing and expanding until it held 1,300 patients in 1939. Its rather elegant, Italianate red brick buildings somewhat belied the grim, institutional interiors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of WW2, all mental patients were evacuated and the hospital again reverted to war work for the duration. Facilities were established in London hospitals and the famous plastic surgeon, Sir Harold Gillies, moved into Rooksdown House, Basingstoke where he remained until 1952. The hospital was a big clearing-station for the Normandy landings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of Park Prewett then reflects the changes in mental health care, with new drugs and treatments, short-term and outpatient care, and eventually care in the community. By 1996 it had become obsolete, its campus became a conservation area, and it became the core of a new housing development, some of it using the old buildings themselves, including the iconic landmark Water Tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A timeline, pictures and references are attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 12:32:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21854 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Old Town Hall</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-old-town-hall</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From Mote Hall to Museum&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basingstoke’s Town Hall has had several re-incarnations in two locations over the centuries. It was originally on the west side of the Market Place, at the junction between Winchester Street and Church Street and was known sometimes as the Mote (or Moot) Hall, sometimes as the Market Hall or the Town Hall. After a disastrous fire in 1665, a more up-to-date Market Hall/Town Hall was built on the same site but this proved to be badly positioned once horse, cart and coach travel increased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1829 an Act was passed for enlarging the Market Place[1] and it was decided to demolish three properties on the north side so that a new Town Hall could be built there. Like the first building, it had an open ground floor, which was enclosed in 1865.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Queen Victoria’s Golden Jubilee in 1887 the mayor, John May, replaced the clock tower with a much bigger one, which many people regarded as a monstrosity. This was eventually taken down in 1961 for safety reasons.[2] The bells associated with the clock went to the demolition firm Brant’s at Tadley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1912 it became clear that more room was needed for Borough offices and the Council bought adjacent property, 3 Church Street, but that was still not enough. In 1921 they applied to the Ministry of Health for sanction to borrow £5,000 for the purchase and adaptation of Goldings House for municipal offices.[3] At the public enquiry one of the Councillors, who was also a trader living opposite the Town Hall, was reported as saying ‘that the noise on market days must make it almost impossible for the borough officials to carry on their work, and on other than market days the square was frequently filled with chars-a-bancs and there was a great deal of noise from them also.’[4]  The Town Clerk, Planning Department and other offices were moved to Goldings but the Town Hall remained the location for concerts, dances etc until a safety inspection revealed that the upper floor was not suitable  for such events. In 1981 the building was sold to Luff Building Ltd, to be renovated for possible office use and a mezzanine floor was inserted, but the developers regretted their purchase. In 1969, when the Library moved from the Mechanics Institute in New Street to the new Town Centre, leaving the Willis Museum on the upper floor, Luff arranged an exchange of buildings with the Council. Luff  took over the Mechanics Institute building and the Willis Museum moved into the old Town Hall, now having the opportunity to put on display the face and mechanism of the clock from John May’s clock tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1983 John Oliver wrote an article for a Workers’ Educational Association class (WEA), outlining the history and uses of the Town Hall up to and during the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1]  Hampshire Record Office (HRO) 148M71/1/5/3&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2]  &lt;em&gt;Hants &amp;amp; Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt; 27 October 1961, p 10&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[3]  HRO 50M63/B12/4 &lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[4]  &lt;em&gt;Hants &amp;amp; Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt; 27 June 1921 p 16&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:42:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21458 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
