<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/basingstoke</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Wesleyan Methodism in Basingstoke c1870 to 1939</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/wesleyan-methodism-basingstoke-c1870-1939</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;From putting down permanent roots in the 1870s until the outbreak of the Second World War, Wesleyan Methodists made a notable contribution to the religious life of Basingstoke. Throughout this period their principal place of worship was in Church Street, opposite the Parish Church of St Michaels. Their first chapel, dating from 1876, was moved to Cliddesden in the early 1900s and replaced by a much larger and more imposing edifice opened in 1905.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the lead church of the Basingstoke Wesleyan Methodist circuit, the Church Street congregation had the privilege of hearing the superintendent minister preach more frequently than those of the other churches. Ministers included the Revd William P. Ellis who in 1872 was appointed by the Wesleyan Conference as ‘the first home missionary’ in the town, where he served until 1876; the Revd Samuel Miles (1876-79) under whose ‘faithful labours the little cause became well rooted’; the Revd J. Robinson Cleminson (1884-87) ‘a prince of builders’ who oversaw substantial improvements to the chapel; the Revd Samuel Oliver (1890-93) whose ‘winning manners and courteous gentlemanly demeanour … made him easily accessible even to the humblest member of his flock’; the Revd Harold Chapman (1903-08) ‘a cultured and devoted minister’, who had the privilege of being in post when the new church was opened;  the Revd Walter Barnes (1912-15) for the ‘strong leadership he provided’; the Revd James Ash Parsons (1927-31) ‘a fine example of muscular Christianity’; and the Revd Walter Weddell (1936-44) remembered for his ‘kindness, sympathy, cheerfulness and manliness.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wesleyans were also fortunate in having some long-serving and committed laymen such as Edward Kynaston, who served as Sunday School Superintendent for many years in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, and William Higgs, the Circuit Chapel Secretary during the same period. They enabled the Church to support a wide variety of affiliated organisations, such as a thriving Sunday school; from 1897, a branch of the Wesley Guild; for a number of years in the late 1870s/early 1880s, a Mutual Improvement Association; and for women a Ladies Sewing Party/Meeting and Women’s Bright Hour. These together with the regular services and those for special occasions and many ad hoc activities, including support for both home and overseas missions, offered both social and spiritual sustenance to many residents of Basingstoke. While major fund raising events provided a welcome diversion from the routine of everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;April 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 17:15:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25706 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Engagement of Churches in Social Welfare and Related Provision in Edwardian Basingstoke - 1903</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/engagement-churches-social-welfare-and-related-provision-edwardian-basingstoke-1903</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to the emergence of the Welfare State, churches made a valuable and valued contribution to social welfare provision either alone or collaboratively. In prioritising the needs of others, churches were seeking to give practical expression to Christ’s injunction to ‘love your neighbour as yourself.’ By the Edwardian era this had become formalised in the concept of ‘the social gospel’ with adherents claiming that ‘good works’ were as legitimate a pursuit for the churches as the saving of souls. Drawing upon examples from Edwardian Basingstoke during a single year, 1903, three main forms of church engagement in social welfare can be identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there was the sponsorship of slate clubs, which were essentially savings/insurance schemes to assist members in times of financial need, such as sickness. Here a good example was the club sponsored by London Street Congregational Church’s Pleasant Sunday Afternoon Society. Established in 1901, 366 members joined the club during 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, there was fund raising for good causes. In January, a two day bazaar and entertainment was organised by the Young Helper’s League to raise funds in ‘support of a “Basingstoke Cot” ’ at the Stepney Causeway homes of Dr Barnardo. A second example, was a concert given by the members of the Bethesda Male Voice Choir in May. This was a cross-denominational initiative, with the aim being to raise funds to ameliorate the suffering of the Penrhyn Quarrymen, who were on strike, and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, there were various kinds of what may be loosely described as ‘direct action’. One involved the establishment of a Lads Institute prompted by what was seen as a duty to provide ‘some form of attractive and healthy recreation, combined with a modicum of useful instruction, for the lads who … [spent] their spare time in the streets for want of a better place.’ Another was the extensive support given to the cause of temperance seen as a means of alleviating the social distress resulting from the excessive consumption of alcohol. This took a variety of forms, such as campaigning to ban the opening of public houses on Sundays and to reduce the number of licensed premises in the town, and facilitating the work of temperance organisations, such as the Women of the White Ribbon, the Band of Hope, the Total Abstinence Union and the British Women’s Temperance Association. On a smaller scale, following a flower service at the Congregational Church in July, the children’s offerings were ‘sent to the Cottage Hospital, the almshouses, and to the Flower Mission.’ Similarly at Harvest time the Cottage Hospital received gifts of flowers, fruit, vegetables and cash from a wide variety of churches in the neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As these examples illustrate, without the involvement of churches, life in Edwardian Basingstoke for those disadvantaged and or in need would have been poorer. By giving attention to ‘good works’, church members sought to make a difference and although on issues, such as temperance, there would have been strongly held differences of view within the community, at the very least churches were motivated by a desire to ensure that spending on alcohol was not at the expense of the wellbeing of family members, particularly women and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 16:12:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25702 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>‘Basingstoke Churches and the People’</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/%E2%80%98basingstoke-churches-and-people%E2%80%99</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The title of this item is taken from the headline of reports which appeared in the 21 March and 4 April 1903 editions of the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. In the first the findings of a census of churchgoing undertaken in Basingstoke by the newspaper were presented. While in the second the results were compared with those from a earlier census carried out in 1882, with attention being drawn to the fact that in the 21 years between them the population of Basingstoke had gone up by 43.5 percent, while the increases in attendance at places of worship in the morning and evening were only 1.9 percent and 14.5 percent respectively. The observation was also made that ‘of all the denominations in the town’, it was the Established Church that ‘had made the greatest advance.’ Nevertheless, the censuses did show that at the time they were undertaken many denominations were represented in the ecclesiastical landscape of Basingstoke, thereby contributing to the diversity and richness of the religious heritage of the town. The results of the two censuses, together with those of the 1851 national religious census, provide historians with valuable insights into the relative strength of the churches both collectively and individually during the second half of the nineteenth century and the early years of the twentieth. It is a great pity that similar surveys were not undertaken in subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For full details of the censuses please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill, March 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 16:02:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25698 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The day the vicar locked the council out of the parish church of Basingstoke.</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/day-vicar-locked-council-out-parish-church-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Basingstoke made headlines in the national and provincial press in 1907 when the vicar of Basingstoke, Revd Boustead, sent an intemperate letter to the town clerk. He told the clerk that the Mayor and Corporation and the police, fire brigade and other public and voluntary bodies would not be welcome to hold the annual Civic Service in the Parish Church if they intended, in line with tradition, to hold a similar service in one of the nonconformist churches. He said that such an action would, ‘degrade God’s Church to the level of one of the 350 man-made sects’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revd Boustead’s letter was reprinted with a brief introduction in dozens of provincial newspapers from the &lt;em&gt;Cornishman&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Aberdeen Press and Journal&lt;/em&gt; under various headlines, including ‘Strange Situation at Basingstoke’, ‘Mockery of Religion’, ‘Not wanted at Church’ and ‘Another Clerical Bigot’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mayor decided not to hold the Civic Service in the Parish Church. However, the following year he decided that the custom of the Civic Service should continue, but when the procession reached the church, the vicar had locked the church door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the full story, please see the attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 12:16:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25681 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Baptists in Basingstoke: c.1867 to 1939</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/baptists-basingstoke-c1867-1939</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were no Baptist causes in Basingstoke recorded in the religious census of 1851. Sixty years later, however, there were two - a Strict (also known as Ebenezer and Particular) Baptist dating from about 1867 and an Open Baptist from 1908. The Strict Baptists had a chapel in Church Street and one of their leading members was Thomas Burberry, the founder of what has become a global brand in the fashion industry. It is not known precisely when the Strict Baptist cause came to an end but the chapel was sold to the Basingstoke branch of the Post-War Brotherhood Movement in 1936 and the building was renamed Brotherhood Hall (later ‘Moose Hall’, ‘one of the local halls for meetings, dances, wedding receptions and other activities’).                                                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Open Baptist cause principally owed its establishment to the efforts of the Revd Alfred Bird an evangelist from Whitchurch who, with assistance from the Southern Baptist Association, guided the fledgling Church during the first couple of years of its existence. For its premises the cause acquired the old British School buildings on Sarum Hill, which were converted into a place of worship. In addition, a number of the institutional markers of church life, such as a Sunday school, women’s group and Christian Endeavour Society were soon established. The Church also formed a close bond with the other major Nonconformist denominations in the town. Served by a succession of diligent ministers the cause thrived during the War years and into the 1920s and 30s. As well as leading and guiding the Church, some ministers were active in other spheres of community life. For example, the Revd Frederick West (1910-12) was a supporter of the cause of women’s suffrage; the Revd Sydney Wing (1925-32), served as a borough councillor from 1926 to 1930, topping the poll on both occasions when he sought the support of the electors; and, following the outbreak of the Second World War, the Revd John Hill (1935-39) resigned in December 1939 to begin a ‘new life as a medical orderly in the R.A.M.C. [Royal Army Medical Corps].’ As the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt; observed Hill’s ‘action must arouse the keenest admiration of the townsfolk.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point during the 1930s the Church ‘severed its connection’ with the Baptist Union, the Hants Baptist Association and the Baptist Missionary Society and affiliated instead to the Fellowship of Independent Evangelical Churches. However, it continued to be known as “Sarum Hill Baptist Church”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25669 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Primitive Methodism in Basingstoke c.1830 to 1932/9</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/primitive-methodism-basingstoke-c1830-19329</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the Methodist Re-Union in 1932, the Primitive Methodists remained a distinctive feature of Basingstoke’s ecclesiastical landscape. They did, however, enjoy good relations, and collaborated closely, with the other Nonconformist denominations in the town. Indeed, their ministers were often described as brotherly and served not only their church and circuit but also the wider community. They included the Revd Charles Portnell (1868-70 and 1883-6), whose ‘preaching was plain but forceful’; the Revd Henry Yeates (1869-73), who ‘was especially gifted to stir and edify a congregation’ and later returned to Basingstoke, serving as a borough councillor from 1884 to 1887; the Revd Joseph Beal (1898-04), who ‘in his six years at Basingstoke … preached over four hundred and fifty sermons and retained his reputation for freshness’ and also superintended the erection of the new church; and  the Revd Ezra Ramm (1928-33), ‘a man sent from God, as a preacher fearless and true’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In leading their church and circuit, these ministers needed the support and encouragement of a large number of lay people, who performed most of the key roles in the organisations that the church sponsored. From Sunday schools to a flourishing Christian Endeavour society; from brass bands to the choir; and from women’s groups to a Peoples’ Pleasant Hour, such organisations cemented the loyalty of members and served as a means of reaching out to those unattached to any church. Indeed, evangelism was the &lt;em&gt;leitmotif&lt;/em&gt; running through much of the life of the Church. Its anniversary celebrations, missions, camp meetings and concerts and entertainments served the dual role of affording opportunities for fellowship amongst church members and affiliates and for drawing in the outsider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 1938 the Church (since the Methodist Re-Union in 1932, simply Sarum Hill Methodist Church) hosted the civic service, a particularly significant event since it ‘was the first occasion on which a member of the … Church, … [had] attended as mayor.’ Also present at the service were all the other civic dignitaries as well as representatives of the Territorials, Fire Brigade and Police. The minister, the Revd Harold Pope, preached on a verse from Revelation, Chapter 21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I, John, saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service was clearly indicative of the extent to which what had originally been a religious group that aroused hostility had now become part of the socio-cultural establishment of the town. In the process, however, it could be argued that it had lost something of the ‘spiritual cutting edge’ that had previously characterised Primitive Methodism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 11:37:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25661 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Christian Endeavour in Basingstoke c.1893-1939</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/christian-endeavour-basingstoke-c1893-1939</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In seeking to find an effective means of bridging the gap between their Sunday schools and full church membership, from the 1890s onwards many of Basingstoke’s Free Churches established a Young People’s Society of Christian Endeavour (YPSCE). Having been founded in 1881 by the Revd Francis Edward Clark, the minister of Williston Congregational Church in the state of Maine, the innovation quickly spread. By the last decade of the 19th century it had been adopted in many countries including Great Britain where it was reported, in November 1894, that 1860 Societies had already been established. The aims of YPSCE were spelt out its founding constitution as: “To promote an earnest Christian life among its members, to increase their mutual acquaintance, and to make them more useful in the service of God.” These clearly resonated with a large number of church leaders who saw in YPSCE a way of harnessing the idealism, enthusiasm and commitment of the young in the service of the Church. In pursuing these aims, there was a very heavy emphasis on young people pledging themselves to follow Christ’s example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of Basingstoke’s Free Churches to establish a YPSCE was London Street Congregational Church in November 1893, with Immanuel Church (Countess of Huntingdon’s Connexion) following suit in January 1895. By the end of the century the Primitive Methodists had also started a Society and the Wesleyans had set up their equivalent, a Wesley Guild. In the early years, the anniversary celebrations of these Societies, at which there were frequently challenging addresses delivered by visiting speakers, were faithfully reported in the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. A notable characteristic of such Societies was their desire to forge close links with each other in order to encourage and to share ideas. Such networking was formalised in late 1897 with the setting up of the Basingstoke and District Christian Endeavour Union, which, in addition to the Basingstoke Societies, included those from Andover, Whitchurch, Overton, Odiham and Fleet. Consequently, by 1900 YPSCE had established firm foundations in Basingstoke and the surrounding area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of progress the years leading up the First World War were, in many respects, the most productive. Initiatives included providing meals and entertainments for the elderly; organising an Eisteddfod; and fund raising for good causes. Moreover, new Societies were established at the Working Men’s Mission in George Street and the new Baptist Church on Sarum Hill. There were, however, various concerns regarding the resilience of YPSCE, such as its ability to attract and energise young people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the War, Societies continued to promote what can best be described as ‘practical Christianity’. Although a number closed or were replaced with other provision for young people, the Primitive Methodist and Baptist societies, as well as the Wesley Guild, were still in existence in 1939. Looking back over the previous 30 to 40 years, there can be little doubt that Christian Endeavourers made their mark both within their churches and the wider community. As it was put by Mr J.B. Holmes the speaker at London Street’s seventeenth anniversary in 1910: ‘He believed in the Christian Endeavour Society because it recognised the young life in … [the] churches and gave them their opportunity of witnessing for Jesus Christ; and next because it did not despise their humble efforts … which perhaps most people looked down upon … [but] were accepted and blessed by Jesus Christ.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the sources of the quotes, please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 12:27:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25654 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Housekeeper, Public Servant and Suffragist: The Productive Life of Mrs Isabella Raynbird (nee Webb) of Basingstoke 1837 -1925</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/housekeeper-public-servant-and-suffragist-productive-life-mrs-isabella-raynbird-nee-webb</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of her death, Isabella Raynbird was praised as somebody who ‘took a keen interest in everything for the good of the parish in which she lived, and, always ready to help any in need, she was greatly beloved by all’.* Such compliments were undoubtedly justified since she had lived a very full and productive life of 87 years. Born in Mapledurwell, her father was a prosperous farmer and Isabella undoubtedly experienced a relatively privileged upbringing. During her childhood and adolescence, she also became familiar with a farming way of life. Thus, unsurprisingly, for many years she was ‘housekeeper’ to Samuel Sparshatt, who farmed in the parish of Weston Patrick. Following his death in 1884 Isabella inherited not only his farming responsibilities but also his public service role of churchwarden and parish overseer, which she retained until her death. In 1890, at the age of 52, Isabella married widower Hugh Edward Raynbird, who was steward to Lord Bolton of Hackwood Park and head of the auctioneering firm, Raynbird and Son. Following her marriage she moved to Old Basing and from 1898 to 1922 served as one of the parish’s two poor law guardians, at a time when most members of boards of guardians were male. As a guardian, Isabella’s particular interests included the welfare and education of Workhouse children and staffing matters. She also attended a number of poor law conferences in Winchester and London. Throughout, she demonstrated her competence in what was, in part at least, a political role, thereby strengthening the case for the increased involvement of women in the public realm. This was also reflected in her support for those campaigning for women’s suffrage. She identified, however, with the moderate suffragists as opposed to the militant suffragettes. After some initial reluctance, in 1910 Isabella accepted the chairmanship/presidency of the Basingstoke and District Women’s Suffrage Society. In promoting the cause, she spoke at, and chaired, meetings and was a member of a deputation which met with the local MP in 1912 to secure his support. Some of Isabella’s intellectual interests, which she shared with her husband, were pursued through membership of the Hampshire Field Club and Archaeological Society. Looked at in the round, her life exemplified the increasing self-confidence of women as the 19th century gave way to the twentieth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite an extensive search, no photographs of Isabella have been found. Consequently it has been necessary to use an image of her husband to illustrate this item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For the source of the quotation, please see the PDF link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 17:29:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25648 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Probate Material 1691-1700</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-probate-material-1691-1700</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this period the probate documents of 18 inhabitants of Basingstoke have been selected to reflect the range of occupations in the town, some show the move to brewing following the decline of the cloth industry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 wills and 11 inventories have been transcribed by the Wills Group of the New Victoria County of Hampshire project based in Basingstoke. These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by Hampshire Record Office and The National Archives. Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links to the documents are below and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;glossary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/inventory-john-browne-victualler-1691&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John  Browne, victualler (Inventory), 1691&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-inventory-and-renunciation-john-wareham-bricklayer-1691&quot;&gt;John Wareham, bricklayer (Will, Inventory and Renunciation), 1691&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-william-hall-clerk-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Hall, clerk (Will and Inventory), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-henry-stone-gunsmith-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Henry Stone, gunsmith (Will and Inventory), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-richard-watmorewattmore-clothier-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Wattmore/Watmore, clothier (Will and Inventory), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-samuel-astin-tanner-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Samuel Astin, tanner (Will), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/inventory-richard-knight-yeoman-1693&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Knight, yeoman (Inventory), 1693&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-richard-jeyes-yeoman-1693-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Jeyes, yeoman (Will and Inventory), 1693&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-bourneborne-scrivener-1694&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Bourne/Borne, scrivener (Will), 1694&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-box-innholder-1694&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Box, innholder (Will), 1694&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/renunciation-and-inventory-joseph-windover-collarmaker-1694&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joseph Windover, collarmaker (Renunciation and Inventory), 1694&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-edmund-cowdry-collarmaker-1695&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edmund Cowdry, collarmaker (Will and Inventory), 1695&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-thomas-edwards-tanner-1696&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas Edwards, tanner (Will and Inventory), 1696&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-rogers-clerk-1696&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Rogers, clerk (Will), 1696&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-michaell-acton-clerk-1697&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michaell Acton, clerk (Will), 1697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-joseph-mooreing-gentleman-1698&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joseph Mooreing, gentleman (Will), 1697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-robert-lancaster-glover-1699&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Lancaster, glover (Will and Inventory), 1699&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-spencer-clothier-1699&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Spencer, clothier (Will), 1699&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 12:58:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25628 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Campaign for Women’s Suffrage in Basingstoke: 1908-1914</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/campaign-women%E2%80%99s-suffrage-basingstoke-1908-1914</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the years leading up to the First World War the impact of the campaign for women’s suffrage was as evident in Basingstoke as in every other part of the country. The campaign aroused strong feelings on both sides of the argument as to whether or not women should be granted the right to vote in parliamentary elections. Moreover, amongst supporters there was a clear divide between the moderate suffragists of the National Union of Women’s Suffrage Societies (NUWSS) and the militant suffragettes of the Women’s Political and Social Union (WPSU). In the absence of opinion polls, it is difficult to judge the balance of views in Basingstoke or the extent to which residents engaged with the issue. What can be said is that few in the town, if any, could have been unaware of the campaign and the arguments advanced by supporters and opponents alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From November 1908, when a local branch of the NUWSS was established, until the outbreak of War there were frequent meetings, held in various locations, both indoors and outdoors, by both advocates and opponents. These were faithfully reported, often in considerable detail, in the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, national figures from both sides of the campaign were sometimes the principal speakers. Those advocating the cause of women’s suffrage included, in October 1910, Mrs Millicent Fawcett, the President of the NUWSS, and in November 1912, Miss Margaret Ashton, Manchester’s first female city councillor. Of the opponents, the most renowned were Miss Mary Angela Dickens (grand-daughter of Charles Dickens) of the Women’s National Anti-Suffrage League, who spoke in February 1909, and Leo Maxse, editor of the &lt;em&gt;National Review&lt;/em&gt;, in February 1911. Among the local leadership, who chaired and spoke at meetings, were Mrs Conran, Mrs Isabella Raynbird and Miss Dorothy Edwards. The last two were members of a deputation which met Arthur Clavell Salter, the Conservative MP for Basingstoke from 1906 to 1917, in July 1912. He can best be described as being moderately sympathetic towards the cause of women’s suffrage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main, it would seem that most local supporters of women’s suffrage were moderates. Indeed, the WPSU Newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Votes for Women&lt;/em&gt;, gives the impression that there were few suffragettes in the town. There are no reports of any ‘direct action’ in Basingstoke, such as seeking to blow up letter boxes, and only one incident of any notoriety. This occurred at an open air meeting held in the Market Place in the summer of 1911, at which the speaker was a leading suffragette, Mrs Leigh. While speaking ‘a boy, without any warning, threw a stone at her, hitting her on the head … Without an instant’s hesitation, Mrs Leigh leapt from the wagonette, caught the boy by the collar, held him until he humbly apologised before the crowd, released him, and was back in the wagonette finishing her last sentence before the astonished audience realised what a narrow escape she had had.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotation please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 09:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25625 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
