<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Woodland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/woodland</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Newtown Linford probate records, 1700-1750</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newtown-linford-probate-records-1700-1750</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Newtown Linford is a small village to the north west of Leicester, on the edge of Charnwood Forest. It is one of several villages being studies as part of the Leicestershire VCH &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/leicestershire/news/charnwood-roots-%E2%80%93-volunteers-needed&quot;&gt;Charnwood Roots &lt;/a&gt;project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newtown-linford-probate-records-1621-40&quot;&gt;Newtown Linford probate records, 1621-40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 11:36:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22720 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bishop&#039;s Cleeve: sale of the manor by James I, 1604</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bishops-cleeve-sale-manor-james-i-1604</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1604, James I disposed of the manor of Bishop&#039;s Cleeve, which had been held by the Crown since the dissolution, to two London merchants, Peter Vanloore and William Blake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Vanloore&#039;s career is detailed in the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography. In brief, he was a Utrecht-born merchant, long resident in London, who appears to have made most of his fortune supplying expensive jewellery to the Court of Elizabeth I. He invested in property in many counties, the Cleeve purchase being one such. He was knighted in 1623, and died in 1627.]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 18:24:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21385 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rentals of rectory lands of Cheltenham and Charlton Kings</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rentals-rectory-lands-cheltenham-and-charlton-kings</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the 17th century, the rectory lands and tithes of Cheltenham and the associated &#039;chapel&#039; of Charlton Kings descended from Sir Baptist Hicks of Chipping Campden through his younger daughter and eventually to the Essex family, with whom they remained until sold to the developer Joseph Pitt in the late 18th century. Three rentals are known to survive, one in Essex papers preserved at Gloucestershire Archives, and two in the Hertfordshire Record Office.  (The Hicks/Capel/Essex families held many lands in Gloucestershire; their descent is detailed in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=66393&quot;&gt;VCH Glos Vol 8 section on Tewkesbury manors and estates&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 05 Aug 2012 13:51:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20972 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Coppicing at Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/coppicing-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The very best oak building timber at the end of the 16th century came from woods which were specifically managed to produce tall, straight trees for posts, beams, and rafters. Such oaks, known as ‘standards’, were grown in the company of species such as hazel which were cut almost to the ground on a regular, cyclical basis and used for necessities such as fuel and fencing. This system of regular cutting is known as coppicing. It not only ensures an almost constant supply of wood which can be harvested again and again as soon as it reaches an appropriate size, but also provides the perfect environment for growing trees suitable for building timber. Between harvests, the coppiced wood grows rapidly — as anyone who has pruned a young tree or shrub will know. The dense new growth forces the young standard timber trees to grow more swiftly than they would in the open, as they are competing for light. The oaks form a crown high above the level of the coppice, unable to throw out lower branches because of the surrounding undergrowth, so lessening the risk of knots which can weaken structural timbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; [i]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[i] O. Rackham, Trees and Woodland in the British Landscape (London, 1976), 8.(Image courtesy of the Woodland Trust Picture Library) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12618 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Downs above Upper Halling</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/downs-above-upper-halling</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Downs above Upper Halling, looking south.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upper Halling is one of the small villages that makes up the Medway Valley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mission room was built in Upper Halling to serve the rising population in Halling, which had risen to around 2,100 in 1871, according to vicar F.Goldsmith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hop cultivation, in the late 19th century, left an indelible mark on the local landscape, most recognisable by the round oasthouses that are scattered not only around Upper Halling, but also across the whole of the Medway Valley.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12380 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Frith Wood</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/frith-wood</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Frith Wood is a 75 hectare wood, owned and managed by the Forestry Commission. It lies just to the north of Ledbury, occupying a roughly north-east/south-west aligned limestone ridge on the western edge of the Malvern Hills Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty. The wood is almost 2km long and 300m wide. The highest point of Frith Wood, called Bradlow Knoll, is 260m above Ordnance Datum (OD).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wood can probably be identified with the wood &#039;half a league by a half&#039; mentioned in the Domesday survey (1086). Long before that time, and up to the present day, the woodland has provided a variety of resources for the inhabtants of Ledbury. Now managed by the Forestry Commission, it is still a productive woodland. It also a great recreational area, its many paths allowing the exploration of the flora, fauna and history of the area.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the early months of 2008 Frith Wood was the subject of  a project which brought together many local groups interested in the geological, natural and human history of the woodland. We are grateful to the Malvern Hills Area of Outstanding Natural Beauty (AONB) Partnership for funding provided by their Sustainable Development Fund, and to the Forestry Commission for access to the woods. Archaeologists from Herefordshire Council&#039;s Archaeology Unit led EPE volunteers in an excercise to record a number of features in the wood. These included a medieval wood-bank and a charcoal-birning platform. The Herefordshire and Worcestershire Earth Heritage Trust and The Ledbury Naturalists&#039; Club provided material on the geology and widlife of the area. Drawing on the knowledge of the tracks  of local resident Steve Clegg a guided walk through the wood has been devised, which takes in some of the most important features. The accompanying booklet was distributed freely in Ledbury and is now available as a pdf file here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12299 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Geology and Landscape of the Bolsover area</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/geology-and-landscape-bolsover-area</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this section on overview of the geology and landscape of Bolsover area is given.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12117 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
