<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Person</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/person-0</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Robbins&#039; Reminiscences - Transcription of a notebook about life in Launceston in the early nineteenth century.</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/robbins-reminiscences-transcription-notebook-about-life-launceston-early-nineteenth-century</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Robbins was a bootmaker, who played an active role in Launceston during the course of the century.  One of his sons, Sir Alfred Robbins, a prominent journalist and freemason, published a history of Launceston, ‘Launceston Past and Present’ in 1888.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this notebook, written in 1895,  Richard Robbins jots down his memories of life in Launceston when he was young, thinking, one imagines, that the information might be useful to future historians.  His lists of tradesmen and professional people, with anecdotes about individuals, about working conditions, about activities in the town, provide a lively picture of everyday life in Launceston.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text preserves Robbins somewhat idiosyncratic orthography.  Some corrections have been made to the punctuation, to assist understanding of the text.  The text is shown in roman type; brief explanatory notes appear in italics within square brackets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An illustrated edition of the text with introduction and annotations is available from the Lawrence House Museum, 9 Castle Street, Launceston, PL15 8BA, telephone 01566 773277.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© Friends of Lawrence House Museum&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 10:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AliceI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23176 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Newnham Probate Material, 1561-80</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newnham-probate-material-1561-80</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is only one surviving will with inventory for this period. The relationship, if any, between Denes, who died in 1572 and Robert Lyde (d. 1541) is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This transcription has been made from a copy of the original probate document supplied by HRO.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-denes-lyde-widow-1572&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Denes Lyde, widow, will and inventory, 1572&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 11:20:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23027 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Newnham Probate Material 1541-60</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newnham-probate-material-1541-60</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Six wills and three inventories survive for this period. Newnham was a mixed farming village in this period and all worked on the land.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three members of the important Fielder family died in this period: father, mother and son.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-thomas-fielderfylder-1541&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas Fielder/Fylder, will, 1541&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-hookerhokar-1541&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Hooker/Hokar, will, 1541&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-robert-lyde-1541&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Lyde, will, 1541&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-elizabeth-fielderfylder-1549&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Elizabeth Fielder/Fylder, will and inventory, 1549&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-john-fielderfylder-1557&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Fielder/Flyder, will and inventory, 1557&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-thomas-stephens-1558&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas Stephens, will and inventory, 1558&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2014 10:45:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23019 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Up Nately and Andwell Probate Material 1561-80</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nately-and-andwell-probate-material-1561-80</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Only two wills survive from this period: one of a wealthy widow from Andwell mill and the other of the poor curate of the chapelry of Up Nately, whose inventory was valued at £2 7s. 2d. in 1572.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links to the wills and inventories are below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-john-turner-curate-nately-1572&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Turner, curate of Up Nately, 1572 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-alice-milton-andwell-widow-1573&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alice Milton, widow, Andwell, 1573 (Will)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 27 Sep 2013 11:05:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22153 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Richard Phelps (1718-85)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/richard-phelps-1718-85</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Phelps is little known today but was a prolific portrait painter and a designer of follies in West Somerset. He came from a very modest background but when he died was worth c.£1,500 and left 260 prints, 50 oil paintings, 80 drawings and sketches of his own and nine waste canvases, gold rings, silver plate and a quantity of walnut and mahogany furniture.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2013 11:03:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21908 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Yankee Jack</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/yankee-jack</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watchet’s seamen included many characters of whom the fictional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ancient-mariner&quot;&gt;Ancient Mariner&lt;/a&gt; is the most well known but Yankee Jack was a real mariner called John Short. His wonderful singing voice and amazing vocal memory, even as an old man, impressed Cecil Sharp. Thanks to Yankee Jack many of our best loved sea songs were published and preserved including versions of &lt;em&gt;Shallow Brown&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Shenandoah&lt;/em&gt;. He was one of the last of the shantymen who sang for his fellow sailors giving them the rhythms for turning the capstan and hoisting sails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about Watchet harbour in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=117145&amp;amp;strquery=watchet%20harbour#s1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Victoria County History of Somerset V&lt;/a&gt; and see local boats at the Watchet Boat Museum just a short walk from Yankee Jack&#039;s statue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:19:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21862 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Piran</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-piran</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;St Piran is a typical example of a legendary Cornish saint. His name is first recorded in 960 at Perranzabuloe, a name that means ‘Piran in the sand’, where the church was later believed to contain his bones. In the 12th or 13th century a Life of him was written in Latin for the church or for Exeter Cathedral, to which it belonged. The author of Life believed that Piran was identical with a similarly named Irish saint, St Ciáran, so he took Ciáran’s Life and made it the basis of Piran’s. He stated that Piran was a saint from Ireland who became a bishop, eventually sailed to Cornwall, made his home there, did many miracles, and died on 5 March.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 07:06:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20689 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Codford census returns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/codford-census-returns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The census returns tell us agreat deal about the people of Codford in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 15:53:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20670 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Jane Austen at Steventon</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/jane-austen-steventon</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jane Austen was born at Steventon rectory in 1775. Her father, George, had been given the Steventon living by his wealthy cousin, Thomas Knight, in 1761. George Austen moved from Oxford to Steventon in 1764 following his marriage to Cassandra, née Leigh. For four years the family lived in the rectory of neighbouring Deane while repairing and extending the dilapidated Steventon rectory. They had been living in Steventon rectory for some years before Jane was born. Her father took in boarders whom he educated for university. Jane and her sister, Cassandra, were encouraged in their literary pursuits by their educated parents. Juvenile stories, plays for the family gatherings and even a history of England survive today. Jane’s first three novels: &lt;em&gt;Sense and Sensibility&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pride and Prejudice &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Northanger Abbey &lt;/em&gt;were drafted in Steventon, before she moved away in 1801. A contemporary newspaper lists some of the effects to be auctioned including a piano, a quantity of music, 200 books and sets of theatrical scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane socialised within north Hampshire society attending balls at Hurstbourne Park. She would visit the Leighs and Knights, meet the Leigh-Perrots in Bath and stay locally with people like the Chutes at the Vyne in Sherborne St John, just outside Basingstoke. She attended dances in the Basingstoke Assembly Rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane and Cassandra were encouraged to visit the homes of Steventon villagers. Jane became godmother to one of the Littleworth children. Nanny Littleworth had been wet-nurse to George and Cassandra’s children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1820 the rectory and surrounding cottages were badly flooded leading to the building of a new rectory in 1823 and the relocation of the cottages to a new site. The relocation of cottages had started in Jane’s lifetime but the flood of January 1820 which devastated the rectory as well as the remaining cottages further down the valley caused the final abandonment of the old village site. A new rectory was built and today Jane’s memory is mainly preserved in the church up the lane from the old rectory site where her father, brother and nephew served as rector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2011 10:45:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20496 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Thomas Read Kemp, Landowner and Developer</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thomas-read-kemp-landowner-and-developer</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Read Kemp (1782-1844) inherited land in the parish of Brighton from his father in 1811.  By this time, Brighton had been a flourishing seaside resort for around sixty years, thus starting well before the arrival of George, Prince of Wales who is often wrongly said to be the founder of the town&#039;s transformation from a declining coastal town into a resort. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Read Kemp&#039;s political interests were in Lewes which he represented as an MP for some time but he knew that his land in Brighton should be a good source of income if it was developed. Most of it was intermingled with others and he slowly began to untangle this to ensure that he obtained blocks of freehold land. His first project was villas in Montpelier, an area which today is known for its distinctive albeit later style. His second, villas along the London Road and his third, Kemp Town which was first mentioned in the local press in 1822 when he began to employ workmen to lay it out to the scheme published as by C.A. Busby and A.H. Wilds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All did not proceed smoothly partly due to the recession which hit this resort in the later 1820s but also to the competition which included not only Brunswick Town but other projects dotted about the resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kemp understood the value of publicity and helped many local ventures, some by giving land. He also had important backers. His first wife was Frances Baring, the fourth daughter of Sir Francis Baring who founded Barings Bank.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to some local claims, Kemp did not die poor nor was he a bankrupt. Both are myths. To read more see Sue Berry  Thomas Read Kemp and the shaping of Regency Brighton c.1818-1845 in the Journal of the Georgian Group Volume XVII (2009) 125-140.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 18:17:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20381 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
