<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Group</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/group</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>St Thomas&#039; Home for the Friendless and Fallen, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-thomas-home-friendless-and-fallen-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2019 St Thomas’ Care Home in Darlington Road, Basingstoke was a dementia care home. St Thomas&#039; has an interesting history as a centre for caring for the less fortunate of the county. In January 1863 the Bishop of Winchester gave his approval to Admiral Ryder’s idea to establish a home for women whose lives were ruined by prostitution or abuse by providing them with work as laundresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1930 OS map calls St Thomas’ the Mount Tabor Certified Institution which was a different kind of home, sheltering people under the terms of the 1913 Mental Deficiency Act. In 1951 St Thomas’ got its old name back as the School for the Deaf which occupied the site until it was closed in the mid-1980s. After that the premises were used as a night-shelter for the homeless but suffered some vandalism and fires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complex was threatened with demolition for re-development in 1989 but local residents fought to save it and achieved statutory Grade II* listing for the chapel built in 1884 and also saved the residential block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a full history and timeline of St Thomas’ see the links below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 17:55:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25693 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Primitive Methodism in Basingstoke c.1830 to 1932/9</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/primitive-methodism-basingstoke-c1830-19329</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the Methodist Re-Union in 1932, the Primitive Methodists remained a distinctive feature of Basingstoke’s ecclesiastical landscape. They did, however, enjoy good relations, and collaborated closely, with the other Nonconformist denominations in the town. Indeed, their ministers were often described as brotherly and served not only their church and circuit but also the wider community. They included the Revd Charles Portnell (1868-70 and 1883-6), whose ‘preaching was plain but forceful’; the Revd Henry Yeates (1869-73), who ‘was especially gifted to stir and edify a congregation’ and later returned to Basingstoke, serving as a borough councillor from 1884 to 1887; the Revd Joseph Beal (1898-04), who ‘in his six years at Basingstoke … preached over four hundred and fifty sermons and retained his reputation for freshness’ and also superintended the erection of the new church; and  the Revd Ezra Ramm (1928-33), ‘a man sent from God, as a preacher fearless and true’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In leading their church and circuit, these ministers needed the support and encouragement of a large number of lay people, who performed most of the key roles in the organisations that the church sponsored. From Sunday schools to a flourishing Christian Endeavour society; from brass bands to the choir; and from women’s groups to a Peoples’ Pleasant Hour, such organisations cemented the loyalty of members and served as a means of reaching out to those unattached to any church. Indeed, evangelism was the &lt;em&gt;leitmotif&lt;/em&gt; running through much of the life of the Church. Its anniversary celebrations, missions, camp meetings and concerts and entertainments served the dual role of affording opportunities for fellowship amongst church members and affiliates and for drawing in the outsider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 1938 the Church (since the Methodist Re-Union in 1932, simply Sarum Hill Methodist Church) hosted the civic service, a particularly significant event since it ‘was the first occasion on which a member of the … Church, … [had] attended as mayor.’ Also present at the service were all the other civic dignitaries as well as representatives of the Territorials, Fire Brigade and Police. The minister, the Revd Harold Pope, preached on a verse from Revelation, Chapter 21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I, John, saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service was clearly indicative of the extent to which what had originally been a religious group that aroused hostility had now become part of the socio-cultural establishment of the town. In the process, however, it could be argued that it had lost something of the ‘spiritual cutting edge’ that had previously characterised Primitive Methodism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 11:37:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25661 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Mills of Nevis and Bishops Hull</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mills-nevis-and-bishops-hull</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bishops Hull acquired several new residents from the mid 18th century who had formerly lived in the West Indies. The Mills of Milligan Hall were plantation and slave owners from Nevis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 08:19:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25658 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Christian Endeavour in Basingstoke c.1893-1939</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/christian-endeavour-basingstoke-c1893-1939</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In seeking to find an effective means of bridging the gap between their Sunday schools and full church membership, from the 1890s onwards many of Basingstoke’s Free Churches established a Young People’s Society of Christian Endeavour (YPSCE). Having been founded in 1881 by the Revd Francis Edward Clark, the minister of Williston Congregational Church in the state of Maine, the innovation quickly spread. By the last decade of the 19th century it had been adopted in many countries including Great Britain where it was reported, in November 1894, that 1860 Societies had already been established. The aims of YPSCE were spelt out its founding constitution as: “To promote an earnest Christian life among its members, to increase their mutual acquaintance, and to make them more useful in the service of God.” These clearly resonated with a large number of church leaders who saw in YPSCE a way of harnessing the idealism, enthusiasm and commitment of the young in the service of the Church. In pursuing these aims, there was a very heavy emphasis on young people pledging themselves to follow Christ’s example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of Basingstoke’s Free Churches to establish a YPSCE was London Street Congregational Church in November 1893, with Immanuel Church (Countess of Huntingdon’s Connexion) following suit in January 1895. By the end of the century the Primitive Methodists had also started a Society and the Wesleyans had set up their equivalent, a Wesley Guild. In the early years, the anniversary celebrations of these Societies, at which there were frequently challenging addresses delivered by visiting speakers, were faithfully reported in the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. A notable characteristic of such Societies was their desire to forge close links with each other in order to encourage and to share ideas. Such networking was formalised in late 1897 with the setting up of the Basingstoke and District Christian Endeavour Union, which, in addition to the Basingstoke Societies, included those from Andover, Whitchurch, Overton, Odiham and Fleet. Consequently, by 1900 YPSCE had established firm foundations in Basingstoke and the surrounding area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of progress the years leading up the First World War were, in many respects, the most productive. Initiatives included providing meals and entertainments for the elderly; organising an Eisteddfod; and fund raising for good causes. Moreover, new Societies were established at the Working Men’s Mission in George Street and the new Baptist Church on Sarum Hill. There were, however, various concerns regarding the resilience of YPSCE, such as its ability to attract and energise young people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the War, Societies continued to promote what can best be described as ‘practical Christianity’. Although a number closed or were replaced with other provision for young people, the Primitive Methodist and Baptist societies, as well as the Wesley Guild, were still in existence in 1939. Looking back over the previous 30 to 40 years, there can be little doubt that Christian Endeavourers made their mark both within their churches and the wider community. As it was put by Mr J.B. Holmes the speaker at London Street’s seventeenth anniversary in 1910: ‘He believed in the Christian Endeavour Society because it recognised the young life in … [the] churches and gave them their opportunity of witnessing for Jesus Christ; and next because it did not despise their humble efforts … which perhaps most people looked down upon … [but] were accepted and blessed by Jesus Christ.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the sources of the quotes, please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Oct 2018 12:27:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25654 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Campaign for Women’s Suffrage in Basingstoke: 1908-1914</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/campaign-women%E2%80%99s-suffrage-basingstoke-1908-1914</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the years leading up to the First World War the impact of the campaign for women’s suffrage was as evident in Basingstoke as in every other part of the country. The campaign aroused strong feelings on both sides of the argument as to whether or not women should be granted the right to vote in parliamentary elections. Moreover, amongst supporters there was a clear divide between the moderate suffragists of the National Union of Women’s Suffrage Societies (NUWSS) and the militant suffragettes of the Women’s Political and Social Union (WPSU). In the absence of opinion polls, it is difficult to judge the balance of views in Basingstoke or the extent to which residents engaged with the issue. What can be said is that few in the town, if any, could have been unaware of the campaign and the arguments advanced by supporters and opponents alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From November 1908, when a local branch of the NUWSS was established, until the outbreak of War there were frequent meetings, held in various locations, both indoors and outdoors, by both advocates and opponents. These were faithfully reported, often in considerable detail, in the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, national figures from both sides of the campaign were sometimes the principal speakers. Those advocating the cause of women’s suffrage included, in October 1910, Mrs Millicent Fawcett, the President of the NUWSS, and in November 1912, Miss Margaret Ashton, Manchester’s first female city councillor. Of the opponents, the most renowned were Miss Mary Angela Dickens (grand-daughter of Charles Dickens) of the Women’s National Anti-Suffrage League, who spoke in February 1909, and Leo Maxse, editor of the &lt;em&gt;National Review&lt;/em&gt;, in February 1911. Among the local leadership, who chaired and spoke at meetings, were Mrs Conran, Mrs Isabella Raynbird and Miss Dorothy Edwards. The last two were members of a deputation which met Arthur Clavell Salter, the Conservative MP for Basingstoke from 1906 to 1917, in July 1912. He can best be described as being moderately sympathetic towards the cause of women’s suffrage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main, it would seem that most local supporters of women’s suffrage were moderates. Indeed, the WPSU Newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Votes for Women&lt;/em&gt;, gives the impression that there were few suffragettes in the town. There are no reports of any ‘direct action’ in Basingstoke, such as seeking to blow up letter boxes, and only one incident of any notoriety. This occurred at an open air meeting held in the Market Place in the summer of 1911, at which the speaker was a leading suffragette, Mrs Leigh. While speaking ‘a boy, without any warning, threw a stone at her, hitting her on the head … Without an instant’s hesitation, Mrs Leigh leapt from the wagonette, caught the boy by the collar, held him until he humbly apologised before the crowd, released him, and was back in the wagonette finishing her last sentence before the astonished audience realised what a narrow escape she had had.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotation please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 09:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25625 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Working Men&#039;s Mission Hall, Basingstoke 1905-28</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/working-mens-mission-hall-basingstoke-1905-28</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;From its opening in February 1905 until its transfer to the Methodists in 1928, the Working Men’s Mission Hall in George Street, Basingstoke, served as a non-denominational place of worship for those living in the vicinity. As it was put at the opening ceremony, it was the ‘earnest desire’ of those behind the enterprise that ‘souls might be saved there and that the preaching of the Gospel in that Hall might be made a means of blessing to the neighbourhood.’ Costing £220, it could accommodate 250 persons and was described as ‘being very comfortable’ and presenting ‘a light and attractive appearance’. It is not known who initiated the Hall’s construction. Although formally un-denominational, it attracted a considerable amount of support from Nonconformists and well-wishers within Basingstoke and beyond. For example, the Hall was formally opened by Mr B.B. Pond from Andover and William Buckland, Basingstoke’s mayor, presided at the evening meeting. At this event, it was made clear that the ‘Hall had not been erected in any spirit of opposition to any other Church.’ Not surprisingly, perhaps, the mood at the Hall’s opening was buoyant and optimistic. The formal opening and afternoon tea, as well as the evening meeting were all exceptionally well attended. By 1910 the debt on the Hall had been cleared. In many respects the Hall functioned just like the other Nonconformist places of worship in Basingstoke, with regular Sunday services; a range of associated organisations, including a Sunday school, a branch of the Band of Hope, a Christian Endeavour Society, a clothing club and, for a time, an orchestra; camp meetings; and social events and entertainments of various kinds. Annual anniversary celebrations were also an important feature in the life of the Hall, which appears to have thrived during the First World War and well into the 1920s. However, a few weeks after the 1928 anniversary celebrations, it was announced that: ‘The Trustees of the Working Men’s Mission Hall in George Street, which … [had] heretofore been carried on as an independent religious organisation, recently met and unanimously decided to offer the Mission Hall to the Wesleyan Methodist Church.’ Although no reasons were given, it is possible that the decision had been prompted by the ‘heavy losses sustained by the lamented deaths’ of two key figures in the running of the Mission, Messrs Lane and Laney. At the 1928 anniversary they had been described as ‘devoted and generous workers in the Mission.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;August 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 13:41:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25617 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Overton Poor Law to 1848</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/overton-poor-law-1848</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1686, the Overton vestry authorised a poor-house in the parish, which continued until the rapidly rising costs of poor relief resulted in a new House of Industry which opened in about 1800. The inmates made sacking but the income did not result in any reduction in the poor rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating under Gilbert’s Act of 1782, the overseers also paid outdoor relief for food, clothes and shoes, widows’ pensions, arrears of rent, money for those who were ill and could not work, for funerals and graves, travel to the county hospital and relief for poor travellers on the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1834, the Poor Law Amendment Act abolished outdoor relief and deterred the able-bodied from seeking relief in workhouses. The Overton poor rates dropped by half.  The Overton House of Industry became part of the Whitchurch Union and was closed in 1848.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 19:26:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25189 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Queen Camel parishioners 1583-1595</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/queen-camel-parishioners-1583-1595</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The account book of the vicar of Queen Camel records not only the tithes due and received but also his Easter offerings. His lists of household members offer a fascinating glimpse into the social structure of Queen Camel between 1583 and 1595.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 07:46:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24653 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The jailbirds, brawlers, vandals, drunkards, swearers and poachers of Windover Street, Basingstoke.</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/jailbirds-brawlers-vandals-drunkards-swearers-and-poachers-windover-street-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Windover Street leads from Cross Street into Joice’s Yard. Even though it was little more than an alley and contained only six cottages, it often, quite literally, punched above its weight. In 1881 it was home to a glorious group of jailbirds, brawlers, vandals, drunkards, swearers and poachers, who entertained the readers of the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette &lt;/em&gt;with their antics, and helped to keep the Magistrates’ Court in business.  The six cottages were demolished during the Town Redevelopment in c.1970 to make way for Joice’s Yard Car Park. The decision in 2013 to call the conversion of 12 Cross Street, &lt;em&gt;Windover Mews&lt;/em&gt;, is a way of remembering one of the most vibrant streets in Basingstoke and the colourful crowd who lived there. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 17:04:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24257 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Dennis Probate Material, 1801-1820</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-dennis-probate-material-1801-1820</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wills, administration bonds, inventories and other probate records, transcribed by VCH Cornwall volunteers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 12:11:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AliceI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23438 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
