<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Codford</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/codford</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Codford&#039;s Domesday Reckoning</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/codfords-domesday-reckoning</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Domesday Book, the most famous record in England’s national archive, and one of the oldest, has been available in printed form since 1783. Here is a facsimile copy of the original manuscript entry for Codford St Mary, and beneath it the 1783 printed transcript of the same entry, which copies as faithfully as possible the form and abbreviations of the original. There have been four published editions of the Wiltshire portion of Domesday Book since 1783, and two are widely available in libraries, so researchers have no problem in finding out what it records for any Wiltshire community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 13:09:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20685 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Codford census returns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/codford-census-returns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The census returns tell us agreat deal about the people of Codford in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2011 15:53:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20670 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Codford Hermit</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/codford-hermit</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The only evidence for Henry the hermit is found in a Patent Roll, one of a series of official documents recording government business. But when Sir Richard Colt Hoare was investigating the history and archaeology of the Codford area in the early 19th century he noticed a group of eight ancient yew trees standing alone on Malmpit Hill above St Mary’s, and discovered from old maps that this area had been called Hermitage Hill.     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; The historian then brings together evidence from the document, a folk memory (the name ‘Hermitage Hill’, which was then included on a printed map of Wiltshire), the old map itself and archaeological fieldwork, to tell us the who, where and when of the story.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12707 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Woolstore Theatre</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/woolstore-theatre</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the influence of his wife, Col Ralph Sneyd made the courtyard at Woolstore into a theatre in the late 1920’s.  From their first production in 1928 the Codford Amateurs, as the group styled themselves, flourished to such an extent that in 1938 they came fourth out of more than 200 entries in a national contest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A separate organisation, the Woolstore Country Theatre Club, was established by Lionel Crawhall, Wiltshire County Drama Adviser, who lived in Codford, for people interested in learning about all aspects of theatre. The Amateurs and the Theatre Club merged in 1964 after the theatre had been purchased by the Amateurs’ chairman, Harry Cole, and later sold for £400 to four benefactors on behalf of the Theatre Club.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12706 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Turnpike Trusts</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/turnpike-trusts</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two important turnpike trusts, based in Amesbury and Fisherton Anger (Salisbury), were authorised in 1761 to take responsibility for long stretches of major roads (including what are now known as the A36, A303 and A360), and both impinged on Codford. The Fisherton trust in 1761 turnpiked the Wylye valley road all the way from Salisbury, via Wilton and along Codford’s main street, to Heytesbury, where an earlier trust continued the route to Warminster. The Amesbury trust, as well as controlling the main Exeter road from near Andover to the hill above Mere, also turnpiked the road from Shrewton, through Chitterne, to Heytesbury, which crosses Codford’s downland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12705 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Floated Water Meadows</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/floated-water-meadows</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A slow but steady flow of river water right across the meadow (known as ‘drowning’ the meadow), kept the ground slightly warmer than it would be if exposed to winter frosts, and also nourishing it with alluvial deposits. If successful this would cause greater amounts of grass, in turn enabling farmers to keep more sheep. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a floated water meadow was expensive and involved skilful surveying and engineering. A main carriage (rather like a mill leat) was created, drawing water from the river upstream of the meadow. The intake and flow along it were controlled by hatches – small removable wooden dams. When full to overflowing the main carriage spilled water into smaller channels, known as carriers, which fanned out across the meadow. Between the carriers, and slightly lower, were drains, which fed the water into a main or tail drain, which in turn took the water back to the river further downstream.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12704 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Copyhold Tenure</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/copyhold-tenure</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Customary tenants made up the largest group, and also the lowest group of tenant farmers. Copyhold was perpetuated by inheritance or by ‘lives’ (leases were often held for the life of one or more lessees). Although rent was generally paid the major expenses were the substantial payments (known as an entry fines and heriots) which the manorial lord exacted on his tenant’s embarking on or inheriting the tenancy. If a copyhold or leasehold was on ‘lives’, generally three named individuals, the tenure could, if the lord agreed, be extended by adding a life when one of the three died – this too incurred a large one-off payment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12703 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Farms in Wartime</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/farms-wartime</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since 1940 about 94 acres of grassland ploughed up; some land taken for military use in Codford’s Manor Farm. At the larger East Farm, almost 400 acres of grassland were converted into arable farmland for the war effort. In addition to expanding available farmland, the government took a detailed account of what each farm was able to produce. These details, preserved in The National Archives, shows how precise the surveys of each farm was, right down to the exact number of cattle.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12702 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Open Fields</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/open-fields</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arable farming on the Wiltshire chalklands, such as Codford, continued until the 19th century to be organised on the basis of enormous open fields, without hedges or fences, which were divided into blocks of strips (or acres), known as furlongs. A Historian must rely on old maps and names in order to reconstruct how the land was farmed. To understand the organisation, extend, and location of a farming community’s common fields, and how this of a farming community’s common fields, and how this affected the development of settlements and farms, a local historian must use maps, documents and surviving place and field names.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12701 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Anglo-Saxon Sculptured Stone</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/anglo-saxon-sculptured-stone</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The basis for much speculation has been the Anglo-Saxon sculptured stone found in St. Peter’s church in 1864. From analyzing what the stone was made out, it has been determined the stone is from the late 8th or early 9th century. What the structure was used for is still argued. A couple possibilities are that it was part of a larger cross, or it belonged to the architecture of a church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The carvings on the stone are the still the focus of the debate. In one sense, the scene has been interpreted as a reference to the wine of the Eucharist, or perhaps to Christ.   On the other hand, the scene could be the biblical King David, dancing in celebration after his triumphant over the Philistines.  Either way, the sculptured stone is a celebrated work of art. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12700 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
