<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Derbyshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/ancient-county/derbyshire</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Local Government since 1834</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/local-government-1834</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between 1834 and 1894 local government at parish level was gradually reformed. The changes were piecemeal and conservative in approach, so that the traditional units such as counties, boroughs, and parishes survived, even if their powers and duties were altered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12676 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Roads and tracks - Old Peverel Road</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/roads-and-tracks-old-peverel-road</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generations of antiquaries have sought to identify stretches of modern road or footpath as prehistoric, Roman or medieval, or they try to link references in medieval deeds to routes on the ground. In fact, there is generally little evidence for the age of roads existing today, most of which have probably been in use since the area through which they pass was first settled, long before they are mentioned in documents or shown on maps. In some areas there are established traditions of roads built for particular purposes in the Middle Ages which have since gone out of use.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12674 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Duchess Georgiana</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/duchess-georgiana</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Duchess Georgiana married the 5th duke of Devonshire in 1775. Although based in London, the couple made regular visits to Hardwick Hall, usually for a few months at a time.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The duchess is believed to have been especially fond of the house and she encouraged some old customs to be revived. For example, in 1774 prayers were said in the chapel for the first time for many years and in 1797 a dance was held in the New Hall, an event that had not occurred since the 3rd duke&#039;s day. As a result of this increased use the house underwent yearly refurbishments between 1779 and 1787.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After Georgiana died in 1806 the duke used the house less; indeed, apart from one visit in 1809 there is little to suggest he ever returned to Hardwick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of the Devonshire Collection, Chatsworth. Reproduced by permission of Chatsworth Settlement Trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12150 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Hardwick Colliery (Holmewood)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/hardwick-colliery-holmewood</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Blacksmith&#039;s Shop at Hardwick Colliery (Holmewood).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of Derbyshire Local Studies Libraries and www.picturethepast.org.uk.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12149 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Legacy of Coalmining and the Hardwick Estate</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/legacy-coalmining-and-hardwick-estate</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;An agreement made in 1656 between the 3rd earl of Devonshire&#039;s receiver, Humphrey Poole, and nine colliers concerning the working of coal at Heath. The document is witnessed by Pooles&#039;s assistant and successor, Richard Derrey, who was also the licensee of the Hardwick Inn; the miners were unable to sign their names and so made crosses or other marks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of the Devonshire Collection, Chatsworth. Reproduced by permission of Chatsworth Settlement Trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12148 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>William Spenser Cavendish, 6th Duke of Devonshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/william-spenser-cavendish-6th-duke-devonshire</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1811, just short of his 21st birthday, William Spenser Cavendish (the 6th duke of Devonshire) inherited one of the largest landed estates in the United Kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During his life he devoted great energy and a vast amount of money to its improvement, including major extensions to the mansion and alterations to the gardens and park at Chatsworth. From 1840 he began a similar campaign of improvement at Hardwick modernising the Hall and improving the farms on the estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He spent more time at Hardwick than any of his immediate predecessors. The 6th duke never married and at his death in 1858, his  title passed to a distant kinsman, who in 1868 conveyed the Hardwick estate to his eldest son, the marquess of Hartington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of the Devonshire Collection, Chatsworth. Reproduced by permission of Chatsworth Settlement Trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12147 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Thomas Hobbes</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thomas-hobbes</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Hobbes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Hobbes, the greatest English political philosopher of his day, who joined the Cavendish household as the 2nd earl&#039;s tutor and stayed as a trusted secretary until he died in 1679. Some of the books he collected are still in the library at Chatsworth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of Chesterfield Library volume of portraits and Picture the Past www.picturethepast.org.uk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12146 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ault Hucknall Church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ault-hucknall-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Ault Hucknall, as in most communities, the oldest surviving building is the parish church. St John’s is unusual among Derbyshire churches in retaining features that date from the 11th century when architecture was still influenced by Anglo-Saxon traditions. The church has three compartments – a nave with a north aisle, a former chancel under a crossing tower, and a sanctuary (now the chancel).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ault Hucknall church played an important role in the Hardwick Estate. All parishioners would have been expected to attend services weekly at Ault Hucknall church, which lay some distance from any of the villages in the parish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of English Heritage (Steve Cole).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12145 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bess of Hardwick</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bess-hardwick</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth dowager countess of Shrewsbury (c.1521–1608), best known to history as `Bess of Hardwick&#039;, is probably the third most famous Englishwoman of her age after Queen Elizabeth herself and Mary Queen of Scots, with both of whom Bess had close links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She was married four times, firstly to Robert Barley, secondly to the courtier Sir William Cavendish, thirdly to Sir William St Loe and lastly to George Talbot, 6th Earl of Shrewsbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bess amassed a large fortune from her four marriages which she invested in both re-building the Old Hall at  and building the New Hall at Hardwick as well as acquiring substantial tracts of land in neighbouring regions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12144 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Chatsworth: seat of the Cavendish family</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/chatsworth-seat-cavendish-family</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chatsworth was transformed in the 1680s from Sir William Cavendish&#039;s Elizabethan house with four tall ranges round a small courtyard into a fashionable Italianate palace. In 1688 the 1st duke of Devonshire ordered one of the Elizabethan ranges to be taken down and rebuilt on the same foundations to designs by William Talman, who in 1689 became Comptroller of the King&#039;s Works. That work was followed by the rebuilding of the other ranges and completed by 1694. The magnificent  house became the family&#039;s main seat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:35:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12142 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
