<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Corby</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/corby</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Studfall Avenue Shopping Precinct</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/studfall-avenue-shopping-precinct</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As had Stewarts and Lloyds at Rockingham Road, the Corby UDC constructed a localised shopping precinct to serve the first phase of their building development, which was completed by 1952. Like the shops on Rockingham Road, the UDC commissioned a self-contained arcade of shops with maisonettes above (Plate 8). Designed by the architects Blackwell, Storry &amp;amp; Scott, fifteen shops with living accommodation above were built following the curve of Studfall Avenue on its northern side, bounded by Clydesdale Road and Throughsale Wood to the west and Darley Dale Road to the east[1]. Accessed by a service road running parallel to Studfall Avenue to the north and set opposite a triangular green space, these brick built shops (with the exception of two of the larger shops) had private entrances to the living quarters above. The shops are constructed in a utilitarian post-war style with steel framing up to first floor level, pre-cast concrete beams to first and second floors and flat roofs constructed using timber framing[2]. This precinct of shops is essential to the homogeneity of early Corby, located as it is between the two areas of early UDC house building, between Studfall Avenue and Forest Gate Road and to the south of Rowlett Road. Its location on Studfall Avenue also physically linked the burgeoning UDC Forest Gate Estate with the established Stewart and Lloyds Estate via one of the major Rockingham Road subsidiaries. [1] Architect and Building News, Shops and Maisonettes, Corby for the Urban District Council (October 30th 1952), 515   [2] A &amp;amp; B N, (October 30th 1952), 515&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 15:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12750 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The BISF House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bisf-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BISF house, designed by Frederich Gibberd and Donovan Lee following the Burt Committee report of autumn 1945 on experimental housing types, was endorsed by the Government and a special company, British Steel Homes Ltd was formed to develop and build houses throughout the UK[1]. At Corby, the type A1 BISF house, of which 35,000 were built nationwide between 1944-1950[2], formed the majority of the 1500 houses hastily constructed to the north west of the Stewarts and Lloyds estate in the post war years prior to New Town designation. The sites for these houses were prepared by Messrs J. Mowlem and Sons, relying heavily on German POWs for labour[3].  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The BISF type A1 house was on 2 floors and constructed as either a semi-detached or terraced house of 89.18m2.[4] At Corby each BISF dwelling was retained as a 2 floor semi-detached house and not subdivided into apartments (as they were in Scotland), no doubt in an attempt to provide a standard of accommodation comparable in size to those constructed by Stewarts and Lloyds. The external walls of the ground floor were of a cement render applied to metal laths, whilst the walls of the first floor were constructed using vertical steel sheeting, fixed to rails and bolted to vertical channels which extend to join the laths below[5]. In many cases, the sheet steel upper walls of the BISF houses were rendered and ‘cracking’ of this render, along with wall cavity fires were common problems associated with this kind of prefabricated house. However at Corby the majority of the BISF houses are un-rendered, with examples where the sheet steel and cover strips have been highlighted as an architectural feature, such as on Dovedale Road.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] The Scottish Building Directorate, A Guide to non-traditional Housing in Scotland (2001), 220   [2] H. Harrison, S. Mullin, B. Reeves &amp;amp; A. Stevens, Non-Traditional Houses-Identifying non-Traditional Houses in the UK 1918-75 (2004), 34   [3] TNA: PRO HLG 104   [4] Scottish Building Directorate, Non-traditional Housing in Scotland , 220   [5] Ibid p222&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 15:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12749 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Stewarts and Lloyds Housing Estates</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/stewarts-and-lloyds-housing-estates</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Having begun construction of the plant, Stewarts and Lloyds were faced with the problem of housing the new workforce, an expected 1650 people, a figure which would swell to some 4000-5000, many of whom had migrated from Scotland with the company[1]. With no provision in the financial plan produced by the company in 1932 for the construction of workers accommodation, assistance was sought from both the Ministry of Health and Northamptonshire County Council. However by the end of 1932 all of the Government schemes, many curtailed by economic depression, had ceased or were coming to an end. Funded by a 90% loan from the Halifax building society on a figure of £306,405, Stewarts and Lloyds made an arrangement with the Ministry of Health and the Northamptonshire County Council for guarantees over 800 houses to be built by Browning Brothers of Leicester[2].   Bessemer Grove, the first of these houses, completed in the summer of 1934 was located to the south of the old village close to the church, although these would be the last Stewarts and Lloyds houses built in this area. The remainder of the 785 houses were constructed on a large estate either side of the Rockingham road (often seen as the divide between the Scottish and English workers) to the north-west of the plant[3]. This was the most obvious location for the development, as it was the closest level and available land to the plant in which building would not be hampered by existing ironstone quarries, the Midland Railway or areas earmarked for future ironstone extraction.     The houses constructed by Stewarts and Lloyds and an additional 314 houses built by the First National Housing Trust, later purchased by Stewarts and Lloyds for a sum of £16, 956 were built to a standard design devised by the company’s architect[4]. The first of these houses were built in a roughly triangular patch of land created by the railway to the east, Rockingham Road to the west and centred on the sweep of the newly laid out Stephenson Way (Plate 1).  The estate was completed by a larger development to the west of Rockingham Road built to a standard grid pattern. Situated adjacent to the blast furnaces, the houses were of a semi-detached design, comprising two bedroom one living room and three bedroom one living room layouts in a late arts &amp;amp; crafts design, clearly influenced by the work of the architect Barry Parker and not dissimilar to other contemporary inter-war housing schemes. The construction of a number of detached and three bedroom, one dining room, one lounge layouts suggest that there was a hierarchy of accommodation based on employee status, although the majority of the company executives were offered new homes in the nearby village of East Carlton[5].   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1939, Stewarts and Lloyds had constructed some 2,149 houses in two large estates either side of the Rockingham Road, bounded by Rowlett Road to the north, Hazelwood Road to the west, Occupation Road to the south and the railway to the east[6]. The majority of these houses were of the two and three bedroom design (2,120) and were described in March 1961 by the Northamptonshire District Valuer as; ‘The better type of pre-war council housing’ and the semi-detached houses made up a far higher proportion of the estate than on the estates later constructed by the Development Corporation. All of brick built construction, with tiled roofs and damp proof courses, these houses were of a good quality, despite the non-cavity walls and metal window frames leading to problems with condensation[7]. The houses built by Stewarts and Lloyds would later form the Penn Green and Studfall Neighbourhoods and were supplemented by a workers club and sports ground built between 1937 and 1938 to the north of Occupation Road, an Odeon cinema, completed in March 1936, shops, schools and churches. Rockingham Road became the main street in Corby with Occupation Road leading westward as the main subsidiary.[8]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] W. Holford &amp;amp; H. Myles Wright, Corby New Town: A Report to the Development Corporation on the Master Plan (1952), 5 and Scopes, Corby Works. 114   [2] Scopes, Corby Works. 114   [3] Scopes, Corby Works. 115   [4] Ibid p116   [5] A.R. Maunders, A Process of Struggle: The Campaign for Corby Steel Making in 1979 (1987), 2   [6] The National Archives (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO) HLG 91/763 Ministry of Town and Country Planning and successors: New Towns, Development Corporations, Registered Files, Corby, Acquisition of Houses Owned by Stewarts and Lloyds Ltd   [7] TNA: PRO HLG 91/763   [8] Holford &amp;amp; Wright, Corby New Town, 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 15:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12748 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Corby Urban District Council</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/corby-urban-district-council</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1939 the Corby Urban District Council was established, separating from the Kettering Rural District Council and taking responsibility for housing provision in Corby, although there was little or no building activity during the war[1]. Following the end of the Second World War, Iron and Steel control, a department within the Ministry of Supply outlined the importance of the Stewarts and Lloyds plant achieving an output of 500,000 ingot tonnes per annum to aid national recovery[2]. With returning servicemen and the requirement of the Ministry of Supply for a substantial workforce at the steel plant, the Corby UDC was faced with a housing shortage. In a letter of 28th December 1945, the directors of Stewarts and Lloyds made it clear that in order to achieve these productivity targets, they would require housing for 400 families immediately and 400 more in 12 months time[3]. At this time some 500 steel workers were living in Prisoner of War Camps, one of which located to the south of Corby village on South Road. The Corby UDC responded to this urgent need for housing by increasing their program of compulsory land acquisition under Part V of the 1936 Housing Act. Importantly, land was acquired on the 15th February 1945 under the Corby (Forest Gate) Housing Confirmation Order[4]. This allowed the UDC to continue to exploit the plateau of land to the west and north-west of the Stewarts and Lloyds housing estates. In order to build houses in large quantity and in a short space of time and with building materials in short supply, a number of non-traditional housing designs were chosen for the first phase of UDC building. The first of these houses, 52 British Iron and Steel Federation (BISF) houses were erected in Southall Road and St John’s place to the south of the village following compulsory purchase of land on 19th June 1945[5] and were completed in July 1947[6]. However the UDC did not continue to develop the old village and the first major UDC estate was to the west of the Stewarts and Lloyds housing, focused on Studfall Avenue and Dovedale Road. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 7th January 1946, Stewarts and Lloyds announced that unless they received Government assurance within a fortnight that 800-1000 new houses would be constructed to serve their operation within the next two years, they would cancel their expansion plans[7]. In June of that year under the terms of the Corby (North-West) Housing Confirmation Order, the UDC purchased a large area of land to the north-west of Studfall Avenue, previously owned by Stewarts and Lloyds and Lord Brooke[8] and in July was granted permission to erect 1000 BISF houses for Stewarts and Lloyds operatives.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Holford &amp;amp; Wright, Corby New Town, 6 [2] The National Archives (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO) AVIA 50/1 Ministry of Supply: Labour, Registered Files, Series 3, Stewarts and Lloyds, Corby: Housing Needs [3] TNA: PRO AVIA 50/1 [4] The National Archives (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO) HLG 23/21981 Ministry of Health: Legal Branch: Sealed Plans, Corby UDC. Forest Gate. Housing Confirmation Order [5] The National Archives (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO) HLG 23/23089 Ministry of Health: Legal Branch: Sealed Plans, Corby UDC. South Rd. Housing Confirmation Order 1945 [6] The National Archives (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO) HLG 104 Ministry of Health and successors: Planning and Redevelopment [7] TNA: PRO AVIA 50/1 [8] National Archives (TNA): Public Record Office (PRO) HLG 23/25377 Ministry of Health: Legal Branch: Sealed Plans Corby UDC. North West Housing Confirmation Order 1946  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 15:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12747 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>UDC Concrete Houses</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/udc-concrete-houses</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 10th December 1947, the Corby UDC received approval from the Treasury to construct 218 Easiform houses and 250 Wates Houses to supplement the redundant aluminium RAF bungalows allocated to Corby and the 140 BISF houses already completed[1]. The Easiform house was developed in 1919 due to a shortage of bricks and bricklayers and was constructed of poured concrete. The same shortages after World War Two saw the Type II design developed with over 100,000 constructed between the 1920s and the 1970s[2]. At Corby these houses were constructed in a two-storey semi-detached layout by Messrs J. Mowlem, and were rendered rather than fair faced with concrete. They were built extensively alongside the BISF houses in the Forest Gate estate and examples can be found on Clydesdale Road.   The first phase of house building by the Corby UDC saw new estates created to the south of the old village, between Studfall Avenue and Forest Gate Road (Forest Gate Estate) and a more substantial estate to the north of Rowlett Road, bounded by Willow Brook Road to the north and west and Rockingham Road to the east (Willowbrook Estate). The Willowbrook estate saw the greatest proliferation of non-traditional housing types in Corby with a mixture of prefabricated steel BISF houses, concrete Easiform houses and concrete panelled Wates houses, constructed there by 1950.   The Wates system was developed by a large building firm involved in the wartime ‘Mulberry’ pre-cast concrete harbour project and consisted of a number of pre-cast ‘tray-shaped’ concrete panels formed around a specially designed jig[3]. This design, of which 22,000 were built in the UK between 1947 and 1956, has since being designated as defective by the Building Research Establishment[4] making the unaltered survival of these houses along Willowbrook Road, Studfall Avenue and the north end of Rockingham Road, all the more remarkable.   The Willowbrook Estate reflects the hasty and ad hoc way in which the houses were constructed, often by a number of different contractors, with different designs of house constructed one type either side of a major road, such as on Shakespeare Way and Welland Vale Road. This is also reflected in the layout of the estate. The bounded, inward facing, tight grid form of the Stewarts and Lloyds estates was replaced with a more organic feeling layout. Long, sweeping boulevards were laid out to connect with the Rockingham Road, with rows of semi-detached houses on both sides and were supplemented by small crescents and cul-de-sacs. To the east of the estate a grid of north-south aligned streets joined Willowbrook Road with Rowlett Road. By the time the Ministry of Town and Country Planning met to discuss Corby on 25th November 1948, 306 houses had been completed by the UDC, 586 were under contract and a further 1236 had been approved[5] and by the time that the Willowbrook Estate was complete, the UDC had constructed over 1500 houses[6].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] TNA: PRO HLG 104&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Harrison et al. Non-Traditional Houses, 556&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] B. Finnimore, Houses from the Factory: System Building and the Welfare State 1942-74 (1989), 171&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] Harrison et al. Non-Traditional Houses, 478&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] TNA: PRO AVIA 50/1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[6] Holford &amp;amp; Wright, Corby New Town, 6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2010 15:00:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12746 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
