<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Political</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/political</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Dummer Boundary and Milestones</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-boundary-and-milestones</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local trusts were obliged to erect milestones on turnpike roads by law in 1773. Some of these stone markers can still be seen along many main roads. Dummer has three such stones on its western boundary on the A30, all of which are Grade II Listed monuments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boundary stones are less common but Dummer has two that survive on the edge of woodland demarking its parish from that of Popham and the Candovers.  Boundaries were inspected by meresmen who would agree the extent of the parish with neighbouring officials and check the condition of ditches, hedges and fences. The old custom of beating the bounds dates back to the importance of passing on the knowledge of the parish limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link below contains photographs and a more detailed account of the stones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 18:34:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25689 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The day the vicar locked the council out of the parish church of Basingstoke.</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/day-vicar-locked-council-out-parish-church-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Basingstoke made headlines in the national and provincial press in 1907 when the vicar of Basingstoke, Revd Boustead, sent an intemperate letter to the town clerk. He told the clerk that the Mayor and Corporation and the police, fire brigade and other public and voluntary bodies would not be welcome to hold the annual Civic Service in the Parish Church if they intended, in line with tradition, to hold a similar service in one of the nonconformist churches. He said that such an action would, ‘degrade God’s Church to the level of one of the 350 man-made sects’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revd Boustead’s letter was reprinted with a brief introduction in dozens of provincial newspapers from the &lt;em&gt;Cornishman&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Aberdeen Press and Journal&lt;/em&gt; under various headlines, including ‘Strange Situation at Basingstoke’, ‘Mockery of Religion’, ‘Not wanted at Church’ and ‘Another Clerical Bigot’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mayor decided not to hold the Civic Service in the Parish Church. However, the following year he decided that the custom of the Civic Service should continue, but when the procession reached the church, the vicar had locked the church door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the full story, please see the attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 12:16:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25681 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Housekeeper, Public Servant and Suffragist: The Productive Life of Mrs Isabella Raynbird (nee Webb) of Basingstoke 1837 -1925</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/housekeeper-public-servant-and-suffragist-productive-life-mrs-isabella-raynbird-nee-webb</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of her death, Isabella Raynbird was praised as somebody who ‘took a keen interest in everything for the good of the parish in which she lived, and, always ready to help any in need, she was greatly beloved by all’.* Such compliments were undoubtedly justified since she had lived a very full and productive life of 87 years. Born in Mapledurwell, her father was a prosperous farmer and Isabella undoubtedly experienced a relatively privileged upbringing. During her childhood and adolescence, she also became familiar with a farming way of life. Thus, unsurprisingly, for many years she was ‘housekeeper’ to Samuel Sparshatt, who farmed in the parish of Weston Patrick. Following his death in 1884 Isabella inherited not only his farming responsibilities but also his public service role of churchwarden and parish overseer, which she retained until her death. In 1890, at the age of 52, Isabella married widower Hugh Edward Raynbird, who was steward to Lord Bolton of Hackwood Park and head of the auctioneering firm, Raynbird and Son. Following her marriage she moved to Old Basing and from 1898 to 1922 served as one of the parish’s two poor law guardians, at a time when most members of boards of guardians were male. As a guardian, Isabella’s particular interests included the welfare and education of Workhouse children and staffing matters. She also attended a number of poor law conferences in Winchester and London. Throughout, she demonstrated her competence in what was, in part at least, a political role, thereby strengthening the case for the increased involvement of women in the public realm. This was also reflected in her support for those campaigning for women’s suffrage. She identified, however, with the moderate suffragists as opposed to the militant suffragettes. After some initial reluctance, in 1910 Isabella accepted the chairmanship/presidency of the Basingstoke and District Women’s Suffrage Society. In promoting the cause, she spoke at, and chaired, meetings and was a member of a deputation which met with the local MP in 1912 to secure his support. Some of Isabella’s intellectual interests, which she shared with her husband, were pursued through membership of the Hampshire Field Club and Archaeological Society. Looked at in the round, her life exemplified the increasing self-confidence of women as the 19th century gave way to the twentieth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite an extensive search, no photographs of Isabella have been found. Consequently it has been necessary to use an image of her husband to illustrate this item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For the source of the quotation, please see the PDF link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 17:29:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25648 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Campaign for Women’s Suffrage in Basingstoke: 1908-1914</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/campaign-women%E2%80%99s-suffrage-basingstoke-1908-1914</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the years leading up to the First World War the impact of the campaign for women’s suffrage was as evident in Basingstoke as in every other part of the country. The campaign aroused strong feelings on both sides of the argument as to whether or not women should be granted the right to vote in parliamentary elections. Moreover, amongst supporters there was a clear divide between the moderate suffragists of the National Union of Women’s Suffrage Societies (NUWSS) and the militant suffragettes of the Women’s Political and Social Union (WPSU). In the absence of opinion polls, it is difficult to judge the balance of views in Basingstoke or the extent to which residents engaged with the issue. What can be said is that few in the town, if any, could have been unaware of the campaign and the arguments advanced by supporters and opponents alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From November 1908, when a local branch of the NUWSS was established, until the outbreak of War there were frequent meetings, held in various locations, both indoors and outdoors, by both advocates and opponents. These were faithfully reported, often in considerable detail, in the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, national figures from both sides of the campaign were sometimes the principal speakers. Those advocating the cause of women’s suffrage included, in October 1910, Mrs Millicent Fawcett, the President of the NUWSS, and in November 1912, Miss Margaret Ashton, Manchester’s first female city councillor. Of the opponents, the most renowned were Miss Mary Angela Dickens (grand-daughter of Charles Dickens) of the Women’s National Anti-Suffrage League, who spoke in February 1909, and Leo Maxse, editor of the &lt;em&gt;National Review&lt;/em&gt;, in February 1911. Among the local leadership, who chaired and spoke at meetings, were Mrs Conran, Mrs Isabella Raynbird and Miss Dorothy Edwards. The last two were members of a deputation which met Arthur Clavell Salter, the Conservative MP for Basingstoke from 1906 to 1917, in July 1912. He can best be described as being moderately sympathetic towards the cause of women’s suffrage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the main, it would seem that most local supporters of women’s suffrage were moderates. Indeed, the WPSU Newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Votes for Women&lt;/em&gt;, gives the impression that there were few suffragettes in the town. There are no reports of any ‘direct action’ in Basingstoke, such as seeking to blow up letter boxes, and only one incident of any notoriety. This occurred at an open air meeting held in the Market Place in the summer of 1911, at which the speaker was a leading suffragette, Mrs Leigh. While speaking ‘a boy, without any warning, threw a stone at her, hitting her on the head … Without an instant’s hesitation, Mrs Leigh leapt from the wagonette, caught the boy by the collar, held him until he humbly apologised before the crowd, released him, and was back in the wagonette finishing her last sentence before the astonished audience realised what a narrow escape she had had.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotation please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 09:09:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25625 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>1939 National Register for Dummer</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/1939-national-register-dummer</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The National Register of 1939&lt;/strong&gt;[1] shows the occupations of Dummer residents (population 360 ) to consist largely of those associated with the land (landowner, farmer, smallholder, labourer, gardener, market gardener, forestry worker, gamekeeper, shepherd, cowman, poultryman, carter, sawyer and tractor driver), in trades related to an agricultural economy (carpenter, wheelwright, blacksmith, haulage contractor, brick layer) and in services supporting the community (grocer, shopkeeper, roundsman, newsagent, plumber/pipe layer, inn keeper, bus proprietor, petrol station owner and road labourer). Four men worked at an aeronautical instrument maker, one each as a telephone linesman engineer, a paper mill hand and a watchman at a motor works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professional and government officers included the rector, an undersecretary of state for agriculture, elementary school teacher, sub-postmistress, government officer (health) and a police constable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women were largely recorded as unpaid domestic workers in their own homes with the exceptions of a foster mother, a café assistant, a tailoress in a clothing factory, a school cleaner and a small number who were employed as domestic servants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Domestic service was limited to six properties: Dummer Grange where there was a butler/chauffeur, gardener, two domestic servants and a children’s nurse; Dummer House with a groom, chauffeur/gardener, cook, parlourmaid and housemaid; Clump House with a cook and housemaid; the Rectory, Dummer Down farm and Dummer Grange farm each with one domestic servant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The golf course established in 1928 gave rise to the new occupations of professional golfer, stewardess and groundsman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty children, twelve retirees, five invalids and four people of independent means are listed in the register but 81 entries are blanked out (listed as A.N.Other) and relate to residents who may still be alive in 2018 and whose identity is protected under the 100 year rule. The total number of children may be assumed to have been very much higher than shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dummer register was compiled by Gertrude Maud Weekes on 14 October 1939, a few weeks after the outbreak of World War 11. It identifies 15 ARP wardens, four Red Cross members, three Special Constables, a Billeting Office and a Land Army organiser as well as the first evacuee. Dubbed ‘The Wartime Domesday Book’ it is said to be the most comprehensive survey of the population of England and Wales ever undertaken. The National Registration Act, 1939 which ordered the register introduced compulsory identity cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images of an original registration card are below as well as the transcription of the register.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1]  &lt;em&gt;1939 England &amp;amp; Wales Register&lt;/em&gt;, Hampshire, Basingstoke RD, EEDU, accessed via Ancestry.co.uk.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Sue Lane &amp;amp; Jennie Butler&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 14:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25446 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Riots, Rough Music and Popular Disturbances in 19th century Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/riots-rough-music-and-popular-disturbances-19th-century-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the 19th century there were a number of incidents of popular disturbances in Basingstoke, including the riots in connection with the Salvation Army in the 1880s that gave rise to questions in Parliament and headlines in the national press, Bonfire Night disturbances, election riots, rough music and window smashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the story of these events see the link below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2018 18:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25371 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Reclaiming the Estuary</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/reclaiming-estuary</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The creeks and marshes along the Essex coast contain large areas of salt marsh.  These were used as land to graze sheep in summer, but were often flooded and inaccessible in winter.  However, the land was more valuable if it could be reclaimed from the sea, drained and protected from the salt water by a sea wall which is what happened in the Gunfleet estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mouth of the estuary was probably protected in earlier centuries by a headland (a Ness) at Little Holland Hall and another at Frinton, but these were eroded to create the straighter coastline of today.  It is probable that some land reclamation was already happening in the Medieval and Tudor periods and natural processes such as silting and longshore drift continued to change the size and shape of the estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tendring Level Commissioners, a public body recruited from local landowners, decided to construct a sea wall in the 17th century.  This meant that hundreds of acres of land was reclaimed in the parishes of Great Holland, Little Holland, Frinton, Great Clacton, Little Clacton and Thorpe-le-Soken.  A &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/holland-haven-sluices-and-marsh-shown-1838-ordnance-survey-map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sluice &lt;/a&gt;was built in the wall to allow the river to drain into the sea.  By preventing salt water entering the marshes the land in the estuary would be improved for agricultural use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This changing landscape had an effect on local land use.  Maps of 1594 and 1603 indicate that there was no route at that time across the Gunfleet estuary which still formed a major barrier to land communications along the coast.  As a result, there was probably much communication in small boats across the Gunfleet estuary and along the coast in the sheltered waters of the Gunfleet Channel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inland, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/andre-and-chapman-map-1777-showing-rice-bridge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rice Bridge&lt;/a&gt; is the earliest recorded crossing point of the Holland River and was in existence by 1319.  It was probably a timber bridge or causeway at this point and was described as a wooden footbridge in 1783.  The bridge connected the two parishes of Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton. The present brick built Rice bridge dates from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/fan-bridge-shown-chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fan Bridge&lt;/a&gt; is the second recorded crossing and is further downstream than Rice Bridge where the river was wider and the land more liable to flood.  This was certainly a more difficult and marshy location for a bridge, as the name Fan or Fen suggests, and in earlier centuries when the Gunfleet estuary was more open to the sea it may have been an impractical location.  The crossing is first recorded in 1509 and is shown on the 1777 map with a dashed line to indicate the marshy terrain.  New bridges were built in the 18th and 19th centuries with the present brick bridge appearing to date from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/holland-bridge-shown-1838-ordnance-survey-map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Holland Bridge&lt;/a&gt; is the most recent bridge to cross the Holland River, and is the furthest downstream.  When the reclamation works were considered sufficiently advanced, a causeway was built across the reclaimed land and the new bridge, named Little Holland Bridge, was built, although on the 1777 map the approach road through the marshes is depicted as a series of dashes to mean that the route was rather impermanent or uncertain and liable to flood.  The date of the bridge is uncertain, but it had probably not been built long when it was first recorded in the 1720s.  This bridge was locally significant as it was the first time that a direct road communication existed between Little Holland and Great Holland on the two sides of the old estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can explore&lt;strong&gt; Reclaiming the Estuary&lt;/strong&gt; using the suggested activities and assets below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How has the landscape changed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spot the difference in the landscape using &lt;strong&gt;maps &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1777&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/gunfleet-estuary-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  You can play a game of spot the difference by using two maps and challenging a partner to find as many differences between them as possible.  At the end make a list of what has changed and what has stayed the same.  You could also play this as a question and answer activity, with players trying to work out their partner’s chosen map or map feature by asking and answering questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider the effects of natural processes &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;maps &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1777&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/gunfleet-estuary-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to overlay and trace the physical features of the landscape creating a new map showing how the landscape has changed over time.  Use your knowledge of natural processes (long shore drift, silting, and erosion) to label the new map showing how each has had an impact on the landscape.  Extend this activity by adding in labels for human features (river crossings, roads).  Use the new map to explain the consequences of the physical changes for local people in terms of industry, agriculture, and communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building bridges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;maps &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1777&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/gunfleet-estuary-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1838&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your team are in charge of building a bridge at Holland Haven in 1594, 1777 or 1838.  It could be a new bridge to cross the river or a replacement for an existing bridge.  The answers to these suggested questions might help you think about where your bridge should be and what it might be built from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you need a bridge? (think about people, jobs, travel)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is a good place for the bridge? (think about how wide the river is, how marshy the land is)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will the bridge look like? (think about materials, coast and strength)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a competition to design and build a river crossing for each of the dates.  At the bridge opening each team will need to explain their choices of location, design and materials. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 12:58:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24626 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Smuggling in the Minehead port area</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/smuggling-minehead-port-area</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minehead port area, which stretched from the Devon boundary to Shurton Barrs near Stogursey, was full of small creeks and landing places where goods could be illegally landed. Such goods might be luxuries but were usually basic commodities like salt and soap. Smuggling was not just a question of evading paying duty but also harbour dues for the upkeep of quays, restrictions on foreign imports in war, restrictions on cattle movements during cattle plague and laws against dumping of cheap Irish manufactures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 11:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22659 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead Harbour Administration</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-harbour-administration</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-harbour&quot;&gt;Minehead harbour&lt;/a&gt; belonged to the Luttrells and was run by harbourmasters. The Crown also had an interest in the form of the Customs and later the Coastguard. Finally a lifeboat service was established to improve the rescue of mariners from shipwrecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Coastguard and the lifeboat continue to serve the coastal waters around Minehead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 10:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22654 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basing House, Old Basing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basing-house-old-basing</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;Standing on a hill above the marshy valley of the Loddon, Basing House has long been the site of human habitation.  Iron Age and Roman remains have been found beneath the earthworks which still dominate the monument.  These were thrown up sometime in the mid 12th century by the de Port family, to form a huge timber ring-work castle now known as the &quot;Old House&quot;, with at least two baileys.  Hugh de Port had been granted the manor of Basing by William 1st shortly after the Conquest and his descendants held it until 1972 albeit with changes through marriage to the family name – first to St John, then Poyning and finally in 1420 to Paulet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;By 1525 Basing was owned by Sir William Paulet, a statesman of outstanding skill and the ability to survive the storms of Tudor court life, dying in bed in 1572 at the age, some claim, of 100 years, as Lord Treasurer of England, and Marquess of Winchester.  During his long life, Sir William rebuilt the house twice, the first time in the 1530s having obtained a ‘Licence to Crenellate’ from the crown and secondly in the 1550/60s when he massively enlarged his home by the construction of the ‘New House’. Most of these structures were of local brick with fine white stone mouldings and decorations of the finest craftsmanship.  Sir William was no stranger to playing host to huge royal progresses which included Henry VIII, Edward VI, Mary and Philip and Elizabeth I, all at vast cost, which his descendants found crippling to continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;Following the visit of James I in 1603 the decision was taken to demolish part of the house.  The Paulet family withdrew to make a home in the estate&#039;s hunting lodge at Hackwood, and by 1635 Basing House was described as ‘forsaken and desolate’. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;In the Civil War the Catholic John Paulet, 5th Marquess of Winchester, declared his support for King Charles I and returned to Basing to refortify his ancestral home and turn it into a royalist garrison.  Large scale earthwork defences were thrown up around the house and the Tudor brick curtain walls were loop holed for muskets and artillery.  The Marquess and his 300 or so men managed to hold the garrison through sieges in 1643 and 1644 but finally the house fell on 14 October 1645 to Oliver Cromwell at the head of a brigade of over 7,000 soldiers.  The house was gutted by fire during the assault and shortly afterwards Parliament gave order that the ruins could be used as a free quarry.  The villagers of Basing lost no time in repairing their war ravaged homes with salvaged material from the once mighty Tudor palace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;Following the Restoration in 1660 John Paulet was given the site back but it was not until the 1670s that his son and heir Charles 6th Marquess of Winchester, later 1st Duke of Bolton, began to show interest in it.  Charles demolished most of the ruins and laid out the site as an elaborate landscape garden with a vineyard to form a view for a new hunting lodge he constructed in the Grange Field next to the Great Barn, the only major survivor of William Paulet&#039;s great building complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;By the middle of the 18th century, the Duke&#039;s hunting lodge had been demolished and the new gardens overgrown and forgotten.  In the 1790s the Basingstoke Canal was driven through the site of the New House and a bridge constructed just inside the surviving Garrison Gate.  Like the Duke&#039;s hunting lodge, the canal was short lived due to the coming of  the London and Southampton railway in 1839 and problems with a dependable water supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;In the 1870s Lord Bolton, owner of Basing House and direct descendant of William Paulet began a series of excavations on site which were to last for 40 years, and revealed much of the plan of the lost house.  A great many small finds were discovered which Lord Bolton housed in a purpose built museum (the Bothy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;During the 2nd World War Basing House served as the site for an anti-aircraft battery and a training ground for the local Home Guard.  In the 1960s excavations were carried out on various parts of the site and in 1972 the historic monument was purchased by Hampshire County Council.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;yiv494148711msonormal&quot;&gt;The University of Southampton are carrying out excavations at Basing House. Follow them on Facebook or on the Project blog&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 13:46:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21446 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
