<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Castle Cary</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/castle-cary</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Castle Cary in the Civil War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/castle-cary-civil-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A coin hoard found in 2006 is a striking reminder of the terrible damage the Civil War did to ordinary people&#039;s lives. Castle Cary suffered from several incidents including a nearby assembly of 5,000 clubmen and the arrival of the New Model Army. Local people saw their church damaged and no doubt suffered looting of houses and shops, which led them to hide their valuables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2010 08:37:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20300 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Castle Cary and area in two world wars</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/castle-cary-and-area-two-world-wars</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Men from Castle Cary and surrounding villages fought in both world wars. Volunteers eagerly joined up in 1914 and many others were rejected as unfit. Civilians also played their part and suffered in bombing raids at Ansford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a long tradition of service in the area. Volunteer corps were raised locally in the late 18th and early 19th century. In 1794 Castle Cary provided the first troop of Somerset yeomanry whose cavalry kept order during local food riots in 1795. In 1797 c. 50 volunteers formed an infantry company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A volunteer rifle corps was founded in 1860 with a resident drill instructor and in 1908 it became part of the Territorial Army. In the 1890s they had their headquarters and armoury in the old infant school and in 1900 a building on John Donne’s estate at Florida was used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the First World War Belgian refugees were a common sight in parts of Somerset and in the Second World War the town housed nursing units and Black American troops. No village escaped the war unscathed as many war memorials testify.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 15:46:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20187 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Education in Castle Cary area</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/education-castle-cary-area</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Schooling in Castle Cary and neighbouring parishes dates back at least until the 17th century although it was only in the early 19th century that education was made available to most children especially the poorest. Alford had a small school in the late 17th century and Barton St David in the early 18th. At Lovington and West Lydford charity schools were founded in the 18th century and Castle Cary had provision for poor children in the late 18th century. Church and private schools sprang up in Castle Cary and elsewhere in the 19th century. Even a small parish like Kingweston supported a school and Babcary had a private school. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to evening classes at the Castle Cary Board school there was a women’s adult school and a men’s school at the Boyd Institute, Castle Cary,  in the late 19th and early 20th century, based on bible studies. Many private schools took boarders, clergy sometimes took boys to prepare them for public school and some farmers took agricultural pupils. By 1900 when elementary education was compulsory only tiny parishes like Wheathill had no school. In the 20th century secondary schooling for all was increasingly provided and a school was built at Ansford. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However by the late 20th century rural schools have also been lost with declining populations and the move towards larger schools. Two large primary schools in Castle Cary and Keinton Mandeville and a small one in Lovington serve the needs of young children many of whom move on to Ansford School, although there are also secondary schools at Bruton and Street on the periphery of the area and many children are educated at private schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 11:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20157 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Nonconformity in the Castle Cary and Keinton Mandeville area</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nonconformity-castle-cary-and-keinton-mandeville-area</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite some early recusancy and nonconformity, dissent did not flourish in the area until the 19th century when it may have been encouraged by the growth of both working and middle classes. Of the major employers, Boyds of Castle Cary were strong supporters of Zion chapel in South Cary. Methodism was particularly successful and besides chapels and permanent congregations there were many lay Methodist preachers and Bible Christian ministers working in the area in the later 19th century and Primitive Methodists in the early 20th century. In the later 20th century many nonconformist chapels have closed but Methodism thrives at Castle Cary and Keinton Mandeville.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 10:24:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20151 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Shops and services in Castle Cary</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/shops-and-services-castle-cary</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Castle Cary grew and developed as a small industrial and market town, a number of shops and services provided for the needs of its inhabitants. The first record of a shop was in 1682. Shopkeepers in the later 18th century included London mercer Richard Gardner who took over a shop in 1780 but went bankrupt in 1791.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot;&gt;William Melliar (d. 1772) was an attorney in Castle Cary from 1750 or earlier and at least one solicitor practiced in the town throughout the 19th century. A barber was recorded in 1781, an apothecary in 1786 and a surgeon in 1790.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot;&gt;In the 1790s the presence of an auctioneer, two land surveyors, an attorney, a dancing master, a carrier, a post and excise office, a confectioner, a grocer, a watchmaker, two linen drapers, and a silversmith indicate that Castle Cary was by then a local centre for shops and services&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoNormal&quot;&gt;It still performs this function today with a wide range of independent shops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2010 07:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20116 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Castle Cary&#039;s markets and fairs</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/castle-carys-markets-and-fairs</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Castle Cary&#039;s market seems never to have been a success despite numerous charters and revivals. There were many rivals in the area and the town&#039;s development was slow before the 18th century and the growth of its textile industries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1633 the market was said to be ‘hardly of the middle size’ and it was regularly let out. In the later 17th and early 18th century the main commodity was sheep. Castle Cary was described as a market town in 1707 although the market was ‘paltry’. Attempts to revive the market in the 1850s following the building of the railway through the area had only limited success but have left the town a legacy in the form of a fine Market House more usually called the Town Hall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2010 09:48:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20109 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Inns of Castle Cary and neighbourhood</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/inns-castle-cary-and-neighbourhood</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Public houses were not only places to stay, eat or drink, but were also the venue for courts, parish meetings and entertainments of all kinds including puppet shows and assemblies as well as less respectable activities. The Castle Cary area has supported a wide variety of public houses down the ecnturies. They varied in size and importance from the Ansford inn to tiny alehouses in Castle Cary&#039;s side streets. In small villages they could be found in the centre of the village, like the Quarry at Keinton Mandeville or beside important roads like the Pilgrims Rest at Lovington. Some inns have remained in existence for centuries although relocated or rebuilt but many small alehouses were short lived. Some lost their licence for disorderly behaviour others simply went out of business. For many alehousekeeping was a part-time occupation or was carried on by women because the income was insufficient to support a family. There were also many unlicensed beer and cider houses often in private parlours or farm outbuildings whose history is more difficult to trace.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2010 09:29:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20099 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Castle Cary&#039;s linen and hemp industry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/castle-carys-linen-and-hemp-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Linenweavers were recorded at Castle Cary in 1726 and 1728 and from the 1790s large scale production of sailcloth and twine, no doubt encouraged by the heavy demands of warfare on the navy, developed in Ansford and then in the Torbay area of Castle Cary. Webbing, rope, cord and twine production continued until the later 20th century and was an important employer in the town.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2010 12:57:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20091 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parish fire engines: Castle Cary</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parish-fire-engines-castle-cary</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1762 the parish agreed, on the encouragement of the clergy, to provide a fire engine paid for out of the church rate with Ansford contributing.[1] In 1764 it attended the fire at Bruton Abbey.[2] The wardens paid for watering it in 1795, building an engine house in 1810, repairing the buckets in 1816, and oiling the pipes in 1841. The engine house was in the corner of the churchyard but by 1870 a building for the engine was rented from the lord of the manor at the street end of the drive to Manor Farm.[3] In 1893 the vestry ordered the overseer to sell the old fire engine, a primitive machine last used c. 1868, 13 buckets, and water cart and in 1895 the parish council demanded part of the proceeds.[4] The parishioners demanded a new fire engine in 1896 and later.[5] Both Boyd’s and Donne’s factories had fire engines which assisted at a major fire in 1914.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fire appliances appear to have been the responsibility of the water company after 1909 but in 1921 they were taken over by the parish council, which decided to form a fire brigade the following year.[7] A new fire station was built in 1959[8] on the corner of Millbrook Gardens, north of the church, and remained in use in 2001 with twelve retained firemen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;


	&lt;p&gt;[1]     SRO, D/P/cas 4/1/3; Parson Woodforde Soc. Jnl. IX (2), 8.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2]     Memoirs of Robert Clarke (1829), 12—13.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
		
			&lt;p&gt;[3]     SRO, D/P/cas 4/1/2—3, 13/2/4, 14/5/1; Castle Cary Visitor May 1900, April 1903; July 1912.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
			
				&lt;p&gt;[4]     SRO, D/PC/cas 1/1/1, 1/2/1; Castle Cary Visitor April 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
				
					&lt;p&gt;[5]     Castle Cary Visitor March 1896, April 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
					
						&lt;p&gt;[6]     Castle Cary Past and Present (1974), unpaginated.&lt;/p&gt;
						&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
						
							&lt;p&gt;[7]     SRO, D/PC/cas 1/2/2.&lt;/p&gt;
							&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
							
								&lt;p&gt;[8]     Som. CC. Lib. negatives 15943, 23160; SRO D/PC/cas 5/4/1; Living History Group, Time to Reflect, 124.&lt;/p&gt;
								&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
								&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2010 14:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20016 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Stocking making in Castle Cary, Somerset</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/stocking-making-castle-cary-somerset</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;There was a great demand for knitted stockings from the late 16th century and many were produced by Castle Cary stockingmakers who employed large numbers of people in the surrounding countryside.&lt;p&gt;In 1624 William Holland, a worsted stocking maker, said he had worked in the parish for 12 years making over £700 a year and setting poor people to work combing, spinning, making yarn, and knitting stockings. After a serious assault and stabbing in 1623 inflicted by William Kirton and his sons Daniel and Edward, who were later convicted, Holland gave up his trade and moved to London. His workers were said to be impoverished.[i]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Burge family of clothiers, hosiers, and stockingmakers was in business throughout the 18th century although one was bankrupt in 1741 and another, also described as a dealer and chapman, in 1808—9.[ii] The latter’s property included land at Torbay and a large house with workshops in South Cary described as suitable for a linen or stocking business.[iii] Another member of the family had a house in High Street in 1839 with a long extension to the rear which may formerly have been workshops.[iv] Seth Burge (d. c. 1752), also a maltster, insured premises worth £400 in 1749 and William, buildings worth £300 in 1751.[v] William Burge, stockingmaker, died in 1778 leaving property and £5,000 to his children and his implements to his youngest son. One of his grandsons became a barrister.[vi]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Edward Russ was a hosier in 1748 and Daniel White, another prosperous stockingmaker, died c. 1765.[vii] In the 1780s most of the poor were said to be employed in the manufacture of knitted stockings and the poor of North Cadbury were spinning and knitting for Castle Cary hose makers.[viii] Many of the 280 people engaged in trade and manufacture in 1801 were probably engaged in the stocking and linen trades.[ix] The stocking trade declined in the 19th century although a hosier was appointed tithingman in 1813.[x]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[i]     TNA, STAC 8/171/24; STAC 8/191/20.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[ii]     J.H. Thomas, ‘Economy and Society in Eighteenth-century Somerset’ PSAS. 141 (1998), 70; SRO, DD/YB 5, 8—9, 11; DD/X/FC 1, 3; DD/X/GC 18; ibid. Q/SO 15; Castle Cary Visitor May 1905.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[iii]     SRO, DD/FF 18/16.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[iv]     Castle Cary Visitor May 1904; SRO, DD/SAS (C/212), map 1808; ibid. tithe award.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[v]     SDNQ. XXX. 186; TNA, PROB 11/793.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[vi]     SRO, DD/BR/hk 1; TNA, PROB 11/1040; Parson Woodforde Soc. Jnl. XXX (2), 35—6.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[vii]     A.J. Webb, Som. Jurors 1748 (1994), 38; SRO, DD/YB 5.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[viii]     SRO, A/AQP 9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[ix]     Census.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[x]     Wilts. RO 383/321.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2010 13:54:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20015 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
