<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Timberscombe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/timberscombe</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Timberscombe&#039;s public houses</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/timberscombes-public-houses</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alesellers were recorded in Timberscombe from 1407 and one of its 19th-century public houses survives in the centre of the village.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 10:13:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23112 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Providence Chapel, Timberscombe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/providence-chapel-timberscombe</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Providence Bible Christian Chapel was built near the village mill by Edward Cording of Croydon in Carhampton and opened on 27 March 1836.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains open as a Methodist church&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 11:57:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22340 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mary Haynes of Timberscombe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mary-haynes-timberscombe</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mary Haynes and her sister Margaret who married Peter Elsworthy of Bickham must have made a great impression when they arrived at Timberscombe. They were two of the daughters of the wealthy Thomas Haynes of Southmead, Bristol and their clothing and jewellery must have made heads turn when they came to church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly Mary, who seems to have made her home with her sister, died young but her will gives us a glimpse into the possessions of a wealthy young woman of  the Civil War period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 08:34:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22303 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Timberscombe School</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/timberscombe-school</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Elsworthy or Ellsworth of Bickham in Timberscombe left £200 in 1714 to build a charity school and library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it was nearly a century before his wishes were at least partly fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, despite much litigation, scandal and financial difficulty the endowed school survived for nearly a century educating hundreds of local children until it was transferred to the local authority. The school survives today at the heart of the village.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 08:44:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22296 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Timberscombe and the Great War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/timberscombe-and-great-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The small parish of Timberscombe in the Avill valley south of Dunster, far away from the theatres of war, showed extraordinary patriotism following the outbreak of war in 1914. From a parish population of under 300 no fewer than 66 men joined up; sometimes several from the same family. They crossed the social divide from young labourer Samuel Tudball to the Honourable Robert Ryder, younger brother of the 5th earl of Harrowby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1919 the vicar declared that he would give his Easter offering towards a memorial in the church to those who fell or served in the Great War and on 11 April 1920 a war memorial tablet was dedicated at evening service containing the names of the 11 fallen and 55 others who served.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2012 16:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21233 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
