<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - somerset</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/somerset</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Betrothals in Somerset</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/betrothals-somerset</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Betrothal is just part of the modern wedding ceremony but in the medieval and later periods it was a separate social and legal contract. It played a part in royal family politics in the 15th and 16th centuries but was a fact of everyday life for all couples at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike marriages, betrothals were conducted by lay people often in private homes and gardens. We only find out about these practices when something went wrong and the church courts were called on to decide whether or not the parties were bound to each other.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 13:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24291 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Nettlecombe Church, Somerset</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nettlecombe-church-somerset</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has probably been a church at Nettlecombe since the late 13th century and by 1440 it was dedicated to the Blessed Virgin Mary. At that date it comprised chancel, nave, south chapel and tower, the last being a recent addition. The chapel was dedicated to St John the Baptist and was endowed as a chantry by Simon de Ralegh (d. 1440). The church was restored by Richard Carver c.1820 and more drastically between 1858 and 1870 by C E Giles under the guidance of the Trevelyan agent James Babbage who claimed the new clerestorey made the church look two centuries older.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 11:17:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20748 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Nonconformity in Carhampton and Withycombe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nonconformity-carhampton-and-withycombe</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;These two rural parishes have little evidence of protestant dissent before the 19th century and Wesleyan Methodism was slow to establish but in the hill areas at Rodhuish and Withycombe the Bible Christians attracted a following.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 10:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20728 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster Castle</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunster-castle</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dunster Castle on its hilltop site forms a dramatic eyecatcher from the road to Minehead or the West Somerset Railway. Although it bears little resemblence to the medieval castle and none at all to the first Norman building they probably inspired the same awe and admiration in visitors. Indeed the approach to the late medieval gatehouse was clearly designed to impress and to form a processional way for the owners and distinguished guests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dunster Castle has been adapted through the centuries from the stronghold of a powerful Norman baron to the administrative centre of a large estate, a gracious stately home, and now a top visitor attraction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 13:40:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20659 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s public houses</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-public-houses</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dunster has always been well served with alehouses and inns. As a market and cloth town in the medieval and early modern periods there was much business for alehouses. The earliest named public houses were Jeollestavern and Trottstavern belonging to William Dodesham in 1436, the George in 1463 and the Wynseseller in the early 16th century. In 1555 William Edwards and his wife Elizabeth were licensed to keep a tavern and sell wines backdated to 1553.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many tipplers or alehousekeepers in Dunster in the early 17th century. The two aletasters presented several for not sending for them to check their ale or their measures or for selling short. George Prolle and his wife were accused of keeping entertainment and drinking at their alehouse in service time in 1606. In Lent 1620 nine victuallers undertook not to sell meat and several tipplers in the 1620s were also butchers, a few were weavers, probably their wives ran the alehouses, certainly several widows were tipplers. In 1630 there were 13 in Dunster and one at Alcombe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numbers of licences remained high well into the 18th century although many inns closed with the decline in trade. Tourism created new demands. Tourism came early to Dunster and the Luttrell Arms was created with tourists in mind in 1779. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 11:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20635 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton police station</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulverton-police-station</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dulverton has a had a series of police stations, the current building a purely utilitarian building but in 1904 a very grand building was designed and built in Lady Street to accommodate the police, their prisoners and the magistrates&#039; court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 13:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20615 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton hydro-electric plant</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulverton-hydro-electric-plant</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;While many remote farms on Exmoor had wind and oil powered generators for electricity in the 20th century, only Dulverton had an ambitious scheme to harness the power of water.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 12:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20613 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Population and Migration: Exmoor 1841-1901</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/population-and-migration-exmoor-1841-1901</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1851 there were only 13 Dulverton people in Wales, mainly wives and servants, but by 1891 there were 102. In 1871 there were only seven Winsford and 90 Dulverton people in London but by 1891 there were 25 and 120 respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hawkridge people had not moved more than a few miles in 1851 but by 1891 of 93 people in England born in the parish 42 still lived there, 33 were in nearby parishes, and 18 were in London, Kent, and Essex. Most southern Exmoor people migrated as craftsmen, servants, or through marriage.  From the 1880s migrants came to work in the coalmines but earlier they came as bootmakers, building workers, ostlers, gardeners, painters and decorators. Exmoor men settled at Cadoxton, Glamorgan as shoemakers and labourers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12691 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Probate Inventories, Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/probate-inventories-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the purposes of the inventory was to determine the probate fees, so the inventory was valued. Many west Somerset inventories survive for the 17th and early 18th centuries and provide us with a striking glimpse of the wealth of Exmoor’s farmers and craftsmen. Whilst less rich in worldly goods than lowland households, Exmoor yeoman farmers at the time were prosperous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In rural areas less attention was paid to the house and its contents except for items of pewter, silver, or brass. Country people’s wealth was usually in their livestock and crops, or for a widow or retired farmer, life savings let out at interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12690 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Place Names of Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/place-names-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most Exmoor place names are of Old English origin and represent features of the landscape. Valleys derive their names from their nature or from the animals there. Smallacombe in Molland was narrow and Liscombe in Dulverton had a &quot;loose&quot; (pigsty). Such names may be English translations of the older British. Many names refer to water, revered by Celtic peoples, such as Hawkwell (crooked stream), Dulverton, Wellshead, or Ludslade (valley of the torrent), Exford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Names ending in &quot;cott&quot;, &quot;ley&quot; (leah, a glade) or &quot;worthy&quot; indicate Anglo-Saxon settlement or places taken over by them. &quot;Worthy&quot; names are often attached to large farms, believed to be early Anglo-Saxon, which may have utilised late prehistoric intakes from moorland. The &quot;ley&quot; names are mainly in Molland, a well-wooded parish, including Bremley (bramble glade), and around Winsford Hill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12689 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
