<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Ledbury</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/ledbury</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Elizabeth Barrett Browning</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/elizabeth-barrett-browning</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Elizabeth Barrett was born in 1806, the eldest daughter of Edward Moulton Barrett, a merchant with connections in the West Indies. Elizabeth was born at Coxhoe Hall, county Durham.  Another three sisters and eight brothrs were to be added to the family. In 1809 the growing family moved to Hope End, a few miles north of Ledbury. Her father built a striking mansion (since demolished) on the 475-acre estate. They were regular attenders at the Congregational chapel behind the High Street in Ledbury. The family enjoyed riding and walking in the countryside, which also inspired some of Elizabeth Barrett&#039;s poetry. A riding accident as a young girl left Elizabeth with serious health problems. In 1828 her mother, Mary, died, and four years later financial difficulties forced her father to sell Hope End. The family eventually settled in Wimpole Street, London, and it was there that she met the poet Robert Browning. They married in 1846 and moved to italy, where their son was born.  Elizabeth died and was buried in Florence in 1861.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although she never returned to Ledbury after leaving in 1832, the scenery of her childhood appears in a number of her verse, notably the long poem &lt;em&gt;Aurora Leigh.&lt;/em&gt;. In the 1890s the town decided to honour its famous  (almost) resident by naming the newly-built ireading room the Barrett Browning Institute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12332 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rental of c.1288</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rental-c1288</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This volume, known as the &#039;Red Book&#039;,  contains rentals for the bishop of Hereford&#039;s manors. Each entry is in a different hand and they seem to have been written at different times, but internal evidence suggests that the rental was made shortly after 1288, during the episcopate of Bishop Swinefield, although probably incorporating older lists.  Rentals are valuable sources of information about people and property. They include personal names and sometimes give titles or occupations, which shed light on the social structure of a place. The wealth of individuals and of the whole community can be gleaned from the size of properties held and the amounts of rent paid. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ledbury rental in the Red Book begins with Borough, the town, the entries laid out street by street, beginning with Southend, shown above. Each tenant is named, with a  brief description of what property they held - everything from 1/4 of a burgage to 3 burgages together - and how much rent they owed at each of the four quarter days. Following the total for the Borough (£27 10s. 7 1/2 d.) there is a list of all the tenants of the Foreign, or rural part, of the parish. This lists those holding land by knight service and the free and copyhold tenants, with the rents and services owed by them. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;                                                           &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;          &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12331 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>George Paul, headmaster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/george-paul-headmaster</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;George Paul was headmaster of Ledbury Boys School for over twenty years, from 1885 until 1917. He did much to improve the reputation of the school and played an important role in several organisations in the town. He was especially involved with Church Lads Brigade and the town fife and drum band.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12330 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ledbury through the Census</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ledbury-through-census</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every ten years since 1801, except in 1941, there has been a general census of the population of England and Wales. The original enumrators&#039; books survive from 1841 and are available for public inspection after 100 years. The originals are kept at the National Archives at Kew, but county record offices have microfilm copies and it is also possible to search for information through many genealogy websites.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The England&#039;s Past for Everyone volunteers have transcribed all the information from the enumerators&#039; books for the town of Ledbury from 1841 to 1901. The town was only part of the enumeration sub-district, which covered the whole parish. To provide a consistent basis for analysis a carefully delineated area was chosen, which encompassed the extent of the town in 1901. This area can be seen in the accompanying map.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once transcribed, the details entered into a database, which enabled an analysis to be made of the population of Ledbury over a sixty-year period. Changes in population size, age and gender distributions, occupations and migrations are all discussed in the accompanying article. The information gathered has also been used to inform other articles on this website and the writing of &lt;em&gt;Ledbury: a market town and its Tudor heritage. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12329 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Homend, no. 42</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/homend-no-42</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This timber-framed, two storey house, now a restaurant, is one of the most prominent in The Homend, principally due to its two-storey jettied porch that stands well forward of the main front. This feature may be a slightly later addition to what is a relatively unadorned building with square panels and a ground floor frontage. The shop windows were introduced after the 1930s. There was formerly a carriageway through the south end of the building. Some remodelling took place in the 18th century when the large window with semicircular head was inserted in the front and sides of the porch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12328 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Homend, no. 24</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/homend-no-24</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now housing a clothes shop, this is an early 17th century building that was remodelled in the late 18th century. It is of two storeys and originally the first floor projected on a shallow jetty. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12327 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Homend, no. 10</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/homend-no-10</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now a modern shop, the previous building on this site was an early 17th century timber framed house with jettied first and second floors and remodelled in the late 18th century. It was demolished after 1930. Part of the lost building can be seen on a photograph of the other demolished building on the street, no. 2 Homend.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was for many years in the late 19th and early 20th centuries the newsagents and fancy goods shop run by Lewis Jones and then by his daughter Edith.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12326 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Homend, no. 4</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/homend-no-4</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now a dry cleaner&#039;s, this is an early 17th century timber-framed house that was refronted in the later 18th century. To the rear there is a 17th century timber-framed range that is visible from Bye Street. It has been noted as containing panelling and an early 18th century fire surround.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;SO 7106 3774 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12325 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Homend, no. 2 (demolished)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/homend-no-2-demolished</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;No. 2 Homend has been demolished and the site is now occupied by the Barrett Browning Memorial Institute, built 1892-6. Judging from surviving photographs and paintings, the original building was a substantial timber-framed structure of two storeys and attics with three bays. The ground floor had two shop fronts with jetties, which were almost certainly designed for storage of goods, loading and unloading by hoist from wagons drawn up beneath the south end of the building. At the rear it was a tan house for many centuries, belonging to the Hankins family over many generations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12324 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Homend, no. 67</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/homend-no-67</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a 17th century building probably of two bays, remodelled in the 18th century with a new brick front sporting four brick pilasters. It is likely there was a central front door between the two central pilasters and that this was reached by means of a short flight of stone steps. There is an alleyway through the south end of the building where some of the later timber framing can be seen.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12323 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
