<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Building / Monument</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/building-monument</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Early Years of All Saints church, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/early-years-all-saints-church-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1902 Church of England services were held at St Michael’s Church and at two mission rooms: the Reading Road Mission Room serving the east of the town; and the Newtown Mission Room, otherwise known as the May Street Mission, serving the west of the town that was rapidly expanding due in part to the arrival of Thornycrofts in 1898.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the parishioners’ meeting on 9 April 1902, the vicar of Basingstoke, the Revd Cooper-Smith referred to the rapid growth of the parish, especially in the Cliddesden Road area. He noted that the Roman Catholics, the Primitive Methodists and the Wesleyans were each adding to their accommodation. He then announced that his sisters had purchased a piece of land on the corner of Victoria Street and he proposed that a temporary iron church should be erected on the site to serve the south of the town. He estimated that the cost of erecting the church and fitting it up would be in the region of £1,000.[1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August 1902 the parish magazine reported that the contractors, Messrs Humphries, had completed the erection of the church and there was ‘good reason to hope that internal structural fittings (gas, heating, etc.) would be completed during the present month’. The vicar appealed for funds for fitting and furnishing the temporary church, and for subscriptions for a permanent church.[2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The October issue of the parish magazine read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Progress is being made with the fitting of the temporary Iron Church, and it is hoped to open it for the Service at the Season of All Saints. It is thought that the Dedication may well be associated with that beautiful Festival, and the Church, when open, may be known as “All Saints Church”.’[3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On All Saints’ Day, Saturday 1 November 1902, the temporary Iron Church was dedicated. The Bishop of the Diocese was ‘so deeply immersed in the multiplicity of pressing duties’ that it was ‘impossible for him to come in person and take the Dedication Service’. The Bishop of Guildford had therefore undertaken to dedicate the church, but ‘by Doctor’s orders has been obliged to cancel all engagements’ and the Bishop of Southampton had also been ‘ordered to give up all duties for three months, the result of strain and over work’. However, as the Bishop of South Tokyo, the Rt. Revd Dr William Awdry, was in England, he agreed to take the service.[4] (His nephew, Revd W. Awdry, was the author of the Thomas the Tank Engine books.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Day of Dedication began at St Michael’s with services of Holy Communion at 7 and 7.45 am. The dedication service began at 3 pm by which time all 130 seats allocated to the congregation were occupied. After the procession of the clergy and the choir, proceeded by the cross-bearer, had passed up the aisle and taken their places at either side of the altar, ‘a considerable number of worshippers came and stood in the aisle and the entrance gangway’.[5]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his address the Bishop told the congregation that they:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘must continually bear in mind that in the course of a few years the Church must give place to a more permanent and worthy structure. It was clean and fresh now, but it would not always meet the requirements of the neighbourhood. In a few years, ten at the most, they would need a larger and more permanent Church, and as the town grew there would then be the need for a beginning in another part.’[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Revd L.C. Hamerton was appointed as the first priest-in-charge of All Saints. The programme of services with effect from Sunday, 2 November 1902 was as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SUNDAYS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy Communion                   8 am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evensong and Sermon                        6 30 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WEDNESDAYS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy Communion                   7 45 am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matins and Litany                   10 am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FRIDAYS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matins and Litany                   10 am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evensong and Address           7 pm.[7]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following year a fund, entitled the ‘All Saints’ Building Fund’ was opened at the Basingstoke branch of the Capital and Counties Bank for the contributions to the building of a permanent Church.[8] In his New Year greeting in 1904, Revd Cooper-Smith announced:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Designs for a permanent Church have been submitted by an eminent Architect, Mr C Hodgson Fowler, F.S.A. who has the charge of the Cathedrals of Durham and Lincoln, and whose plans for rebuilding the Spire of Rochester Cathedral have just been accepted by the Chapter. I hope that 1904 will see some definite steps taken for the creation of at least a portion of the permanent Church.’[9]&lt;/p&gt;
During 1904 the church acquired an organ to replace the hired harmonium that had provided the instrumental music of the church. Revd L.C. Hamerton left the parish to take up the living of Ashbury in Berkshire and was replaced as priest-in-charge of All Saints by the Revd A.H. Thorold. In December, Revd Cooper-Smith explained that the urgent need for enlarging the Church of England schools had prevented progress with the All Saints’ Building Fund in the past year.[10]
&lt;p&gt;In 1905 Revd H.W. Boustead became vicar of Basingstoke and for several years after his arrival there was no mention of building a replacement for the temporary Iron Church and no apparent progress was made to add to the building fund. Rev. Ernest Lang replaced Revd Thorold as priest-in-charge of All Saints in 1906 until September 1909 when he was replaced by Revd G.M. Wheeler.[11]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In January 1910 Revd Wheeler announced that the All Saints’ church roll had made a beginning with 44 members, and had begun to make their offerings for the permanent Church.[12] By May the fund stood at £169 10&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;. 2&lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;.[13] In the same year an All Saints Enlargement Fund was started, and in November, Revd Wheeler thanked ‘all those who have enabled us to enlarge the Church so quickly’.[14] The building plans for the extension to the Iron Church, dated 13 November 1910, show that an extension was made to the west of the building, and the porch was removed from the south side of the building and re-erected in its present (2017) position at the new west end. The materials were timber and iron for the walls and roof and there was a new floor level with the existing floor. The architects were Wallis and Smith acting for Revd Boustead and churchwardens.[15] The cost of the enlargement was £69 19&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;. paid to Goodall and Sons, contractors, and £2 2&lt;em&gt;s&lt;/em&gt;. paid to Arthur Smith the architect.[16] The lengthening of the Church enabled 48 seats to be added.[17]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In March 1912 Rev. Wheeler left to take up appointment of vicar of Hindhead and was replaced as priest-in-charge by Revd A.P. Le Maistre.[18]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1913 saw the beginnings of the Great Debate over whether resources should be deployed towards building a new Church in the West before a permanent Church for All Saints could be built. Revd Boustead was strongly in favour of the former. He argued:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘In the Western district of the town, many of those who live there and work at Thornycrofts never see a Church at all. They pass up Sarum Hill to shop in the town – they pass to their work or school at Deep Lane … It so happens that a site for a future Church is secured opposite the Grammar School [in Worting Road]. The Bishop of Guildford who visited the Parish some time since with a view to examining what provision should be made to meet the growth of the town westward, advised that a Church should be erected on that site.’ [19]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Parish Meeting on 21 April 1913 opinion was divided between those who felt that they were ‘pledged to a permanent Church for All Saints before anything [else] was done’, and those who supported Revd Boustead’s argument that a Church in the west was more urgent as the West District was ‘by far the largest in Basingstoke’ and the May Street Mission could never hope to satisfy ‘the spiritual needs of the West’.[20]   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notes of the Basingstoke Easter vestry meeting in 1914 recorded that strong convictions continued to be held on either side of the argument:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Naturally, All Saints, as a flourishing, if small, community, demands a Church. For this they have waited these 12 years … True worship is made as difficult as possible by the heat from the iron furnace in summer, and the cold, mitigated by the fumes of coke, in winter … Others of the Committee felt that the largest district of the town was in the west. Something must be done there, and that at once. To wait till £4,000 could be raised for All Saints might mean waiting for many years, and the opportunity for forward and Mission work in the large West End district would be lost.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a spirit of compromise (or indecision) the Committee decided that an appeal be made for funds to secure a temporary church for the West as well an appeal for funds to build a permanent Church for All Saints.[21]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that meeting, Revd Alexander Hall, a retired priest living at Coombehurst, Cliddesden Road, came forward and offered £5,000 to build a permanent church for All Saints. On 6 October 1914 the Committee approved the architect’s plans for the new church.[22]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable work to start on the permanent Church, the temporary Iron Church had to be moved from its original position in Southern Road to its present position in Victoria Street. The last service before its removal was held on the first Sunday after Easter 1915.[23] The work of dismantling and rebuilding the Church was, ‘promptly done, and with the willing help of some members of the choir and other assistants, among them a Belgian refugee, the Altar was brought up from the Parish Church, where it had found a temporary resting place’. The first service on the new site was held on the fourth Sunday after Easter, 2 May 1915.[24]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 6pm on Thursday, 15 July 1915 the Bishop of Winchester laid the foundation stone for the new Church. This was the first time that the Bishop of the diocese had visited Basingstoke for a similar purpose since 1510.[25] The parish magazine noted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘The original offer was for a Church for 500 people costing £5,000. Owing to the increased cost of materials, modifications and improvements made on the original plans, and also to the change of building material from brick to stone, the Church and its furniture will, no doubt, cost over £10,000. The Parish must, therefore, feel most grateful to Mr Hall, not only for his original offer, but for the magnificence of his further generous gift … It had been arranged to ask the congregation to subscribe for the Bells for the New Church. A day or two before the service Lieut-Col. John May telephoned from the nursing home in which he is, that he desired to have the privilege of presenting the Bells himself.’[26]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in 1915 Revd Le Maistre resigned as priest-in-charge of All Saints and was replaced by Revd T.F. Fuller.[27]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout 1916 and into 1917 the parish magazine provided updates on the progress of the building of the new All Saints. It recorded that Mr Blencowe had given the Lady Chapel window in memory of his wife.[28] In July 1916 it reported that the construction of the roof had begun and that most of the wood was from the Imperial forests of Archangel and bore the mark of the Russian Eagle.[29] In February 1917 it reported that on Wednesday 17 January 1917 the peal of nine bells, given by John May, were blessed before being raised to the tower. The Latin inscription on the tenor bell, when translated into English read, ‘To the Glory of God, John May gave me and my companions as a gift to this Church during the Great War of 1916’. It was decided that, that as the costs of the Church was being met by Revd Hall, the sums subscribed in years past to the building fund should be applied towards the cost of an organ for the new church.[30]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revd Boustead confirmed that the organ in the Iron Church was, ‘quite unsuited to lead the singing in the new Church, being too small in scale and of insufficient depth and solemnity of tone’. He said that a suitable organ was in the factory of Messrs Hunter of Clapham, which had become a munitions factory. It would cost £635.[31]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new All Saints Church was dedicated on Thursday 27 September 1917 by the bishop of Winchester. The service took place at 5 p.m. by which time, according to the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, ‘the Church was packed to the utmost capacity, many being obliged to stand’. Among those in the congregation were the Mayor and members of the Town Council wearing their robes, together with the borough officials, John May, and the ministers of the Congregational, Wesleyan, Primitive Methodist, Countess of Huntingdon’s and Baptist churches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bishop and clergy, having robed in the Iron Church, entered the church followed by ‘a long procession of choristers’. The bishop, wearing cope and mitre, and the choir and clergy proceeded up the aisle chanting the 24th Psalm ‘a fine effect being obtained by the alternation of men’s and boy’s voices’. The bishop said prayers at the chancel steps and at the high altar. He then proceeded to the Chapel of our Lady and dedicated the altar there, after which he returned to the chance and pronounced the sentence of dedication. As the congregation left the church at the end of the service, the new bells rang out for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Gazette&lt;/em&gt; provided a brief history of events leading up to the service, in which it said that the foundation stone was laid in 1915, ‘about six months after the builders had set to work, so that more than two years and a half have elapsed since the building was begun’.[32] An earlier guide to All Saints explained:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘A splendid set of elderly stone masons and labourers, all over 60, plodded on, excellent at their work, but far too old to be of use in any warlike occupation.’[33]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the service of dedication, the bishop explained that, owing to lack of time and legal delays, it was not possible to complete the legal formalities that would enable to the act of consecration to take place. That would follow at a later date.[34] On the afternoon of Thursday, 8 November 1917, the Bishop of Guildford attended All Saints and signed the legal instrument of consecration.[35]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parish magazine said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘The original plans in brick, and of less stately dimensions, were changed by the Architect, Mr Temple Moore, at the request of Mr Hall, to the wonderfully effective stone Church … The style if English Gothic 14th Century. The glass in the great East Window is the gift of Mr Hall, the subjects being the Life of our Blessed Lord. The East Window of the Lady Chapel is the gift of Mr R.C. Blencowe (former Churchwarden of this Parish). The figures represent Our Lady holding the Holy Child, while in the two side lights figures of St Mary Magdalen and St Elizabeth with St John Baptist.’[36]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final cost of the Church was about £18,000, nearly all of which was borne by Rev. Hall.[37] The craftspeople involved in the building and decoration of the church included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Architect: Temple Moore, Hampstead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contractors: Benfield and Loxley, Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stained Glass: Burlison and Grylls, London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decorative Painting: Mr C. Head of Colchester after designs by Mrs Leslie Moore of Hampstead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bells: The Whitechapel Foundry of Mears and Stainbank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marble Work: Mr R. Colles of Kilkenny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iron Work: Coldron and Son of Lincolnshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organ builders were unable to make the necessary alterations and build it up in the organ chamber as they were doing munition work and were ‘simply not allowed by government to leave their work or to touch the organ which stands ready in their factory’.[38]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on 5 June 1919 the new organ was erected and played for the first time at the service of Sung Eucharist at 11 o’clock. In the afternoon, Basil Johnson, the Director of Music at Eton College, gave a recital in which he ‘skilfully shewed the organ’s great possibilities. The parish can well be proud of an instrument of so great beauty and richness of tone’.[39]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Clarke, 2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;ABBREVIATIONS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BMM  Basingstoke Monthly Magazine, the Basingstoke Church of England parish magazine. Bound copies from 1865 are at the Hampshire Record Office in the series 46M74/PZ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H&amp;amp;BG  Hants and Berks Gazette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HRO  Hampshire Record Office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] BMM, May 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] BMM, August 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[3] BMM, October 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[4] BMM, November 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[5] H&amp;amp;BG, November 8, 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[6] BMM December 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[7] BMM November 1902.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[8] BMM June 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[9] BMM January 1904.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[10] BMM June, August, October and December 1904.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[11] BMM September and October 1909.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[12] BMM January 1910.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[13] BMM May 1910.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[14] BMM November 1910.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[15] HRO, 58M74/BP529.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[16] BMM June 1911.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[17] BMM June 1915.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[18] BMM April 1912.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[19] BMM March 1913.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[20] BMM May 1913.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[21] BMM May 1914.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[22] BMM June and November 1914.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[23] BMM May 1915.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[24] BMM June 1915.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[25] BMM July 1915.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[26] BMM August 1915.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[27] BMM October 1915.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[28] BMM June 1916.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[29] BMM July 1916.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[30] BMM February 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[31] BMM May 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[32] H&amp;amp;BG September 29, 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[33] ‘&lt;em&gt;A modern church – All Saints, Basingstoke&lt;/em&gt;’ by HWB, no date.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[34] H&amp;amp;BG September 29, 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[35] &lt;em&gt;Reading Mercury&lt;/em&gt;, November 10, 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[36] BMM October 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[37] &lt;em&gt;All Saints Church Basingstoke: A Guide&lt;/em&gt; (1998).&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[38] BMM October 1917.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[39] BMM July 1919.&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2017 08:48:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25070 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Holland bridge is the most recent bridge to cross the Holland River (or Holland Brook), and the furthest downstream. Maps of 1594 and 1603 indicate that there was no route at that time across the Gunfleet estuary which would therefore have still formed a major barrier to land communications along the coast. Then the first crossing point was at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, some one and a half to two miles inland from the sea. As a result, there was probably much communication in small boats across the Gunfleet estuary and along the coast in the sheltered waters of the Gunfleet Channel (now known as the Wallet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, probably sometime towards the end of the 17th century the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs decided to construct a sea wall across the mouth of the estuary which was becoming silted up. As the former Gunfleet estuary behind the sea wall was converted to marshland pastures (although still liuable to winter flooding), so the course of the Holland River became channelled into a water way, now known as the Holland Brook, that ran through its lowest part. The river water, resulting from the many thousands of acres draining into the Holland Brook, was discharged into the sea via a sluice built in the new sea wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the reclamation works were considered advanced sufficiently, a causeway was built across the reclaimed land and a new bridge, named Little Holland bridge, was built over the brook. The date of the bridge is uncertain, but it was first recorded in 1727. The bridge was locally significant for it was the first time that a direct road communication existed between the settlements of Little Holland and Great Holland on the two sides of the old estuary. Chapman and Andre&#039;s map of Essex in 1777 shows the nature of the land half a century after the bridge was first built. A road led from Little Holland Hall into the marhses and then crossed the Holland brook by the new bridge before travelling northwards through the marshes and up the valley side towards Great Holland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach road to the bridge through the marshes in 1777 was depicted as a series of dashes indicating that the route was rather impermanet or uncertain and liable to flood. Chapman and Andre often depicted roads in this way when they crossed common land or where routes were poorly demarcated; another example is their map of the route through the marshes east of Fan bridge. The present Holland bridge appears to date from the early 20th century and until rceent years it had a metal sign indicating where the Great and Little Holland parish boundaries met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map, 1&quot; (1838).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/ST 20 (Map of part of TendrinG level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tednring Levels Commissioners&#039; Map (early 20th century; in private ownership).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 18:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24008 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rice bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rice-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rice bridge is the earliest recorded crossing point on the river now known as the Holland Brook, and one of the furthest inland. It was in existence by 1319 when an Agnes de Risbregge (Agnes of Rice Bridge) was recorded in a taxation return for Little Clacton. Her name probably meant that she lived at or near the bridge. The bridge also gave its name to the surrounding land as an estate called Risbridge or Rosebridge was recorded in the later 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bridge was built on a route that was probably locally important in the Middle Ages. Not ony did it connect the two parishes of Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, but also the manors on either side of the river that were owned by the bishop pf London and his cathedral church of St Paul&#039;s. In the Domesday Book of 1086 the bishop held the manor of Clacton (comprising both Great Clacton and Little Clacton)  while all of Thorpe-le-Soken, Kirby-le-Soken and Walton-le-Soken were held by the Dean and Chapter of St Paul&#039;s (the cathderal clergy). By 1127 on one side of the bridge lay Little Clacton park, a deerpark owned by the bishop, while on the other side lay Thope park, a deerpark owned by the Dean and Chapter. The road over Rice bridge therefore connected the two church estates and their hunting parks. Possiby the huntsmen ranged across both parks quite freely, otherwise the deer could have swum across the river to safety!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name Rice bridge is itself very informative, as it probably originates in the Old English words &#039;hris&#039; (meaning brushwood) and &#039;brycg&#039; (meaning bridge or causeway). The crossing may therefore have started out as a timber bridge or causeway and it probably continued in that form for many centuries. In 1612 the tenants of Thorpe Park and Clacton Park were ordered to &#039;make&#039; the bridge (perhaps from timber available in the deer parks), and it was still described as a wooden footbridge in 1783. County maps from 1594 and 1603 show a main road from Little Clacton and Weeley towards Thorpe, Kirby and Walton that crossed the Holland River at what must be Rice bridge, although it was not named. A survey of the Holland Levels by the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs in 1703 named Rice bridge, and many maps from the 18th century such as that by Chapman and Andre in 1777 show the same route. The present brick built Rice bridge dates from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (Cambridge, 1935), p. 336.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P. Morant, The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex (1768), Volume II, p. 475.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M. Gibbs (ed), The Early Charters of St Paul&#039;s (Camden Society, 3rd series, lviii, 1939), no. 60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London Metropolitan Archive, Guildhall Library, MS. 25416/3; MS. 9531/6, f.192v.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), Q/SR 199/79, 154, 155 (Quarter Sessions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/DHw E14 (A true survey of ye Levll or Flatts ... several parcells of land endamaged at or near Gun-Fleet Haven, 1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 20 (Map of part of Tendring Level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 17:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24006 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fan bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fan-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fan bridge is the second earliest rcorded crossing point on the river now known as Holland Brook (formerly Holland River). Further downstream than Rice Bridge, the river valley here was broader in character and more liable to flood. Fan Bridge (often spelt &#039;Fann&#039; or &#039;Fenn&#039;) was first recorded in 1509 and it was also depicted on Norden&#039;s map of 1594; its name is likely to mean fen or marsh. The present flood plain of the Holland Brook probably indicates the width of the river in medieval times, and at Fan bridge it is nearly one tenth of a mile across. The site of the bridgemust therefore have been approached by a causeway through the marsh before a bridge spanned the main channel of the Holland Brook. Indeed, the original route may have been on a different alignment and changed when the bridge was built, which might explain the curious dog-leg in the approach road from Little Clacton (see map).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chapman and Andre map of 1777 shows that the fens still existed all around the bridge at that date. The same map reveals that the approach road through the marsh to the west of the bridge (Little Clacton side) was relatively short, but that on the other (Great Holland side) it was longer and shown as a series of dashes indicating that the route was impermanent and liable to flood. Chapman and Andre often depicted roads in this way  when they crossed common land where routes were poorly demarcated. A good example is the track through the middle of Cooks Green in Little Clacton, to the west of Fan Bridge. The name Fanbridge Common was recorded between about 1600 and  1800, revealing that the fens next to the bridge continued to be used for common grazing at certain times of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probable later date of Fan Bridge, compared to Rice Bridge, may have several explanations. This was certainly a more difficult and marshy location for a bridge, and in earlier centuries when the Gunfleet estuary was more open to the sea it may have been an impractical location. In addition, Fan Bridge was located on a more minor local road linking the parishes of Great Holland and Little Clacton. On the west side between Clacton village and the bridge lay the hamlet of Cooks Geeen, while on the east between Great Holland village and the bridge lay Great Holland Common (or Jeffries Common). These greenside settlements were minot and traffic between them was probably not extensive; in the Middle Ages and later Little Clacton and Great Holland manors were also in different ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In later centuries the bridge was apparently maintained by the parishes of Little Clacton and Great Holland. In 1776 the Little Clacton parish surveyors (the parish officials in charge of highways) painted posts at the bridge, and in 1795 they built a new bridge of timber and brick (although it was not named). According to a survey of the Tendring Levels in 1783 the bridge was constructed of brick. In 1808 Great Holland&#039;s parish surveyors accounted for the demolition of the old bridge and the erection of a replacement. In 1821 the Little Clacton surveyors carried out work on &#039;Holland Bridge&#039;, presumably meaning Fan Bridge (rather than the true Holland Bridge between Little Holland and Great Holland). It is not known how long the 19th-century brick bridge lasted. The present brick bridge appears to date from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (Cambridge, 1935).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/DHw E14 (A true survey of ye Levell or Flatts .... several parcells of land endamaged by a breach at or near Gun-Fleet Haven, 1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 19 (Map of part of TendringLevel, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/P 80/21/1, 2 (Little Clacton Parish Surveyors&#039; Accounts, 1769-1807, 1813-35).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/P 396/21/1 (Great Holland Paroish Surveyors&#039; Accounts, 1804-40).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 16:42:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24004 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Beaumont Quay Lime Kiln</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/beaumont-quay-lime-kiln</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beaumont Quay and similar landing places along the Essex coast were chiefly used for the export of local agricultural produce to London. However, the barges also brought back return cargoes and these were mainly building materials (such as stone, flint or bricks) or soil improvers such as manure and chalk (limestone). The manure was collected in London (both from the capital’s horses and human ‘night soil’) and the chalk on the return journey from quarries along the Thames estuary in both Essex and Kent. The main reason that farmers wanted to apply chalk was to correct high levels of acidity in the soil and therefore improve the uptake of major plant nutrients such as nitrogen and to maximise crop yields. It could also provide a source of calcium and magnesium for growing plants. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the chalk could simply be spread on the farmland it was more efficient burn the chalk at high temperature in a kiln which led to the release of carbon dioxide and created a product called ‘quicklime’. When the ‘quicklime’ was mixed with water (a process known as ‘slaking’) it was turned into a stable powder form of lime which could then be spread on the land. The use of lime for agricultural purposes was described in Sir Anthony Fitzherbert&amp;#039;s Boke of Husbandrye, in 1523, but these activities became increasingly important during the age of agricultural improvement in the 18th and 19th centuries. There was also demand for lime for use in lime mortars in the building industry in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lime kilns were therefore a natural addition to the facilities alongside many of the small Essex quays, wharves and landing places. Although many were built only a few have survived, and the kiln at Beaumont Quay is built to an East Anglian (mixed-feed) design which is fairly rare. It is a circular red brick building within an earthen mound, and is some 2.5 metres high and about 13 metres in diameter. From the main entrance you can access a barrel-vaulted circulation passage around a central combustion chamber. On the other side of the mound another smaller rectangular opening was probably a ventilator that allowed the operators to regulate the draught to the kiln. The central combustion chamber had an opening for lighting the kiln, two others for raking out the lime and ash. The kiln was fired with wood and coal, and alternative layers of fuel and chalk would be added from outside via the opening at the top of the kiln. The chalk would turn to lime at about 900° C and fall to the bottom of the kiln where it could be raked out. The kiln was probably in continuous use, and the quay would have large heaps of chalk and coal ready for processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;br /&gt;
J. Moore, ‘Beaumont Quay’, Colchester Archaeological Group Bulletin, 54 (2014), pp. 8–12.&lt;br /&gt;
English Heritage Listing: Beaumont Quay, Hamford Water: a 19th century quay and lime kiln. List entry Number: 1020688 (See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://list.historicengland.org.uk/&quot;&gt;http://list.historicengland.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 18:59:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23922 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The history of St Mary’s Church, Eastrop</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/history-st-mary%E2%80%99s-church-eastrop</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The story of Eastrop Church is about how one of the smallest churches in the diocese grew to be one of the biggest. The church was enlarged in four stages: in 1835, in 1886, in 1912, and in 1996. It is possible that the change in 1835 was made because of the poor condition of the church. That was certainly the case in 1886. The changes in 1912 and 1996 were made because the existing buildings were too small to accommodate the number of worshippers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2015 18:26:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23266 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fairfields Board Schools, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fairfields-board-schools-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former site of the sheep fair on high ground in the south of the town was given by the Corporation in 1885 for the Board Schools to accommodate 1,310 pupils.[1] The initial plan was to have one school for boys, one for girls and infants but the design soon changed to mixed infants in one building and seniors housed on two floors in an adjacent detached building.[2] The foundation stone was laid on 29 November 1886 by George Freeman Dunn, Chairman of the School Board. Other members of the Board listed on the stone are Richard Sterry Wallis (Vice Chairman), Revd Canon Millard, Edward Adams, Edwin Charles White, Charles Pinder and Thomas John Edney. Francis Samuel Chandler was the clerk. Charles Bell of London was the architect and local builder Henry James Goodall was the contractor. The schools opened to children in February 1888.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schools are still in use in 2014, one as a primary school, the other as a creative arts centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a full history of the education at the school refer to Basingstoke Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] J.R. John, &lt;em&gt;Fairfields Schools, Basingstoke (1888-1979),&lt;/em&gt; (1979), 11.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] Hants RO (HRO), 22M88/1&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2014 15:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23005 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Lutterworth</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-lutterworth</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lutterworth is a small market town in south Leicestershire, close to the borders of Warwickshire and Northamptonshire. It had a number of educational charities, which supported two schools for boys and one for girls, and also provided apprenticeships for poor children. Under a scheme prepared by the Endowed Schools Commissioners in 1874, these charities were merged to create the Sherrier public elementary school (built in 1876) for boys, girls and infants. Lutterworth Grammar School, originally for 50 boarders and 30 day-pupils, also owes its beginnings to the original charities, and opened in 1881.  Lutterworth (Secondary) Modern school opened in 1966.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lutterworth was one of the last parishes in Leicestershire to become part of the so-called &#039;Leicestershire Plan&#039;, which introduced comprehensive education across the county&#039;s secondary schools in stages between 1957 and 1969 through a high-school/upper-school structure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 15:13:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22954 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ibstock Probate Material, 1701-1720</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1701-1720</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibstock is one of Leicestershire&#039;s largest villages. It is in the west Leicestershire coalfield area, and both coal mining and clay extraction for brick-making have shaped its size and character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other mining villages in this area, nonconformity was strong. The village had one of the very few British schools in the county (affiliated to the non-denominational British and Foreign Schools Society), in contrast to most Leicestershire villages, where the school was closely tied to the Anglican church. Plans of the British School show that it had the sloping floor beloved by educationalist Joseph Lancaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probate inventories reveal a diverse community lived here in the late 16th, 17th and early 18th centuries. Some people had substantial wealth, often in money and bonds (loans to others) rather than farming assets. The quantity and range of goods in Samuel Goadby&#039;s shop (1705) are similar to those found in the shops of market towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1640-and-earlier&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1640 and earlier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1641-1660&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1641-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1661-1680&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1661-1680&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1681-1700&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1681-1700&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 10:12:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22589 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Farleigh Congregational Chapel</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/farleigh-congregational-chapel</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This chapel served the parish of Farleigh Wallop where the Congregational cause was established in 1900. Initially, services took the form of cottage meetings. In the course of time, however, ‘as members increased, the services were conducted at … [a] farm, by kind permission of Mr Cole.’ Then in 1906 a purpose built chapel was constructed. It was opened with considerable fanfare on Thursday 6th September by Miss Sarah Jane Wallis the Mayoress of Basingstoke, who had donated half of the cost. The chapel was located at Foxhall some distance from the main settlement on a site owned by the Earl of Portsmouth who ‘offered it on a 999 years’ lease at a nominal rent.’ The simple building was ‘of corrugated iron, with a patent felt roof, for which … [was] claimed the advantage of keeping … [it] cool in hot weather. At the rear end … [was] a shed for cycles etc., … [for] preachers and visitors from distant churches. The interior … [was] matchboarded, and … [it could] accommodate nearly one hundred people.’ In her remarks the Mayoress commented that it was now ‘comparatively easy … for those who live in villages as well as in towns to hear the Gospel of the grace of God.’ At a public meeting held later in the day, Alfred Capes Tarbolton, the minister of the parent church - London Street in Basingstoke, observed that although ‘it was only a small building, … it was well sometimes to compare the small with the great. He had thought of Solomon’s temple as compared with their little chapel. Although there were no glittering jewels or outward adornments, yet the spiritual life and glory of their services might exceed that of Solomon’s temple.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first few years after it was opened, services were held every Sunday evening and in the afternoon there was a Sunday school. There was also a fortnightly Mother’s Meeting. After a promising start, however, it was not long before the cause was struggling. Like many rural chapels the removal of families who had played a crucial role in its activities created difficulties and resulted in the closure of the Sunday school. Thus, by 1914 Farleigh was already being described as a ‘weak cause’. The chapel was ‘temporarily closed’ from 1918 to 1920. It reopened in 1921 and hosted well-attended harvest thanksgiving services during the first half of the 1920s. The roof was repaired and a stove installed. However, in 1927 the London Street deacons decided to abandon the work at Farleigh and the chapel was closed permanently, just over 20 years after it had been opened. It is not clear what happened to the building, but today there is little evidence that a chapel ever existed on the site which is covered with trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[All quotations are from the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, September 8, 1906.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2013 14:49:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22261 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
