<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Minehead</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/minehead</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Minehead and the West Indies</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-and-west-indies</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 17th and early 18th centuries Minehead&#039;s extensive overseas trade embraced the West Indies and the names of Barbados and Jamaica were associated with the lucrative tobacco trade as well as more mundane cargoes like cured herring and potatoes. The downside was piracy and shipwreck and some Minehead men faced death far from home.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2019 08:41:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25678 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead gas and electricity works</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-gas-and-electricity-works</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the later 19th century Minehead’s growth put pressure on fuel supplies. Also better-off visitors expected the same comforts they had at home including gas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 1900s electricity was seen as desirable. Two companies based in Minehead supplied both fuels to the town and surrounding communities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 11:21:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23150 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead&#039;s water supply</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mineheads-water-supply</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like any community Minehead needed water and this was traditionally supplied by springs and streams and later also from wells but the growth in tourism strained resources to breaking point and it is no coincidence that the Minehead Waterworks Company was formed in 1874, the year the railway arrived.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 13:56:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23090 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead banks</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-banks</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During Minehead’s days as an important trading port mercantile families provided each other and other people with credit. However, by the later 19th century there was sufficient demand from residents and visitors for a number of retail banks to establish branches in the town.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 14:20:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23053 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Street Lighting in Minehead and Dunster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/street-lighting-minehead-and-dunster</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We take street lighting for granted but it was slow to reach many parts of Britain and some communities have never had street lighting and do not desire it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the mid 19th century the area’s growing popularity with visitors, often from towns where street lighting was commonplace, probably fuelled demands for lighting in the area. One of the main reasons for creating the Minehead Gas Light and Coke Company in 1868 was to provide street lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minehead is fortunate is having many preserved early street lamp standards both gas and electric.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 10:22:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23045 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead Market</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-market</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minehead market was always overshadowed by that at Dunster but has its own interesting history and a fine Edwardian market house.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 15:32:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22907 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Smuggling in the Minehead port area</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/smuggling-minehead-port-area</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Minehead port area, which stretched from the Devon boundary to Shurton Barrs near Stogursey, was full of small creeks and landing places where goods could be illegally landed. Such goods might be luxuries but were usually basic commodities like salt and soap. Smuggling was not just a question of evading paying duty but also harbour dues for the upkeep of quays, restrictions on foreign imports in war, restrictions on cattle movements during cattle plague and laws against dumping of cheap Irish manufactures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 11:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22659 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead Harbour Administration</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-harbour-administration</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Minehead-harbour&quot;&gt;Minehead harbour&lt;/a&gt; belonged to the Luttrells and was run by harbourmasters. The Crown also had an interest in the form of the Customs and later the Coastguard. Finally a lifeboat service was established to improve the rescue of mariners from shipwrecks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Coastguard and the lifeboat continue to serve the coastal waters around Minehead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 10:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22654 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead harbour</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-harbour</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Minehead harbour is a well known feature of the seaside resort offering shelter for pleasure boats, fishing trips and the occasional excitement of a visiting steamer or paddle boat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, four hundred years ago it was a thriving commercial port with foreign trading ships, passenger boats and military transport visiting the quay. Even in the early 20th century coal and fish were landed regularly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2013 08:58:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22649 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Minehead: the seaside resort</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/minehead-seaside-resort</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tourism began in a modest way in the late 18th century and by the mid 19th century as the port declined Quaytown&#039;s houses opened their doors to holidaymakers. The railway, opened in 1874, brought in more visitors. Hotels were built and carriage proprietors, photographers and shopkeepers gained much of their income from the summer influx of tourists. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/somerset/work-in-progress/minehead&quot;&gt;Minehead &lt;/a&gt;began to grow many houses were built with a few to letting rooms in the summer. In the 1920s many people moved to Minehead to set up business to cash in on the tourist trade and builders bought land for houses and hotels but some failed during the Depression. Although the traditional seaside resort went into decline in the late 20th century, Minehead continues to be a popular place for holidays and retirement. Its economy still depends heavily on tourism; Butlin&#039;s was the largest employer in the town with over 200 employees in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 08:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22091 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
