<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Burford</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/burford</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>East Side</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/east-side</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opposite Nos. 1–2, former commercial use can be seen in Weavers and Tiverton Cottages. Much of the street&#039;s east side, however, is taken up by the former almshouses and by Vick&#039;s Byways Garage. Opposite the Old Vicarage are Ford Close and Emmanuel Cottage, another late 18th- or 19th-century cottage pair; each have long gardens, the former now displaying a Chinese influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 11:10:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22000 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>West Side</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/west-side</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This near-continuous run of cottages begins with Nos. 1–2 , where stonework shows that a first-floor central casement has been removed. The central dormer was probably shared between the two attics, with a central partition forming the window&#039;s central mullion. Beyond, Homeleigh and No. 4 display a rusticated treatment typical of the mid 20th century; No. 4 has a memorial stone to Nan Meadows (1912–88), a former District Nurse and (latterly) peace campaigner. Fortey’s Close, perhaps the most stylish house in the street, is followed by Nos. 5–8, built in the 18th century as two mirror-image cottage pairs but long since converted into two houses. The street&#039;s western side ends with Russell Cox&#039;s vicarage of 1937, an excellent example of sympathetic 20th-century building in Burford.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 08:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21998 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Market Houses and the Tolsey</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/market-houses-and-tolsey-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Timber-framed and set on octagonal stone columns, the Tolsey is typical of a broad range of market houses, town halls, and moot- or guildhalls found in most small market towns. Tree-ring dating of its roof timbers has shown that it was built in or soon after 1525, though a similar building may well have stood here earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its primary function was as a market house – the name ‘Tolsey’, found particularly in the Cotswolds and Wiltshire, suggests a place where market tolls were collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like similar structures elsewhere the Tolsey had other uses. Town meetings may have been held in the upper chamber, and the back part housed the town lock-up, with the stocks, pillory, and ‘couckinge stowle’ standing outside in the 1580s. A reading room (lit by a gas chandelier) was opened here in the 1860s, and a town museum in 1960.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 09:48:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20688 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fulling and Finishing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fulling-and-finishing-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;After weaving, cloth had to be fulled to shrink and strengthen the fabric, providing greater resistance to wear and weather. The process originally involved immersing the cloth in a trough filled with water and chemicals (such as fuller’s earth and urine), which helped remove any grease or dirt, and compressing it by foot or hand. The introduction of water-powered fulling mills in the later 12th century mechanised and speeded up the process, with two wooden hammers replacing human effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 08:44:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20683 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sheep and wool processing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sheep-and-wool-processing-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sheep farming was an important part of the Cotswolds economy by the Roman period. Medieval Cotswold sheep were a distinctive breed, producing fine white wool which was highly valued for cloth manufacture: in the 15th century, out of 50 grades of wool produced by English sheep that of the Cotswold ranked third. Probably they were smaller than modern breeds: long-necked and fine-limbed, with short curly fleeces and a woolly forelock from which the nickname ‘Cotswold Lion’ derived. Certainly their fleeces weighed far less than their modern counterparts, about 1½ pounds compared with 9 pounds or more. Medieval fleeces were sold by the sack, each of which weighed 364 pounds and contained the wool of some 240 sheep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 08:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20682 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Burford and the Arts and Crafts Movement</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/burford-and-arts-and-crafts-movement</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among its most famous proponents was William Morris (1834-96), who, with others in his circle, produced hand-crafted wallpapers, textiles, furniture and books aimed at recapturing the spirit and quality of medieval craftsmanship. The movement developed a strong architectural dimension, dedicated to reviving traditional vernacular architecture based on local materials, traditional local styles, and fine craftsmanship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Burford, such ideas were shared by many of the artists, writers and intellectuals who moved into the town c.1900-30, and exerted a strong impact on the town&#039;s social tone and appearance.  Among other interests they shared an enthusiasm for English folk dancing: the folksong revivalist Cecil Sharp was a visitor to both Kelmscott and Calendars.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12717 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Market Houses and the Tolsey</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/market-houses-and-tolsey</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its primary function was as a market house - the name &#039;Tolsey&#039;, found particularly in the Cotswolds and Wiltshire, suggests a place where market tolls were collected, and the building overlooked the town&#039;s main medieval market area on High Street, allowing officials in the upper chamber to oversee the proceedings. Its location allowed it to face down Sheep Street as well as High Street, though in fact the building turns its back to Sheep Street: presumably by 1525 the market area there had become less significant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12715 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fulling and Finishing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fulling-and-finishing</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fulling shrank the cloth considerably - in the early 16th century it was accepted that a 32-yard cloth would shrink to 25 yards - so as it dried, the fabric had to be stretched (or tentered) on fulling racks to restore some of the length and remove wrinkles. The matted effect of the cloth was often enhanced by raising the nap with teasels (since iron-toothed combs were considered too rough), and clipping the resulting fuzz with large shears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12714 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Urban Inns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/urban-inns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burford&#039;s earliest surviving inn building is the front part of the New Inn at 124 High Street (built c.1401). More extensive traces of courtyard layouts survive at the George Inn, the former Bear Inn, and within the later structure of the Bull. The best preserved is the George, where the gateway leads to two parallel courtyard ranges converted into cottages in the 19th century (Figure 91).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 18th and early 19th centuries competition for the coaching trade affected the inns&#039; architecture. The Bull&#039;s new brick and stone façade (probably added c.1715)was no doubt aimed at making it unmistakable to the visitor arriving by coach, and the rebuilding also enabled the heights of the rooms in the street range to be increased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12713 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dating Vernacular Buildings</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dating-vernacular-buildings</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medieval houses usually followed a common arrangement whose traces can sometimes be detected in what appear to be much later buildings. But the best way to date the original construction is through the internal roof structure. Where this remained structurally sound it was replaced less often than visible features, and can be roughly dated by comparing carpentry techniques - though as these changed slowly, particularly in country areas, the science is not precise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest advance in building-dating has come from the development, over the last few decades, of scientific tree-ring dating or dendrochronology, which can provide an accurate date for when oak timbers used in a building were felled. The technique is based on the fact that each tree-ring (representing a year&#039;s growth) is of a different width, depending on growing conditions that year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12712 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
