<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Compton Chamberlayne</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/compton-chamberlayne</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Compton Chamberlayne Field Book, 1597</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/compton-chamberlayne-field-book-1597</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1597, shortly after Sir Edward Penruddocke completed his purchase of the manor of Compton Chamberlayne, he commissioned this survey of the entire parish. Detailing the occupation and use of every single parcel of land and every building, it provides us with an extraordinary snapshot of life in the village at the end of Elizabeth&#039;s reign. Besides the dimensions and crops contained in the parish&#039;s fields, it reveals tensions and frictions between neighbours, and the beginnings of the assult on the parishioners&#039; customary rights by the family that would dominate the village for the next 300 years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 03:39:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20599 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Compton Park, Compton Chamberlayne</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/compton-park-compton-chamberlayne</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has probably been a park at Compton Chamberlayne since at least the 14th century, possibly even earlier. The park was landscape and greatly altered by Capability Brown in the 18th century. Formal lakes and gardens that had lain to the east of Compton House were replaced as the park was given a more rustic, arcadian feel; two large, shapeless lakes were formed, and trees were planted on their slopes. The old carriageway which had run from Dinton through the park to the what is now the A30 was closed, and the cottages that lay along it were removed; a holloway and housing platforms are still visible in the park where they had lain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the middle ages, the park was maintained for the hunting of deer, and it continued to be a deer park in the 1860s, when there was a herd of 90 deer. The park continues to operate as a shooting park.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 03:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20596 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Compton House, Compton Chamberlayne</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/compton-house-compton-chamberlayne</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compton House is an extensive house that stands at the heart of Compton Park in the village of Compton Chamberlayne. It was built by Sir Edward Penruddocke in the late 16th century, following his acquisition of the manor. It stands on the site of the original manorial complex, adjacent to the parish church, and may incorporate material from the medieval farmhouses that stood on the site previously. The house would be the ancesteral home of the Penruddockes until 1930. It was much altered in the 18th century, at the same time that Compton Park was transformed by Capability Brown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 03:10:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20593 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
