<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Moorland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/moorland</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Ibstock Probate Material, 1701-1720</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1701-1720</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibstock is one of Leicestershire&#039;s largest villages. It is in the west Leicestershire coalfield area, and both coal mining and clay extraction for brick-making have shaped its size and character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other mining villages in this area, nonconformity was strong. The village had one of the very few British schools in the county (affiliated to the non-denominational British and Foreign Schools Society), in contrast to most Leicestershire villages, where the school was closely tied to the Anglican church. Plans of the British School show that it had the sloping floor beloved by educationalist Joseph Lancaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probate inventories reveal a diverse community lived here in the late 16th, 17th and early 18th centuries. Some people had substantial wealth, often in money and bonds (loans to others) rather than farming assets. The quantity and range of goods in Samuel Goadby&#039;s shop (1705) are similar to those found in the shops of market towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1640-and-earlier&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1640 and earlier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1641-1660&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1641-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1661-1680&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1661-1680&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1681-1700&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1681-1700&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 10:12:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22589 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Uncovering Exmoor&#039;s Prehistoric Past</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/uncovering-exmoors-prehistoric-past</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;rteleft&quot;&gt;Evidence for past environments is contained within many buried archaeological deposits, but upland peat bogs and valley mires are especially rich locations. They contain a stratified record of flora and fauna which is highly detailed and crucially, datable, through Carbon 14 dating methods. In a sense they are a chronological document, or archive, of environmental change. Taken together the landscape of southern Exmoor conveys a story of continual settlement expansion and contraction around the moors as climatic, economic and social circumstances permitted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rteleft&quot;&gt;The unfavourable climate and soil and the existence of Exmoor Royal Forest protected large parts of Exmoor&#039;s moorland from cultivation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12682 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Early Wearmouth Settlements</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/early-wearmouth-settlements</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until 1719, the area that was to become Sunderland was divided into two parishes which served administrative as well as religious purposes. These parishes in turn were subdivided into a number of townships or vills, with small settlements distributed throughout the townships. The two parishes took their names from the larger villages near the mouth of the river where medieval parish life was centred. South of the river the pre-Conquest South Wearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wiremuthe australem&lt;/em&gt;)eventually became known as Bishopwearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wermouth Episcopi&lt;/em&gt;) since this township, together with the small medieval borough of Sunderland and the outlying vills of the parish were held by the bishop of Durham. On the northern bank of the river the site of the Anglian monastery, formerly known as Wearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wiremuthe&lt;/em&gt;), subsequently became known as Monkwearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wermouth monachorum&lt;/em&gt;) since this settlement and its two adjacent townships were, from the late 11th century, in the hands of Durham priory.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12242 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The parish of Monkwearmouth</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parish-monkwearmouth</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ancient parish of Monkwearmouth comprised the townships of Monkwearmouth, Fulwell, Southwick and Hylton. Part of the township of Simonside, situated in the parish of Jarrow, was also attached to the medieval parish. With the exception of Hylton, the townships of the parish of Monkwearmouth were in the hands of Durham Priory. The manor and lordship of Hylton belonged to the Hilton family, prominent tenants in chief of the bishop. In ecclesiastical terms, however, Hylton fell under the priory&#039;s jurisdiction, its chapel a dependent of the mother church of Monkwearmouth.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12222 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The parish of Bishopwearmouth</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parish-bishopwearmouth</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The medieval parish of Bishopwearmouth comprised the townships of Bishopwearmouth, Ford, Bishopwearmouth Panns, Ryhope, Silksworth, Tunstall and Burdon. It included the borough of Sunderland which was part of Bishopwearmouth parish until 1719.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12221 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Winsford Hill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/winsford-hill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The hill today is a large stretch of open heather moorland between the rivers Barle and Exe. It is crossed by several roads, notably that from Dulverton to Exford. It is famous for the Caratacus Stone and the wild Exmoor ponies. Cattle grids on the roads stop the ponies straying from the hill over which they roam freely. Every age has left its mark on the hill from prehistoric barrows to quarries. During the medieval and early modern periods there were enclosed fields on the hill for cultivation. Traces of the ridges and furrows left by ploughing can still be see in places.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11815 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Exmoor ponies</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/exmoor-ponies</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exmoor ponies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Exmoor pony lives wild in several parts of Exmoor. It is a descendant of ancient wild ponies which became isolated on Exmoor. Sir Thomas Acland is credited with preserving the pure breed when he founded what is now the Anchor herd, which grazes Winsford hill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the ponies live freely on the moors all year eating grass, heather, rush, and gorse, their breeding is carefully controlled by their owners. The herd is rounded up once a year at autumn gatherings. Ponies are branded with a mark, an anchor in the case of the Winsford herd, and a number. Young ponies are then removed for sale and domestication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For several centuries ponies from the moor were sold at an annual fair in Bampton. In the 19th century pony wrestling was a popular sport. In the early 20th century ponies were widely used by Exmoor farmers for herding livestock and getting around their land. The Exmoor Pony Society was inaugurated in 1921 and registers all ponies&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11771 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Early Farming: Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/early-farming-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ridge and furrow near Withypool, evidence of medieval arable cultivation of the moorland.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11761 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Anglo Saxon Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/anglo-saxon-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This stream, a tributary of the Devon Yeo and the boundary between Molland and Twitchen, may have been the ancient western boundary of the Anglo-Saxon royal manor and hundred of Molland.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main settlements have names reflecting the natural world. Most Exmoor place names are of Old English origin and record landscape features, such as Hawkridge and Withypool, and especially means of communication Brushford (causeway ford), Exford, Dulverton (the settlement by the hidden ford), and Twitchen (the cross road). Most ford names are associated with larger settlements. Fords were essential in an area with so many rivers and streams and the emphasis remains on the ford element of names.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11728 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
