<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - HowTo</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/howto</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Highworth pot</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/highworth-pot</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Roman Highworth ceramic pot was discovered in the village of Highworth in June 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its location is just 4 miles away from &quot;Ermin Street&quot; which was a main Roman road which was a vital connection between the settlements of Gloucester, Silchester and Circencester. The pot was found with other smaller Roman artefacts and was positioned in an upright position suggesting it had been placed in the pit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is of a significant heavy weight as it takes several people to lift. The pot measures 2ft tall by 1 1/2 feet wide, with a 12 inch diameter mouth. The pot was used for storing milk this has been proven by the residue. It is going to be put on display in the Swindon Museum and Art Gallery.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 18:57:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21548 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Wiltshire and Swindon History Centre</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/wiltshire-and-swindon-history-centre</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Wiltshire and Swindon History Centre is located in Chippenham. It holds a vast amount of material on the history of Wiltshire and Swindon. It is open to members of the public who are interested in tracing ancestors, the history of their parish or town, educational projects and other heritage based matters. The centre holds over 40,000 photographs of the county as well as newspapers dating back to the 18th century and detailed maps from 1773 to the present day. These show changes in infrastructure and population density of all Wiltshire settlements. The Centre has different departments which are accessible to all. These include archives, local studies, archaeology, conservation, Wiltshire Buildings Record and the Victoria County History.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WSHC is open Tuesday to Friday 9.30am – 5.30pm and then 9.30am – 5.00pm each week and more details are provided on their website: www.wiltshire.gov.uk/history-centre.htm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 15:50:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21410 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Thomas by Launceston</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-thomas-launceston</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is one of the three Launceston parishes our volunteers are currently working in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 16:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>CoralP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20797 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Burford and the Arts and Crafts Movement</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/burford-and-arts-and-crafts-movement</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Among its most famous proponents was William Morris (1834-96), who, with others in his circle, produced hand-crafted wallpapers, textiles, furniture and books aimed at recapturing the spirit and quality of medieval craftsmanship. The movement developed a strong architectural dimension, dedicated to reviving traditional vernacular architecture based on local materials, traditional local styles, and fine craftsmanship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Burford, such ideas were shared by many of the artists, writers and intellectuals who moved into the town c.1900-30, and exerted a strong impact on the town&#039;s social tone and appearance.  Among other interests they shared an enthusiasm for English folk dancing: the folksong revivalist Cecil Sharp was a visitor to both Kelmscott and Calendars.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12717 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Market Houses and the Tolsey</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/market-houses-and-tolsey</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its primary function was as a market house - the name &#039;Tolsey&#039;, found particularly in the Cotswolds and Wiltshire, suggests a place where market tolls were collected, and the building overlooked the town&#039;s main medieval market area on High Street, allowing officials in the upper chamber to oversee the proceedings. Its location allowed it to face down Sheep Street as well as High Street, though in fact the building turns its back to Sheep Street: presumably by 1525 the market area there had become less significant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12715 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fulling and Finishing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fulling-and-finishing</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fulling shrank the cloth considerably - in the early 16th century it was accepted that a 32-yard cloth would shrink to 25 yards - so as it dried, the fabric had to be stretched (or tentered) on fulling racks to restore some of the length and remove wrinkles. The matted effect of the cloth was often enhanced by raising the nap with teasels (since iron-toothed combs were considered too rough), and clipping the resulting fuzz with large shears.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12714 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Urban Inns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/urban-inns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burford&#039;s earliest surviving inn building is the front part of the New Inn at 124 High Street (built c.1401). More extensive traces of courtyard layouts survive at the George Inn, the former Bear Inn, and within the later structure of the Bull. The best preserved is the George, where the gateway leads to two parallel courtyard ranges converted into cottages in the 19th century (Figure 91).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 18th and early 19th centuries competition for the coaching trade affected the inns&#039; architecture. The Bull&#039;s new brick and stone façade (probably added c.1715)was no doubt aimed at making it unmistakable to the visitor arriving by coach, and the rebuilding also enabled the heights of the rooms in the street range to be increased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12713 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dating Vernacular Buildings</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dating-vernacular-buildings</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Medieval houses usually followed a common arrangement whose traces can sometimes be detected in what appear to be much later buildings. But the best way to date the original construction is through the internal roof structure. Where this remained structurally sound it was replaced less often than visible features, and can be roughly dated by comparing carpentry techniques - though as these changed slowly, particularly in country areas, the science is not precise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The greatest advance in building-dating has come from the development, over the last few decades, of scientific tree-ring dating or dendrochronology, which can provide an accurate date for when oak timbers used in a building were felled. The technique is based on the fact that each tree-ring (representing a year&#039;s growth) is of a different width, depending on growing conditions that year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12712 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sheep and Wool Processing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sheep-and-wool-processing</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sheep were washed and shorn in June and the wool sorted for sale. To be used for cloth manufacture it was carded and spun, either on a spindle and distaff or, from the early 14th century, on a spinning wheel. The woollen yarn produced was then woven. The earliest medieval looms were narrow, limiting the size of the finished cloth, but in the mid-13th century the broadloom was introduced, allowing cloths measuring 24 by 1¾ yards (21.9 x 1.6m) to be produced by two weavers sitting side by side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12711 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Hidden Graffiti</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/hidden-graffiti</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is more likely to have been written by a Flemish worker employed to plaster or panel the room, who may not have intended the texts to be seen. The persecution of Protestants in France and Holland had led to a steady stream of immigrants seeking safety - and employment - in England. It seems that these texts may have been concealed as soon as they were written, making their dark tone seem subversive. The Adam and Eve text was taken from a sermon given by the Lollard priest, John Ball, at the time of the peasants&#039; revolt in 1381. Having asked the question &#039;when Adam dug, and Eve span, were there then any nobility?&#039;, Ball exhorted his listeners to &#039;cast off the yoke of bondage, and recover liberty&#039;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12708 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
