<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Industrial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/industrial</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Gower&#039;s Iron Foundry, Hook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gowers-iron-foundry-hook</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former iron foundry in Hook run by the Gower family on the London Road, opposite the Old White Hart Inn started production in 1826. It has intermittently come within Odiham and Newnham parishes, but being located in the centre of the village it employed men and boys from Hook as well as Nately Scures and Newnham. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From their origins in Suffolk, the Gower family created a thriving business with award winning, innovative designs of seed drills, turnip and mangold cutters and other agricultural equipment having many distinguished customers across England. The foundry survived an arson attack in 1851 and was taken over in 1912 by the Hazell family who retained the Gower name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final closure date is unknown but in 2004 the site was sold and 74 houses built on the site named Foundry Close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed history and images of some of the equipment click on the link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2019 15:22:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25710 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Wallis and Steevens Engineering Company, Basingstoke 1856-1981</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/wallis-and-steevens-engineering-company-basingstoke-1856-1981</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wallis and Steevens was a family business, founded in Basingstoke in 1856 to sell agricultural machinery in the rural hinterland. By the 1880s they marketed Basingstoke built machines world-wide. In the 20th century, the company manufactured road rollers for the home and export markets and guaranteed their market share by major design innovations in the 1920s and 1960s. The company closed its Basingstoke business at Daneshill  in July 1981.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engine to the left (works no. 7498, reg. no. HO 5629), was manufactured in 1916 for the Ministry of Munitions and was used on various duties associated with WW1 including hay tying of fodder for horses which was then shipped to fighting forces in Europe.  In 1951 it was working in Duncton Quarry, Petworth, Sussex where conditions caused excessive wear and tear on its gears. In 1958 it was offered to the National Traction Engine Club to help raise funds for its restoration. A raffle was held which was won by a teenage boy who chose to have the £100 cash prize instead as his family had nowhere to keep the engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1963 to 1977 it stood unused with various owners until 2002 when extensive restoration began and it made its first working appearance in June 2008. This photograph was taken in June 2018 at the Bloxham Steam Rally, Oxfordshire where it was driving a log sawing bench.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For images of other machines produced by the company see the links below and for a detailed history of the company and its production see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/hampshire/work-in-progress/modern-economic-history-trade-and-industry-1860-2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 10:24:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25429 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Portals Paper Mills, 1718-1995: Papermakers to the Bank of England</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/portals-paper-mills-1718-1995-papermakers-bank-england</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Portals paper mills have had a profound economic and social effect on Overton parish. In the south of England, it is most unusual to find a single dominant industrial employer over such a long period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Portal, a Huguenot refugee from France, was awarded the contract to make hard-wearing banknote paper for the Bank of England in 1724. The company grew steadily, eventually outgrowing the limited space at Laverstoke Mill, 1km beyond the boundary of Overton parish, and a new factory was built at Overton Station in 1924. Portals became the largest security paper company in the world, employing about 1,550 people in the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 18:14:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25258 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Roughmoor mill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/roughmoor-mill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unlike the other Bishops Hull mills Roughmoor mill was not on the river Tone but on one of its northern tributaries. Like many mills in the area it had many uses over its history from cloth production to flour milling.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 08:17:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25178 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fideoak and Longaller Mills</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fideoak-and-longaller-mills</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both Fideoak mill and Longaller mill in Bishops Hull were on Fideoak manor and were fulling mills in 1578 and presumably until the 17th century. The main buildings of the latter survive with the leat.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 07:52:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25172 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bishops Hull Mills</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bishops-hull-mills</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The medieval manor mill at Bishops Hull went out of use in the 1340s but by the late 16th century the parish was home to a large number of mills, all but one on the river Tone. Frethey mill was in use from the mid 16th to early 18th centuries and Burchin mill, a former fulling mill, was a grain mill by 1585 but was ruinous by the 1780s.  Like all rural mills near Taunton they suffered competition from the development of the medieval manor mills near the Castle into the Town Mills.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 07:29:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25167 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Probate Material 1651-1660</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-probate-material-1651-1660</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One inventory and thirteen wills survive for this period, only one document is held in the Hampshire Record Office (HRO), the remainder are held at The National Archives (TNA).  All bishoprics were abolished in 1646 following Parliament’s victory in the First Civil War 1642-6 and wills were proved in the Prerogative Court of Canterbury (PCC), archived in The National Archives, until the Restoration of 1660. Unusually, in Winchester, officials kept the probate service going in the late 1640s. Some of the wills reflect the difficult times of religious dissent and Civil War whilst others indicate considerable wealth with property held in Basingstoke, Berkshire and London. In fact at any time wills with property in more than one diocese had to be proved at the PCC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document but which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire. Links to all of the transcriptions are below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-roger-weston-senior-yeoman-1653&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Roger Weston, senior, yeoman (Will and Inventory), 1653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-thomas-south-elder-clothier-1653&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas South, the elder, clothier (Will), 1653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-holmes-yeoman-1653&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Holmes, yeoman (Will), 1653&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-aylwyn-gent-1654&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Aylwyn, Gent (Will), 1654&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-richard-george-woollen-draper-1656&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard George, woollen draper (Will), 1656&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-tempule-farmer-1656&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Tempule, farmer (Will), 1656&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-herne-clothier-1657&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Herne, clothier (Will), 1657&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-pell-gent-1657&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Pell, Gent (Will), 1657&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-jane-dovey-widow-1657&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jane Dovey, widow (Will), 1657&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-james-wyther-gent-1658&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;James Wyther, Gent (Will), 1658&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-stephen-webb-minister-1660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stephen Webb, minister (Will), 1660&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-richard-everadevered-tanner-1660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Everad/Evered, tanner (Will), 1660&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-kew-haberdasher-and-soldier-1660&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Kew, haberdasher and soldier (Will), 1660&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2017 09:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25055 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>An introduction to Holland Haven </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/introduction-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, Holland Haven is the place where the Holland River (now the Holland Brook) once ran out into the North Sea between Clacton and Frinton in Essex.  This estuary was called the Gunfleet and it was once wide enough for boats to sail through it and in 1677 for a whale to become stranded there.  Towards the end of the 17th century a sea wall was built across the mouth of the estuary, the land behind the wall was reclaimed from the sea and converted to marshland pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographically, the Essex coastline is characterised by a series of creeks, inlets and estuaries which in the past have allowed access for small boats to sail inland.  When the Gunfleet estuary was open to the North Sea, small boats may have been able to sail up river as far as Thorpe-le-Soken. Small wharves and landing places were built along the banks of Holland River allowing crops grown on nearby farms and other local produce to be loaded easily onto boats and carried along the river, out to sea, into the Thames estuary and into London. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote and out of the way landing places could also be used to avoid customs control and the isolated marshes at Holland were notorious in the past for smugglers even after the estuary was reclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can get an idea of what it would have been like in the Gunfleet estuary by looking at nearby Beaumont Quay on Hamford Water which was used as a landing place for boats from the Middle Ages to the 1930s.  From here barges were loaded with produce such as corn, hay, cheese and timber, and brought return cargoes, mainly building materials or soil improvers such as manure and chalk from London, Kent and Essex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature in this landscape would have been tide mills, different to water mills or windmills as they use the ebb and flow of the tides to power the waterwheel.  The Essex coastline was dotted with this ancient type of mill with sites identified at nearby Thorrington, St Osyth and Walton-on-the-Naze.  The work of tide mills was often supplemented by a nearby windmill such as at Thorrington and Walton-on-the-Naze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that alongside agriculture, the copperas industry was also important locally in the 17th and 18th centuries.  Copperas stones (which were actually iron pyrites) were washed out of the London Clay cliffs onto the shore and converted to copperas (green vitriol) at factories known as Copperas Houses.  Copperas was used for various purposes such as dyes and inks.  The stones were collected by local people all along the coast from Clacton, Frinton and Walton, and were also dredged up from the Copperas Bank off the coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reclaimed estuary is now used for leisure pursuits, including the Holland Haven country park and Frinton Golf Links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	You can explore&lt;strong&gt; An introduction to Holland &lt;/strong&gt;Haven using the suggested activities and assets below.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use maps to introduce your study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a modern map to locate the Holland Haven area by first viewing Europe, UK, East Anglia, the Essex coastline (naming the North Sea, London and the Thames estuary), and finally Clacton, Walton and Frinton.  Use these key places to locate the course of the Holland Brook and notice the marshes, follow the length of the Brook - it looks a bit like a ladder.  Find other places of interest such as your school, local beaches and houses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use one or more of the maps &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Norden 1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chapman and André 1777 &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ordnance-survey-map-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OS 1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ordnance-survey-map-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;to find out what was it like here in the past.  Compare the historic map with your modern map.  You can use the map showing &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/land-liable-flood-holland-levels&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;land liable to flood on the Holland Marshes&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;as an indication of the size of the former estuary.  These are some suggestions to help you explore what is the same and different:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for local place names and spellings.  It might help to read them out loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the shape of the roads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the shape of the coastline and waterways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locate crossings over the river and if you are using more than one map check if they are on each one.  What does this tell us about when they were built?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see any buildings? What are they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extend this activity by tracing or overlaying the maps chronologically to locate, describe and label the changes that have happened in the landscape including the shape of the estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was life like here for people in the past?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use images&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/copperas-pickers-shoreline-harwich&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; “Copperas pickers” on the shoreline at Harwich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;photos&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/thorrington-mill-1929&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thorrington Mill &lt;/a&gt;(1929), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/beaumont-quay-1960-showing-rose-and-warehouse&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beaumont Quay &lt;/a&gt;(1960) &lt;/strong&gt;and documents&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/stranding-monstrous-whale-1677&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;‘A monstrous whale’&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/poaching-holland-marshes-1609-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Poaching on Holland Marshes &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;and&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/possible-landing-places-gunfleet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Possible landing places on the Gunfleet Estuary &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;and choose one or more&lt;strong&gt; maps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about what you would like to know and group your questions under headings (for example, work, food, events).  Look at each source for the information it gives you to answer your questions.  Move on to another source and add in more information.  Remember that there are additional assets for you to use on other parts of the VCH Explore site (link to home?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go on a fieldtrip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a modern map and historic map together to plan a route for a walk or place to visit.  Aim to take in as many of the landmarks and features identified in the previous activities as possible.  Take photos or make sketches and use these to label a copy of the map.  Add labels with the answers from your previous activities, and explain the connections between past and present human and physical features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24612 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Walton&#039;s Copperas House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/waltons-copperas-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Walton was one of the chief places for the production of Copperas or green vitriol (ferrous sulphate), which was used for a variety of purposes including inks and dyes. An important by-product of the manufacturing process was sulphuric acid. The Copperas was manufactured from pyrites (bisulphide of iron, FeS2) washed out of the London clay cliffs at Walton&#039;s Naze onto the shore. There the raw material was collected by &quot;Copperas pickers&quot; - the wives and children of fishermen and other poor people, who were paid in tokens. Some Copperas stones were also dregded up from the sea floor by boats. The material was then taken to a Copperas House (a factory) to be chemically transformed into the green vitriol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chronology at Walton:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not known exactly when Copperas production was established at Walton, but it was probably in the 17th century. Daniel Defoe, writing in 1724, noted that &quot;At Walton-on-the-Naze, they find on the shoar copperas-stone in great quantities; and there are several works, call&#039;d Copperas Houses where they make it with great expence&quot;. Samuel Dale, writing in 1730, stated that there had been two Copperas Houses in 1696, but that one had since been washed away by the sea. Coastal erosion was certainly a constant problem at Walton, although it also provided the raw pyritic material from the cliffs for the Copperas industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copperas Houses were very valuable and most of those in south-east England were controlled by a group of families with strong social links. By 1702 the Walton works were in the hands of the Hopkins family who owned other works including that at Brightlingsea. Rights to the raw Copperas found on the shore were usually owned by the local Lord of the Manor from whom the Copperas manufacturers took a lease to enable them to legally collect it. In 1772 the Lord of the Manor of Walton, the Rt. Hon.  William Henry, Earl of Rochford, of St Osyth Priory, leased the rights to Ephraim Rinhold Seelil (or Seckl) for 21 years at £42 p.a. Seelil owned a similar works at Blackwall (Kent). By the early 19th century the Walton factory had passed to Charles Pearson, a Copperas magnate who attempted to dominate the industry and who controlled 30% of production in southern England by 1808. The attempt failed and the Pearson family were bankrupted c.1835 as the industry began to decline. Although production at Walton ceased sometime in the earlier 19th century, the raw material continued to be collected there until the late 19th century when it was being transported to chemical factories in London and Ipswich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Copperas House and the manufacturing process:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a detailed inventory of the Copperas House from 1702 indicating that it had a boiler and several coolers, a great variety of tools and equipment and much old scrap iron. The Copperas House was located between Mill Lane and Vicarage Lane, close to Walton Channel, the Tidal Mill and wharves there, a water supply being important for both the manufacturing process and for the export of the final product. The factory needed quite a lot of open space, typically called a Copperas Ground, where the large tanks could be arranged. A set of depositions in a legal case, probably from the later 18th century, records a dispute over the ownership and rights of access to Copperas House Wharf. In 1907 there was still a piece of open ground at Walton saturated with sulphurous matter and having visible remnants of leaden tanks and pipes from the old factory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An account of the manufacture of Copperas at Walton in the 19th century, recorded in VCH Essex, Volume II, notes the process used. The Copperas was first packed into heaps into which scrap-iron was introduced and then moistened. The action of the air and water then oxidised the copperas into ferrous sulphate of iron (green vitriol or Copperas) and sulphuric acid. Extra scrap iron could be added which reacted with the sulphuric acid to produce more vitriol. The solution was then removed to leaden tanks or boilers and the water evaoprated by heat so concentrating the product. It was then removed again to a cooler, where rods were placed across the product onto which the Copperas crystallized. It could then be gathered and packed into barrels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details of the origins and development of the whole industry see the separate word document provided as an Explore Asset &quot;The Copperas Industry&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office, D/DB T608; D/DHw T19; D/Y 37/2/43; D/DU 5/49, 5/50, 5/62.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre,&lt;em&gt; Map of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S. Dale, &lt;em&gt;The History and Antiquities of Harwich and Dovercourt &lt;/em&gt;(1730)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. George and S. Vincent, &#039;Report of Field Meeting to walton-on-the-Naze and Wrabness&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Tertiary Research&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 1, No. 3 (June 1777), pp.87-90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J.C. Shenstone, &#039;Copperas Industry&#039;, in W. Page and J.H. Round (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Victoria Hitsory of the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. II (1907), pp. 411-13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T. Allen, M. Cotterill &amp;amp; G. Pike, &lt;em&gt;Copperas. An Account of the Whitstable Works and the first Industrial-scale chemical production in England &lt;/em&gt;(Canterbury Archeological Trust, Occasional Paper, No. 2, 2004).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 18:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24246 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Beaumont Quay Lime Kiln</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/beaumont-quay-lime-kiln</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beaumont Quay and similar landing places along the Essex coast were chiefly used for the export of local agricultural produce to London. However, the barges also brought back return cargoes and these were mainly building materials (such as stone, flint or bricks) or soil improvers such as manure and chalk (limestone). The manure was collected in London (both from the capital’s horses and human ‘night soil’) and the chalk on the return journey from quarries along the Thames estuary in both Essex and Kent. The main reason that farmers wanted to apply chalk was to correct high levels of acidity in the soil and therefore improve the uptake of major plant nutrients such as nitrogen and to maximise crop yields. It could also provide a source of calcium and magnesium for growing plants. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the chalk could simply be spread on the farmland it was more efficient burn the chalk at high temperature in a kiln which led to the release of carbon dioxide and created a product called ‘quicklime’. When the ‘quicklime’ was mixed with water (a process known as ‘slaking’) it was turned into a stable powder form of lime which could then be spread on the land. The use of lime for agricultural purposes was described in Sir Anthony Fitzherbert&amp;#039;s Boke of Husbandrye, in 1523, but these activities became increasingly important during the age of agricultural improvement in the 18th and 19th centuries. There was also demand for lime for use in lime mortars in the building industry in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lime kilns were therefore a natural addition to the facilities alongside many of the small Essex quays, wharves and landing places. Although many were built only a few have survived, and the kiln at Beaumont Quay is built to an East Anglian (mixed-feed) design which is fairly rare. It is a circular red brick building within an earthen mound, and is some 2.5 metres high and about 13 metres in diameter. From the main entrance you can access a barrel-vaulted circulation passage around a central combustion chamber. On the other side of the mound another smaller rectangular opening was probably a ventilator that allowed the operators to regulate the draught to the kiln. The central combustion chamber had an opening for lighting the kiln, two others for raking out the lime and ash. The kiln was fired with wood and coal, and alternative layers of fuel and chalk would be added from outside via the opening at the top of the kiln. The chalk would turn to lime at about 900° C and fall to the bottom of the kiln where it could be raked out. The kiln was probably in continuous use, and the quay would have large heaps of chalk and coal ready for processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;br /&gt;
J. Moore, ‘Beaumont Quay’, Colchester Archaeological Group Bulletin, 54 (2014), pp. 8–12.&lt;br /&gt;
English Heritage Listing: Beaumont Quay, Hamford Water: a 19th century quay and lime kiln. List entry Number: 1020688 (See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://list.historicengland.org.uk/&quot;&gt;http://list.historicengland.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 18:59:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23922 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
