<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Gardens &amp; Parks</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/gardens-parks</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Audleys Wood, Cliddesden</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/audleys-wood-cliddesden</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Audleys Wood lies in the northeast corner of Cliddesden parish, its grounds separated from Hackwood Park by the road from Basingstoke to Alton. The entrance is from this road by a tree-lined drive to the house. Originally, a second entrance existed from the Farleigh Road, the drive passing the Pensdell farm buildings. The name occurs as &lt;em&gt;Oddele&lt;/em&gt; in the thirteenth century and as &lt;em&gt;Odlease&lt;/em&gt; in 1576.[1]  The 25” Ordnance Survey map of 1870 marks the land as &lt;em&gt;Odleys Copse&lt;/em&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built in the 1880s of red brick with tiled roofs, the house is a mixture of styles with many antique fittings imported giving an impression of an earlier age. Major alterations were made c.1900 with the addition of a conservatory/ball-room, in 1952 when converted to a Home for the elderly and again in 1986 when the house became a hotel. It stands in extensive wooded –grounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A gentry house and sporting estate, owners included Thomas Pain a director of Tattersalls, the bloodstock auctioneers; William Bradshaw, a great benefactor of St Leonard’s church, Cliddesden; and three generations of the Reading brewery Simonds family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the 1939-45 war the house was occupied by Lord Camrose, owner and editor-in-chief of the Daily Telegraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] MSS. penes, Merton College, Oxford; VCH vol. 4 p.145.&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 19:47:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23078 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Newtown Linford probate records, 1700-1750</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newtown-linford-probate-records-1700-1750</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Newtown Linford is a small village to the north west of Leicester, on the edge of Charnwood Forest. It is one of several villages being studies as part of the Leicestershire VCH &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/leicestershire/news/charnwood-roots-%E2%80%93-volunteers-needed&quot;&gt;Charnwood Roots &lt;/a&gt;project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newtown-linford-probate-records-1621-40&quot;&gt;Newtown Linford probate records, 1621-40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2014 11:36:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22720 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Walled Garden</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/walled-garden</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structural features of gardens, such as buildings and walls, can be permanent and outlive plant life.  A detailed history of these gardens is preserved only with those who tended to, and experienced personally how these gardens evolved under their care.  The walled garden at Parham was probably created in the 18th century and paths and brick walls survive from that period. It must always have been a productive garden, supplying food and flowers for the household.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12680 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Coppicing at Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/coppicing-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The very best oak building timber at the end of the 16th century came from woods which were specifically managed to produce tall, straight trees for posts, beams, and rafters. Such oaks, known as ‘standards’, were grown in the company of species such as hazel which were cut almost to the ground on a regular, cyclical basis and used for necessities such as fuel and fencing. This system of regular cutting is known as coppicing. It not only ensures an almost constant supply of wood which can be harvested again and again as soon as it reaches an appropriate size, but also provides the perfect environment for growing trees suitable for building timber. Between harvests, the coppiced wood grows rapidly — as anyone who has pruned a young tree or shrub will know. The dense new growth forces the young standard timber trees to grow more swiftly than they would in the open, as they are competing for light. The oaks form a crown high above the level of the coppice, unable to throw out lower branches because of the surrounding undergrowth, so lessening the risk of knots which can weaken structural timbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; [i]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[i] O. Rackham, Trees and Woodland in the British Landscape (London, 1976), 8.(Image courtesy of the Woodland Trust Picture Library) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12618 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parham House Gardens</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parham-house-gardens</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The gardens and grounds at Parham House are featured in this section. It includes quotations about the work of the gardeners in the 1920s and 1930s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image supplied courtesy of English Heritage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12609 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parham House Depicted</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parham-house-depicted</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Parham House has been depicted many times in paintings, prints, sketches, maps and photographs, as well as in architectural drawings. By using the depictions of various dates we can trace how the house developed. We must always be conscious that such depictions are done by artists with different degrees of skill for different purposes. Some artists have a reputation for accuracy, usually established by comparing their images with what survives or what we can prove to have been there. Prints made as illustrations for books often conform to a distinct style, particularly when the book belongs to a series, and may give only a general impression. Sketches made by those who knew the house well, though amateur, may be quite accurate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some pictures show materials or setting clearly, for example this painting of the house which forms part of the background of a portrait of Sir Edward Bisshopp painted in 1636. It tells us that the house was plain with three tall gabled projections, information borne out by study of the house itself. It also suggests that it was roofed with red clay tiles, which we know from the roof structure was not true; the colour must have been added to enliven the painting. The features of the landscape are painted quite accurately and can still be traced, which is one of the reasons we know this is Parham House and not another house of the same type.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12608 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parks and open spaces</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parks-and-open-spaces</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mowbray Park, created from the open space and quarries of Bildon, or Building, Hill in 1854-7, was doubled in size in 1865 when it took in land around the museum and winter gardens. It formed a buffer between the middle class suburb of Ashbrooke and the increasingly busy commercial centre of the town.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;See also the resorts of Roker and Seaburn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:36:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12194 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Redcliffe Caves</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/redcliffe-caves</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some people mistakenly believe that the network of caves under Redcliffe Hill was used to store slaves before sale in Bristol. Perhaps this rumour came about after some French Prisoners of War were kept in the caves briefly during the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars.   The caves were usually used to keep the stores for ships. Today the City Council sometimes opens the caves for guided tours, but be careful - it is easy to get lost in the dark passages! Against the wall on your right above one of the entrances to the caves is a plaque referring to the &quot;Middle passage&quot;. The plaque above the entrance suggests that slaves were incarcerated in the barred section within the caves.  This story may have originated because goods relating to the African and West Indian trades were stored there. The only other evidence linking the caves with the slave trade is an 18th century account of French seamen, some of whom may have been black, being taken prisoner by Bristol privateers and kept in the caves. The main product of the caves was sand, needed for the production of glass for bottling beers and spirits such as rum (made from molasses from sugar cane which was produced on the slave plantations) and for other glass objects including trade goods for Africa. These areas known as Temple Gate and St Phillips were the main centres of glass production in Bristol, with owners listed such as John Cave and George Daubeny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:29:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11827 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
