<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Commemorative</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/commemorative</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Dummer War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wooden lychgate at the entrance to the church yard from the street was erected in 1919 as a memorial to the 13 men of the parish who lost their lives in the First World War. It was designed by Lady Emily Rycroft, second wife to Sir Richard Nelson who lived in the village from the time of his marriage in 1911 until his death in 1925.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The memorial was based on the style of a wooden porch at Boxford church in Suffolk. Although she was born in London to a military family, Lady Emily at one time lived at Edwardstone Hall (demolished in 1952), with her parents and siblings so would have known the nearby Boxford church well.[1] The timbers for the lychgate were donated by Robert Miller of Dummer Grange where an old barn was being demolished.[2] Wording on the cross beams reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To those fallen in the service of their country 1914-1918.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My flesh also shall rest in hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plaque bearing the names of eight men who lost their lives in the Second World War was later added as a memorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link below gives details of the men remembered on the WWI plaques displayed on the gate. No records have as yet been found for Frederick Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is also a roll of honour inside the church and a stone plaque remembering the dead of WW2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] 1901 Census; www.lostheritage.org.uk/houses (accessed 3 May 2018).&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] HRO, 65M72/PZ3 &lt;em&gt;Dummer parish magazine&lt;/em&gt; Jun. 1968.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 11:01:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25391 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bishops Hull War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bishops-hull-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The war memorial for Bishops Hull stands in a prominent position in the centre of the village. There are plaques around the plinth replacing the originals. In 2017 it was planned to replace that for the First World War, which contains errors and omissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The war memorial is naturally a focal point for remembering those in the community who died in conflict but of course men from Bishops Hull had served and died in the military services long before there was any thought of war memorials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 10:20:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25183 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 233 names on the town memorial represent only a small proportion of Basingstoke men who died serving in the First World War. It is believed that 600 is nearer to the total number of men lost. They are listed only by surname and initial. By using websites, record offices, church memorials and other local sources a more detailed identification of the men has been made. Inevitably some records are ambiguous and others are missing but work will continue to try and complete the information. The spreadsheet below is the work to date. By identifying home addresses a pattern emerges of streets where several fathers and sons were lost and family groups who not only lost serving men but also husbands and wives still at home. The impact on individual families and the town itself is hard to appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a memorial was first discussed on 28th January 1919 when a public meeting at the Town Hall unanimously resolved that a War Memorial for Basingstoke should be erected. A meeting in the following May agreed that Goldings – a Georgian house situated within five minutes from the town centre – should be purchased along with its 15 a. well timbered park. Thomas Burberry put up the sum of £10,500 to acquire the house and grounds until the Council were able to raise sufficient funds, mainly by subscription. By 1921 the £4,500 loan for the park was repaid and two years later an additional £2,000 enabled the newly commissioned War Memorial to be unveiled on Empire Day, the 24th May 1923, in front of Goldings House which had by then been acquired by the Council for municipal purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Memorial is of Portland stone standing on a circular platform four steps above ground level. Three of the four faces display bronze tablets with the names of 233 men who died serving their country in the First World War. The fourth side was initially inscribed with ‘In Memoriam A.D. 1914-1918’ with a stone cross and the arms of the Borough. On top of the column is a winged bronze figure of Victory shown alighting to place a laurel wreath in memory of the fallen. This was donated anonymously by four subscribers and was cast by L.F. Roslyn. The stonework for the monument was erected by Messrs Mussellwhite &amp;amp; Son of Basingstoke. The total cost of the gates, monument and park represented a substantial fund raising effort by the inhabitants of the town.  Names of those who died in the Second World War have been added on separate plaques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The website www.holyghostcemetery-basingstoke.org.uk has information and guides relating to the CWGC graves in their cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 14:47:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21662 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Timberscombe and the Great War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/timberscombe-and-great-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The small parish of Timberscombe in the Avill valley south of Dunster, far away from the theatres of war, showed extraordinary patriotism following the outbreak of war in 1914. From a parish population of under 300 no fewer than 66 men joined up; sometimes several from the same family. They crossed the social divide from young labourer Samuel Tudball to the Honourable Robert Ryder, younger brother of the 5th earl of Harrowby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1919 the vicar declared that he would give his Easter offering towards a memorial in the church to those who fell or served in the Great War and on 11 April 1920 a war memorial tablet was dedicated at evening service containing the names of the 11 fallen and 55 others who served.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2012 16:14:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21233 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The George Inn</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/george-inn</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The George Inn, first recorded in 1541, had become the stopping place for the Rocket stagecoach before 1800, and was described in 1787 as a stone and timber thatched building, whose landlord operated two post-chaises. It was rebuilt in brick in 1893 slightly further from the road, and survives as the only public house in Codford.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The George Inn would have handled mail conveyed by coach until the post office opened in 1841. When the courthouse accidentally burnt down in 1728 court met at the George Inn. It functioned in this way until the 1860s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;View photographs and documents associated with The George Inn from the selection on the right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12631 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>ANZAC Cemetery</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/anzac-cemetery</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The military cemetery in Codford St Mary, the second largest of its kind in the UK, lies in a peaceful spot by the parish church and contains the graves of 31 Australian and 66 New Zealand soldiers from the First World War.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the end of the First World War, these servicemen have been remembered on Anzac Day – 25th April (or the Sunday nearest to it) by the residents of Codford. A dawn service in the cemetery is followed by a ‘Gunfire Breakfast’ of coffee and rum and ANZAC biscuits, and there is a further service at nearby Sutton Veny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;View photographs and documents associated with the ANZAC cemetery from the selection on the right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12626 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cap Badge on Lamb Down</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cap-badge-lamb-down</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cap badge on the slope above Foxhole Bottom, made by Australian troops, 1916-17, incorporating glass beer bottle bases.  Polishing the bottles became a punishment duty, giving rise to the site&#039;s colloquial name, &#039;Misery Hill&#039;. Turfed over during the Second World War to prevent its use by enemy bombers, the outline was restored in chalk and last scoured in 1999 by Austrailian troops.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;View photographs and documents associated with the Cap Badge from the selection on the right.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12624 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ledbury War Memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ledbury-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ledbury War Memorial commemorates the dead of two World Wars. The memorial was constructed in two stages at the end of each war. It is in a central position in Ledbury High Street, outside St. Katherine&#039;s Hospital and opposite the Market House. It was first unveiled on Sunday 5th December 1920.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stone used is oolitic limestone with granite plaques where the names are inscribed. There are mosaic pictures of an angel, a soldier and a seaman on the lower WWI section and a striking decorated tile picture of an airman on the WWII addition above. Of the 125 men, nine are buried in Ledbury Cemetery in New Street and one in Bosbury village cemetery. More information about the men can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bsswebsite.me.uk/Local-history/War%20Memorial/LedWarMemWW1.html&quot;&gt;The Men Who Served.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information on the protection and conservation of war memorials in the UK see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.warmemorials.org/&quot;&gt;War Memorials Trust.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12257 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>People of African Descent in Bristol before 1850</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/people-african-descent-bristol-1850</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The table shows people of African descent  who lived in Bristol. Scipio Africanus  (1720) was one of them. It was customary for slaves to be named after Roman emperors and generals or given other ironic titles which would display both the classical education of their owners and the subservient status of the the person so named. Scipio Africanus was named after a General Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus (236-186 B.C)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although very little is known of his life it is known that he was the servant of Charles William Howard, 7th Earl of Suffolk, who in 1715 married Arabella Morse and lived in the &quot;Great House&quot; in Henbury, Gloucestershire near Bristol. It is not known how he was acquired, but he died there aged, according to his headstone, eighteen. His Master and Mistress would die two years later.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;He is remembered because of the elaborate grave, consisting of painted headstone and footstone, in the churchyard of St Mary’s in Henbury, which is a grade II listed building.[1] Both stones feature black cherubs and the footstone bears the unusual epitaph:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I who was Born a PAGAN and a SLAVENow sweetly sleep a CHRISTIAN in my GraveWhat tho&#039; my hue was dark my SAVIOR&#039;S sightShall Change this darkness into radiant LightSuch grace to me my Lord on earth has givenTo recommend me to my Lord in heavenWhose glorious second coming here I waitWith saints and Angels him to celebrate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is thought that 10,000 black slaves and servants were in Britain in the early 18th century, but this is one of the very few memorials to them. Curiously, there is no record of his burial in the church registers.[2]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;[1] Memorial to Scipio Africanus 10 metres NW of south porch of Church of St Mary. &lt;em&gt;Images of England&lt;/em&gt;. http://www.imagesofengland.org.uk/  Retrieved on 10.09.2007[2] The 18th century: church records. &lt;em&gt;Discovering Bristol&lt;/em&gt;. http://www.discoveringbristol.org.uk/ Retrieved on 10.09.2007&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11874 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Raja Rammohan Roy</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/raja-rammohan-roy</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Raja Rammohan Roy was born of a distinguished Brahmin family in Bengal. After liberal education he entered the service of the East India Company and rose to high office.  (Image courtesy of the Bristol Central Reference Library, Braikenridge Collection).Essentially a humanist and religious reformer, he left the Company to devote his time to the service of his people. Profoundly influenced by European liberalism, Rammohan came to the conclusion that radical reform was necessary in the religion of Hinduism and in the social practices of the Hindus. He founded the Brahmo Samaj at Calcutta in 1828, which was initially known as the &quot;Brahmo Sabha.&quot;Ram Mohan&#039;s is remembered in Indian history is as the originator of all the more important secular movements in that country. His services to the cause of the abolition of suttee are well-known. He was the first feminist in India and his book, &lt;em&gt;Brief remarks regarding modern encroachments on the ancient rights of females&lt;/em&gt; (1822), is a reasoned argument in favour of the equality of women.He argued for the reform of Hindu law, led the protest against restrictions on the press, mobilised the Government against the oppressive land laws, argued the case for the association of Indians in Government and argued in favour of an English system of education in India.Rammohan Roy arrived in England in 1831 as the ambassador of the Mughal Emperor Akbar Shah II.   He came to stay at Beech House, Stapleton Grove, Bristol in 1833. However, ten days after arriving in Bristol he fell ill with meningitis, and died on 27 September 1833. He was initially buried in the grounds of Beech House, but ten years later his friend Dwarakanath Tagore had him reinterred at Arno&#039;s Vale. A chattri (funerary monument or mandir (shrine) was designed by William Prinsep and built with sponsorship from Dwarakanath Tagore. In 1997 a statue of Raja Rammohan Roy was placed on College Green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chattri has recently received a substantial amount of money for its renovation. You can read about this by following this link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/bristol/6745569.stm&quot;&gt;http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/bristol/6745569.stm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11868 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
