<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Record</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/record</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Old Basing (Basing) Probate Material 1521 to 1700</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1521-1700</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;About half of the parish of Old Basing lies on chalk, with the sands and gravels of the Reading beds running through the centre of the village from NW to SE, separating the chalk uplands (up to 100m OD) in the south from the low-lying London clays (c.60m OD). The river Loddon flows from the chalk just west of Basingstoke through the village towards Reading, the River Lyde, another eventual tributary of the Thames, touches the parish on the south and east. Petty’s Brook, another tributary, forms part of the boundary. The variety of soils has had an impact on the agricultural richness of the parish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parish is not heavily wooded, most of the woodland being on the clay soils, or plantations within Hackwood Park in the south. The river Loddon has determined the form of the village which grew up mainly on the south bank above the flood plain between the two best crossing points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basing parish had four manors: Basing, Byfleet, Hackwood and Lychpit. One of the earliest references to the place-name is the Battle of Basing in the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle in 871 when Alfred (before he became king) was defeated by the Danes. In Domesday, it formed part of the holding of Hugh de Port, the family who retained lordship living in Basing for a long time. It passed to the Paulet family and William Paulet in the 16th century rose to great heights in the government and rebuilt Basing House so that it became the grandest private residence in the land, visited by all the Tudor monarchs. In the 17th century it was famous for the stalwart defence of the house for King Charles during the civil wars by the fifth Marquis John Paulet. It was finally taken by Oliver Cromwell in October 1645 and was completely destroyed by Act of Parliament. It is said that houses in the village were built using bricks from Basing House. In the 18th century, the main Hampshire seat of the family, by then Dukes of Bolton, moved across the park to Hackwood House, which is not in Basing parish. The estate remained an entity until the mid 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wills and inventories survive for Old Basing in Hampshire Record Office (HRO) and The National Archives (TNA). These are being transcribed by the Wills Group of the New Victoria County of Hampshire project based in Basingstoke and will be published in the near future. These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Old Basing is described as Basing being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words and links to the documents are below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1521-40&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1521-40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1541-60&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1541-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1561-1580&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1561-80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1581-1600&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1581-1600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-probate-material-1601-1620&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1601-20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 10:36:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24989 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Milestones: Hampshire&#039;s Living History Museum, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/milestones-hampshires-living-history-museum-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1968 Hampshire County Council took possession of the Tasker Collection of traction engines relating to the Waterloo Ironworks in Andover which closed in 1937. During the 1970s they acquired more redundant agricultural machinery, lorries, steam rollers, wagons etc from Hampshire’s industrial past, including Basingstoke manufacturers Thornycroft and Wallis &amp;amp; Steevens. Looking for a suitable site to display the items, HCC and Basingstoke &amp;amp; Deane Borough Council went into partnership and in 1994 made land available at West Ham Leisure Park. Two years later a £6M Heritage Lottery Fund grant enabled the project to start.[1]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A competition was held to name the proposed museum and work commenced in March 1997 by contractors John Sisk &amp;amp; Son Limited. The building is of concrete, aluminium, stainless steel, glass and slate. It is two storeys high but unusually the floors have been sunk 7m into the ground, which involved the removal of 43,000 cubic metres of chalk to create the 102m long arena.[2] The natural insulation provided by the chalk maintains a stable temperature for exhibits and virtually eliminates the need for heating or cooling. The hangar-style roof consists of 17 steel trussed arches of 55m spans. The glazed walls at either end have sealed-in blinds which react to changes in brightness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some 21,000 objects in the museum have been laid out in Victorian and 1930s-40s working street scenes, although some household items date back to the early 1700s. Photographic evidence helped to create the façades, and an appeal was made at the beginning of the build for donations of any old bricks, cobbles, slates and tiles as well as street furniture, shop and advertising signs. The Basingstoke Willis Museum Archaeological Group rescued door furniture and fireplaces from houses which were demolished in the late 1960s as part of the town’s redevelopment. Salvage was recycled from Reading bus depot and the demolished Thornycroft factory in Basingstoke; granite kerb stones came from Aberdeen; several hundred feet of unwanted tramrail was purchased from Blackpool and wooden blocks from St Mary’s Gas Works in Southampton.[3] The material was collected by the County’s Museums Services based in Winchester where staff and volunteers collated, cleaned and restored exhibits, finally fitting out the completed buildings in February 2000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visitors, aided by costumed guides, can enter fully stocked shops, purchase Milestones Ale in the pub, enter the station booking office and get up close to cars, horse drawn carts and commercial vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final cost of the project rose to £11M which was raised by substantial donations from local companies, HCC and B&amp;amp;DBC. The Basingstoke based Sony company donated audio visual equipment.[4] The official opening was carried out by HRH the Duke of Edinburgh on 1st December 2000 with 175,000 visitors in the first year although it has been difficult to maintain this level of interest.[5] In addition to the museum space there is also a restaurant, facilities for school parties and corporate events and an exhibition area. The complex won the Best Social and Industrial Museum of the year award in 2002.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] Text based on &lt;em&gt;The Making of Milestones&lt;/em&gt;, compiled by Mark Fenton, Hampshire County Council Museums Service, 2000; Hampshire Record Office HPUB/MU1/1/1/3 unless otherwise stated.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, 8 Jan 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;em&gt;Milestones News&lt;/em&gt;, Issue 2, July 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, 18 June 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, 23 Nov 2001.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;em&gt;Basingstoke Observer&lt;/em&gt;, 29 Aug 2002.&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 15:29:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23103 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bosbury Probate Material 1681-1700</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bosbury-probate-material-1681-1700</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are surviving probate documents for 37 Bosbury people in the period 1681-1700.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 21:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SylviaP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21420 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bosbury Probate Material 1661-1680</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bosbury-probate-material-1661-1680</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are surviving probate documents for 49 Bosbury people during the period 1661-1680.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 21:28:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SylviaP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21416 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bosbury Probate Material 1641-1660</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bosbury-probate-material-1641-1660</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are surviving probate documents for 14 Bosbury people during the period 1641-1660. The disruption of the Civil War and then the abolition of the church courts during the Interregnum mean that not many probate documents survive from this time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 21:26:09 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SylviaP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21415 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bosbury Probate Material 1621-1640</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bosbury-probate-material-1621-1640</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are surviving probate documents for 23 Bosbury people in the period 1621-1640.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2013 21:21:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SylviaP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21414 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mapledurwell Probate 1621-40</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mapledurwell-probate-1621-40</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are nine surviving wills with ten inventories belonging to them and one inventory of John Smales who died intestate in this period. Nicholas Smith’s will was proved in 1632, a further inventory was valued after the death of his wife in 1638. One testator, Thomas Kent, held the 60 acre freehold in the parish. Four of the testators were yeomen and two were husbandmen. The rest were rural craftsmen: a carpenter, a sieve maker and a tailor. The inventories reflect the mixed arable and pastoral farming and are a rich source for household goods and, in the case of Thomas Been, for a carpenter’s tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links to all the documents appear below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;glossary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21296&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Smales, Tailor, 1624 (Inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21297&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Smales, Tailor, 1624 (Accounts)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21298&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicholas Smith, yeoman, 1632 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21299&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas Been, carpenter, 1634 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21300&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Hawkins, husbandman, 1635 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21301&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Benham, yeoman, 1635 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21302&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ann Benham, widow, 1635 (Will and Inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21303&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicholas Nutt, husbandman, 1636 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21304&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Christopher Lester, yeoman and College bailiff, 1637 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21305&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas Kent, yeoman, 1638 (WIll and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21306&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Maudlin, sieve maker, 1639 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21307&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nicholas Smith, yeoman, 1639/1632 (Will and inventory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 14:53:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21294 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mapledurwell Probate Material  1518-1831</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mapledurwell-probate-material-1518-1831</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wills and inventories dating from 1518-1831 have been transcribed by the Wills Group of the New Victoria County of Hampshire project, based in Basingstoke.  These have been transcribed from copies of the original documents which were supplied by Hampshire Record Office. Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier. Names have been transcribed as written. Words in square brackets have been transcribed as seen but the meaning is unclear. Words in italics were missing and have been inserted to make sense of the text. Mapledurwell is described as in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire. Analysis of these wills has contributed to the group&#039;s first publication, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/hampshire&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mapledurwell.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (The Victoria History of Hampshire, 2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only wills and inventories from 1518 to 1720 have been posted here as after that date inventories are not preserved and probate records become less interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The testators were mainly copyhold tenants of Corpus Christi College, Oxford who have been lords of the manor of Mapledurwell for 500 years. The college also owned some land in Up Nately and Newnham which was managed as part of the manor of Mapledurwell. The excellent estate records of Corpus Christi College have enabled some testators to be linked with the property they held and even with farmhouses still surviving today. The copyholds were let for three lives. The names of the three lives are recorded on the copy of the manorial court roll. If one life died, the second and third life could hold the property. For the detailed descent of all these properties, see the Waight papers in Hampshire Record Office (HRO, 83A02/10). Winchester College also owned some copyhold land in the parish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documents have been grouped into short chronological sections.  The links appear below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mapledurwell-probate-material-1518-1560&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1518-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mapledurwell-probate-material-1561-80&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1561-80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21524&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1581-1600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21353&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1601-20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21294&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1621-40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21364&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1641-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21373&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1661-80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21429&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1681-1700&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21441&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mapledurwell Probate Material 1701-20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 18 Feb 2013 14:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21291 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bosbury Probate Material before 1540</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bosbury-probate-material-1540</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Statute of Wills (1540) made it legal to devise (leave) certain types of land. After 1540 wills had to be in two forms - the will, dealing with moveable property, and the testament, dealing with real property. This is why most wills use the formula &#039;last will and testament&#039;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there are very few surviving probate documents for Bosbury people before 1540.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2012 15:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SylviaP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21033 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bosbury Probate Material 1601-1620</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bosbury-probate-material-1601-1620</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;From the start of the 17th century, more probate documents survive. There are surviving documents for 37 Bosbury people from 1601-1620. Three of them were proved at the Prerogative Court of Canterbury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2011 18:07:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SylviaP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20791 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
