<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Education</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/education</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Working Men&#039;s Mission Hall, Basingstoke 1905-28</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/working-mens-mission-hall-basingstoke-1905-28</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;From its opening in February 1905 until its transfer to the Methodists in 1928, the Working Men’s Mission Hall in George Street, Basingstoke, served as a non-denominational place of worship for those living in the vicinity. As it was put at the opening ceremony, it was the ‘earnest desire’ of those behind the enterprise that ‘souls might be saved there and that the preaching of the Gospel in that Hall might be made a means of blessing to the neighbourhood.’ Costing £220, it could accommodate 250 persons and was described as ‘being very comfortable’ and presenting ‘a light and attractive appearance’. It is not known who initiated the Hall’s construction. Although formally un-denominational, it attracted a considerable amount of support from Nonconformists and well-wishers within Basingstoke and beyond. For example, the Hall was formally opened by Mr B.B. Pond from Andover and William Buckland, Basingstoke’s mayor, presided at the evening meeting. At this event, it was made clear that the ‘Hall had not been erected in any spirit of opposition to any other Church.’ Not surprisingly, perhaps, the mood at the Hall’s opening was buoyant and optimistic. The formal opening and afternoon tea, as well as the evening meeting were all exceptionally well attended. By 1910 the debt on the Hall had been cleared. In many respects the Hall functioned just like the other Nonconformist places of worship in Basingstoke, with regular Sunday services; a range of associated organisations, including a Sunday school, a branch of the Band of Hope, a Christian Endeavour Society, a clothing club and, for a time, an orchestra; camp meetings; and social events and entertainments of various kinds. Annual anniversary celebrations were also an important feature in the life of the Hall, which appears to have thrived during the First World War and well into the 1920s. However, a few weeks after the 1928 anniversary celebrations, it was announced that: ‘The Trustees of the Working Men’s Mission Hall in George Street, which … [had] heretofore been carried on as an independent religious organisation, recently met and unanimously decided to offer the Mission Hall to the Wesleyan Methodist Church.’ Although no reasons were given, it is possible that the decision had been prompted by the ‘heavy losses sustained by the lamented deaths’ of two key figures in the running of the Mission, Messrs Lane and Laney. At the 1928 anniversary they had been described as ‘devoted and generous workers in the Mission.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;August 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 13:41:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25617 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Norton Fitzwarren National School</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/norton-fitzwarren-national-school</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norton Fitwarren had a succession of school premises but the 1872 National School was in use for over a century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 10:43:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25513 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fairfields Board Schools, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fairfields-board-schools-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former site of the sheep fair on high ground in the south of the town was given by the Corporation in 1885 for the Board Schools to accommodate 1,310 pupils.[1] The initial plan was to have one school for boys, one for girls and infants but the design soon changed to mixed infants in one building and seniors housed on two floors in an adjacent detached building.[2] The foundation stone was laid on 29 November 1886 by George Freeman Dunn, Chairman of the School Board. Other members of the Board listed on the stone are Richard Sterry Wallis (Vice Chairman), Revd Canon Millard, Edward Adams, Edwin Charles White, Charles Pinder and Thomas John Edney. Francis Samuel Chandler was the clerk. Charles Bell of London was the architect and local builder Henry James Goodall was the contractor. The schools opened to children in February 1888.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schools are still in use in 2014, one as a primary school, the other as a creative arts centre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a full history of the education at the school refer to Basingstoke Education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] J.R. John, &lt;em&gt;Fairfields Schools, Basingstoke (1888-1979),&lt;/em&gt; (1979), 11.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[2] Hants RO (HRO), 22M88/1&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2014 15:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23005 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Timberscombe School</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/timberscombe-school</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Richard Elsworthy or Ellsworth of Bickham in Timberscombe left £200 in 1714 to build a charity school and library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately it was nearly a century before his wishes were at least partly fulfilled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, despite much litigation, scandal and financial difficulty the endowed school survived for nearly a century educating hundreds of local children until it was transferred to the local authority. The school survives today at the heart of the village.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 08:44:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22296 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Bagworth</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-bagworth</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bagworth is a mining village in west Leicestershire, around 8 miles north-west of the city centre. The story of its school is closely linked to the mining industry, which brought prosperity to the village, and yet (literally) undermined its structures. The Norman church (much restored) had to be demolished in 1968 and replaced by a lightweight building, which is now (in 2013) reaching the natural end of its life. The school effectively went the same way, and now almost all that remains of a building which was once at the heart of village life is the road sign: Old School Lane.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2013 20:55:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22014 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Newbold Verdon</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-newbold-verdon</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Newbold Verdon is 10 miles south-west of Leicester, and 3 miles east of Market Bosworth. The parish takes its suffix from the Verdon family, who were landowners here in the thirteenth century. Another landowner who was remembered for many years was Nathaniel, Lord Crewe, Bishop of Durham, who inherited an estate in Newbold Verdon in 1681 on the death of his brother John. In his will of 1720, Lord Crewe left part of his large estate in trust for a school in this village.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 13:24:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21973 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Stoney Stanton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-stoney-stanton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stoney Stanton is 10 miles south-west of Leicester and 6 miles east of Hinckley. As the name suggests, the village contains quarries, and a directory of 1877 describes the parish &#039;famous for its basalt rocks, which afford an inexhaustable supply&#039;. Today, we recognise the rock as a quartz-diorite, which is crushed and used in laying roads. Earlier in the 19th century, many residents were employed in framework knitting. One of the former quarries, known as Stoney Cove, is now a major inland diving centre.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 23:23:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21969 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Kilby</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-kilby</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kilby is about 8 miles south-east of Leicester, and on the Grand Union Canal. Like many south-Leicestershire villages, in the early 19th century, many of the inhabitants were framework knitters. The village is closely linked with that of Wistow through common land ownership.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 23:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21967 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Countesthorpe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-countesthorpe</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Countesthorpe is about five miles south of Leicester, and was originally a chapelry of Blaby. It became a civil parish in 1866. By the early 19th century it was an industrial village, and many of its inhabitants were employed in the framework knitting industry. In 1884 the Leicester Board of Guardians built 11 large houses on a 55-acre site in Countesthorpe, known as the Cottage Homes, to house up to 250 children who would otherwise have been in the workhouse. They survived far longer than the workhouse, becoming less institutionalised over the 20th century, before finally closing in 1974, and being converted into private houses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 22:57:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21965 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Schools in Hugglescote</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/schools-hugglescote</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hugglescote is a village on the edge of the coalfield area of north-west Leicestershire, 12 miles north-west of Leicester. It is also close to the diorite quarries at Bardon and Markfield, and a stone-crushing plant was installed here in the 1870s to turn this hard rock into a useful material for macadamising roads. Originally a chapelry of Ibstock, Hugglescote and Donington became a civil parish in 1866, but in 1936 both villages were absorbed for administrative purposes into the civil parish and urban district of Coalville. Like many villages in this area, nonconformity was strong in the 19th century, and this ethos influenced local schools.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 11 Aug 2013 22:35:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21964 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
