<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Oxfordshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/ancient-county/oxfordshire</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>East Side</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/east-side</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opposite Nos. 1–2, former commercial use can be seen in Weavers and Tiverton Cottages. Much of the street&#039;s east side, however, is taken up by the former almshouses and by Vick&#039;s Byways Garage. Opposite the Old Vicarage are Ford Close and Emmanuel Cottage, another late 18th- or 19th-century cottage pair; each have long gardens, the former now displaying a Chinese influence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 11:10:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22000 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>West Side</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/west-side</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This near-continuous run of cottages begins with Nos. 1–2 , where stonework shows that a first-floor central casement has been removed. The central dormer was probably shared between the two attics, with a central partition forming the window&#039;s central mullion. Beyond, Homeleigh and No. 4 display a rusticated treatment typical of the mid 20th century; No. 4 has a memorial stone to Nan Meadows (1912–88), a former District Nurse and (latterly) peace campaigner. Fortey’s Close, perhaps the most stylish house in the street, is followed by Nos. 5–8, built in the 18th century as two mirror-image cottage pairs but long since converted into two houses. The street&#039;s western side ends with Russell Cox&#039;s vicarage of 1937, an excellent example of sympathetic 20th-century building in Burford.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 08:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21998 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Urban Inns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/urban-inns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Burford&#039;s earliest surviving inn building is the front part of the New Inn at 124 High Street (built c.1401). More extensive traces of courtyard layouts survive at the George Inn, the former Bear Inn, and within the later structure of the Bull. The best preserved is the George, where the gateway leads to two parallel courtyard ranges converted into cottages in the 19th century (Figure 91).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 18th and early 19th centuries competition for the coaching trade affected the inns&#039; architecture. The Bull&#039;s new brick and stone façade (probably added c.1715)was no doubt aimed at making it unmistakable to the visitor arriving by coach, and the rebuilding also enabled the heights of the rooms in the street range to be increased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12713 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Chantries, Obits and Altars</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/chantries-obits-and-altars</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To medieval parishioners, heaven and hell were not abstract ideas but reality, reinforced by the wall paintings which adorned most parish churches. Wealth and prestige were no safeguard against damnation: artists frequently delighted in showing merchants, kings, bishops and even popes among the tormented souls in Hell. Good works and adherence to Christian doctrine were performed in order to avoid hell. But the deceased might spend centuries in Purgatory, waiting to be sent to heaven. So an industry developed of wealthy parishioners founding chantry chapels, or side altars and obits, where masses could be said for the souls of the deceased.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12671 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Reconstructing Medieval Towns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/reconstructing-medieval-towns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The analysis of medieval towns relies on the fact that the property boundaries which define urban house-plots (burgages) are very unlikely to change over time. Excavations in York and Southampton have shown that some plot boundaries survived unchanged for a millennium or more, carefully marked out using hedges, fences or walls. Plots were laid out based on a standard perch (16.5 ft). In Burford it is still possible to find plots which have retained their original dimensions from the late 12th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information is found in the attached documents. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12668 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Northfield End</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/northfield-end</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;NORTHFIELD END is the name for the stretch of road which links the Fairmile (from Bix and Assendon) with the northern end of Bell Street, on the town&#039;s extreme northern edge. (See map). With Bell Street it forms part of Henley&#039;s original medieval street plan, and its origins may, in fact, pre-date the town, since the Fairmile follows the approximate line of the Roman road from Dorchester. The road from Marlow, which is also of medieval origin, intersects Northfield End just beyond Bell Lane.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Northfield End lay just outside the town boundary until the borough was extended in 1894. But from the Middle Ages there was suburban development here, with houses and other buildings (including a mill) mentioned from the 14th and 15th centuries. The name originated as &#039;Old Field&#039; (from a small open field close by), and was gradually corrupted first to Naldefeld and later to Northfield. The form &#039;Northfield End&#039; was established by the 16th century.   Up here away from the commercial heart of the town there was room for larger houses set apart from the noise, bustle and smell of the town centre. From an early date, therefore, Northfield End may have had a relatively genteel suburban character, though this was always tempered by the presence of farmers, craftsmen and tradesmen. Even in 1901 doctors, solicitors and those with private means rubbed shoulders with corn dealers, bakers, carriers, coach builders, and labourers.   This mix is reflected in the buildings, which include small 18th- and 19th-century cottages or shops as well as those with grand 18th-century facades (e.g. Nos 9 and 11, the former concealing an earlier timber-framed house). Another grand frontage is that of the former Bell Inn (just north of Bell Lane), which was established here by the late 16th century and became one of the town&#039;s busiest and most upmarket coaching inns, until its conversion into a new home for Henley Grammar School in the 19th century. Another building of note is the Friends&#039; (Quaker) meeting house, established in converted cottages at Northfield End in the early 1660s, and largely rebuilt in brick in 1894.   Read the censuses for Northfield End.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12597 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Henley&#039;s Street Plan</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/henleys-street-plan</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Henley&#039;s central streets originated probably in the late 12th century, when the planned town of Henley was laid out alongside the river within a pre-existing royal estate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The founder may have been King Henry II, who is known to have founded other towns including New Woodstock in west Oxfordshire. Such town foundations were common from the 11th to early 13th centuries, and represented hard-headed commercial ventures by wealthy lords hoping to benefit from the expanding economy and growing commercialization of the period. Henley proved a success, based partly on its role in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/Counties/Oxfordshire/Projects/HenleyOnThames/Items/Henley_and_the_Thames_River_Trade?Session/@id=L_p1wIW1s71HvGKb6iaJlP&quot;&gt;Thames river trade&lt;/a&gt;.   The early street plan was simple, comprising two main intersecting roads (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/Counties/Oxfordshire/Projects/HenleyOnThames/Items/Henley_s_Streets/assetdetails/4790?Session/@id=L_p1wIW1s71HvGKb6iaJlP&quot;&gt;see map&lt;/a&gt;). The first was a single, broad east-west street, leading eastwards across the medieval bridge, and opening up on the west into a wide wedge-shaped market place. In the Middle Ages its whole length was called High Street, but from the 16th or 17th century its east end became known as Hart Street, from the medieval White Hart Inn on its north side. Intersecting it was a north-south route from Oxford and Dorchester to Reading, known in the Middle Ages as North Street (north of the crossroads) and Brook Street (south of the crossroads, so called from the town brook or ditch near its southern end). These later became known as Bell Street (from the important Bell Inn at Northfield End), and Duke Street (a corruption of Ditch or Duck Street). Both streets may have existed in some form before the town was laid out.   Friday Street, on the medieval town&#039;s southern edge, may have originated as a small squatter settlement, though by c.1300 its north side was included in the town, and it acquired some high-quality late medieval houses. New Street (running from Bell Street to the river) was an addition to the original town plan, but seems to have been built up by 1307 when it was mentioned in a surviving property conveyance.   Until the early 19th century Henley&#039;s street plan expanded very little. But from then on there was pronounced &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/Counties/Oxfordshire/Projects/HenleyOnThames/Items/Henley_s_19th_Century_Suburbs?Session/@id=L_p1wIW1s71HvGKb6iaJlP&quot;&gt;suburban growth&lt;/a&gt;, particularly to the south along Reading Road and the neighbouring St Marks Estate (e.g. St Marks Road, St Andrews Road, Vicarage Road etc). Station Road was laid out to serve the new railway station (opened 1857), with Queen Street (1879) and King&#039;s Road added later. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/Counties/Oxfordshire/Projects/HenleyOnThames/Items/Henley_s_Streets/assetdetails/4789?Session/@id=L_p1wIW1s71HvGKb6iaJlP&quot;&gt;See map&lt;/a&gt;.)   Further growth took place in the 20th century, with new building along Peppard Lane and Mount View (1930s), and after the Second World War on the Gainsborough estate and elsewhere on the town&#039;s west side. Even so, Conservation legislation has done much to preserve the town&#039;s character and save it from unbridled expansion, particularly on the north along the ancient Fair Mile.    &lt;strong&gt;Read more&lt;/strong&gt; about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/Counties/Oxfordshire/Projects/HenleyOnThames/Items/Henley_s_Streets/assetdetails/4791?Session/@id=L_p1wIW1s71HvGKb6iaJlP&quot;&gt;Henley&#039;s medieval origins&lt;/a&gt; and 19th-century &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/Counties/Oxfordshire/Projects/HenleyOnThames/Items/Henley_s_19th_Century_Suburbs?Session/@id=L_p1wIW1s71HvGKb6iaJlP&quot;&gt;suburban development&lt;/a&gt;, or explore particular streets (including census entries):  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/hart-street&quot;&gt;Hart Street&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bell-street&quot;&gt;Bell Street&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/northfield-end&quot;&gt;Northfield End&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/friday-street&quot;&gt;Friday Street&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/henley-wills-and-inventories-1651-70&quot;&gt;Church Street&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/station-road&quot;&gt;Station Road&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thameside&quot;&gt;Thameside &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12596 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bell Street</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bell-street</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;BELL STREET is one of Henley&#039;s four main central streets, running southwards from Northfield End on the town&#039;s outskirts to the central crossroads with Hart Street and the Market Place (see map). With Duke Street, it forms part of a major north-south route from Oxford and Marlow through to Reading, and its line probably pre-dated the creation of the planned town in the 12th century. In the Middle Ages it was called North Street. Its later name derived from the Bell Inn at the street&#039;s northern end (technically at Northfield End rather than Bell Street), which by the 17th century was one of Henley&#039;s most important inns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern Bell Street is a narrow thoroughfare flanked by shops and other commercial premises, though as it widens out beyond New Street there are some handsome Georgian houses such as Rupert House and Countess Gardens. These lend its northern end a very different character, which continues along Northfield End. Also along the stretch beyond New Street, hidden behind later facades, are remains of some high-status 15th-century timber-framed houses, built probably for wealthy merchants. One (at Nos 74, 76 and 78) has been dendro-dated to 1405, making it one of Henley&#039;s earliest surviving domestic buildings.   Further south, the street&#039;s commercial character was well established in the Middle Ages: in 1341 there was a shop at the south-east corner with Hart Street, with another one adjoining it to the north. The street also acquired some relatively early inns. The Bear (77-79 Bell Street) was an inn by 1666, and has a medieval hall at the back which has been dendro-dated to 1438. The Bull (57-59 Bell Street) may have been an inn by the 16th century, and the Duke of Cumberland on the opposite side (renamed Ye Olde Bell in 1920) opened in the mid 18th. Part of the building (at the back) has recently been dendro-dated to 1325, making it the earliest domestic building so far found in Henley.   The &lt;strong&gt;19th-century &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;censuses&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;see Assets below&lt;/em&gt;) confirm that shops and services comprised the majority of premises along Bell Street. A flourishing draper’s business was situated on the south-west corner by the Market Place (1-3 Bell Street), giving it the name Monk&#039;s Corner well into the 20th century. There were several grocers and butchers, always a fishmonger, chemist, and tailor, and a pastry-cook-cum-confectioner, catering for relatively well-off patrons either living in the town or passing through. A short-lived beer house called the &lt;em&gt;British Workman&lt;/em&gt; had metamorphosed by 1901 into the British Workman’s Coffee House. Further north at the high-class residential end of Bell Street were several households &#039;living on their own means&#039; (i.e. enjoying a private income), and at various times there were two surgeons or general practitioners, Mr Jeston and Mr Egerton Baines. In 1901 Baines (aged 54) occupied Rupert House (90 Bell Street) with a household of ten, including his immediate family, a visitor and a boarder, and 3 servants.   On the west side of the street behind the modern frontages of Nos 5-7 (Boots Chemist) was Goffs Yard, one of several cramped, insanitary cottage yards scattered around the town in the 19th and early 20th centuries. .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12592 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Henley&#039;s 19th-Century Suburbs</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/henleys-19th-century-suburbs</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image: Norman Avenue, developed by the Henley builder Charles Clements from c.1885. These eccentrically-detailed red brick houses with their striking ornamentation and carved stonework recall Friar Park.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of Henley&#039;s southern part (along Reading Road south of Friday Street) was built up only during the 19th century. Though usually upstaged by the historic buildings in the town centre, some of these 19th-century housing developments display a rich variety of inventive detail which repays further exploration. Scan the Assets (below) for some of the buildings erected, or for more on Henley&#039;s by local builders and developers like Robert Owthwaite, Thomas and William Hamilton, and the Wilson brothers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Streets included: Vicarage Road, St Marks Road, St Andrews Road, Harpsden Road, Queen Street, Station Road, Norman Avenue, Greys Hill, Church Street and Holy Trinity church.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12584 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Caroline Powys and Henley</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/caroline-powys-and-henley</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The diaries of Caroline Powys (1738-1817) are one of the most vibrant and entertaining sources for the social life of the gentry and aristocracy in and around Henley in the later 18th century, a time when the town was emerging as a fashionable social centre partly on the back of its coaching trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The daughter of a Berkshire surgeon, in 1762 Caroline Powys (née Girle) married Philip Lybbe Powys of Hardwick House in Whitchurch (Oxfordshire). In 1784, with their children grown, the couple moved to Fawley Rectory (just outside Henley) to live with Philip&#039;s brother the Revd Thomas Powys, who was a bachelor.   Caroline began keeping a diary in 1756, describing amongst other things the coronation procession of George III. Her later diaries record in lively and gossipy detail the daily social round of her class, encompassing visits to neighbouring country houses, plays and concerts, grand balls, seasons in London and Bath, and winter balls and assemblies in Henley. Many of her descriptions evoke the world of Jane Austen, to whom she was distantly related through marriage (&lt;em&gt;find out more&lt;/em&gt;).   Extracts from the diaries were edited in 1899 by Emily Climenson (Passages from the Diaries of Mrs Philip Lybbe Powys of Hardwick House, Oxon, AD 1756 to 1808). A fuller account of her life is in the Oxford Dictionary of National Biography.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12578 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
