<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Salisbury</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/salisbury</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Salisbury Cathedral </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/salisbury-cathedral</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;First cathedral was built between 1075 &amp;amp; 1092 by the Bishop Osmond a larger building was on the site circa 1120.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cathedral was moved by Bishop Richard Poore and the moved was completed in 1266. In 1218 the decision to move the cathedral was formally approved by Rome. In 1219 a wooden chapel and cemetery was constructed at the new site. In 1225 three eastern chapels were consecrated and in the 14th century a tower &amp;amp; spire was added.      &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Cathedral still stands today and dominates the city&#039;s skyline.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21322 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Sarum</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-sarum</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum in Wiltshire is well known as notorious rotten borough pre the 1832 reform act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum was the original site of the settlement of Salisbury but the population moved to a nearby site as the original site was not big enough to satisfy the local needs. The rotten borough had 7 votes for just 3 houses and 1 MP represented these voters despite no MP’s for many of the new industrial cities such as Birmingham, Sheffield and Manchester. In the last election of 1831 11 votes were cast all from land owners who didn’t live in the borough.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The settlement moved a mile and a quarter to the south away from the natural hill fortress so the site could be easily expanded. It was mentioned in the doomsday book and was owned by the bishop of Salisbury the books mentions 50 hides and land for 32 ploughs in 1086. Cathedral foundations were found within the hill fort. The settlement was named as Sorbiodunum and was one of ten British cities that had particular privileges such as a castle and good roads. The city was established in 1220 in this new location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:27:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21320 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Salisbury Railway</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/salisbury-railway</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The railway through Salisbury served different areas: the local market (the Market house line &amp;amp; the Bishopstoke line) the area around Salisbury: (the Yeovil &amp;amp; Westbury lines) which connected the local villages) and the region as a whole: (the central line) from Exeter to London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Direct London connection enhanced the social importance of the city, important staging post for the London – West Country connection.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 13:59:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21318 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Salisbury Market</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/salisbury-market</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Salisbury had markets on Tuesdays and Saturdays between 1361 and 1960; there was no market on the other four to encourage trade in Old Sarum and Wilton. The market belonged to the bishop who kept the tolls from it. In 1661 there were 28 stalls. The average yearly net income received by the corporation from market tolls was £23 in 1797–1800, £22 in 1801–1804, £25 in 1805–15, and £43 in 1827–33.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salisbury was also well known for its cattle market. In the late 18th century the fortnightly cattle market was described as one of the largest in the kingdom, and was still so in 1851.    &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 15:35:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21277 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
