<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Leicestershire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/county/leicestershire</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Ibstock Probate Material, 1640 and earlier</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1640-and-earlier</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ibstock is one of Leicestershire&#039;s largest villages. It is in the west Leicestershire coalfield area, and both coal mining and clay extraction for brick-making have shaped its size and character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like other mining villages in this area, nonconformity was strong. The village had one of the very few British schools in the county (affiliated to the non-denominational British and Foreign Schools Society), in contrast to most Leicestershire villages, where the school was closely tied to the Anglican church. Plans of the British School show that it had the sloping floor beloved by educationalist Joseph Lancaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probate inventories reveal a diverse community lived here in the late 16th, 17th and early 18th centuries. Some people had substantial wealth, often in money and bonds (loans to others) rather than farming assets. The quantity and range of goods in Samuel Goadby&#039;s shop (1705) are similar to those found in the shops of market towns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1641-1660&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1641-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1661-1680&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1661-1680&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1681-1700&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1681-1700&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-probate-material-1701-1720&quot;&gt;Ibstock Probate Material, 1701-1720&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2017 10:46:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25075 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Retail Trade in Lutterworth</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/retail-trade-lutterworth</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lutterworth&#039;s market charter was granted in 1214. A fresh charter was obtained in 1414 for both the market and an annual fair, held on the eve and day of the Ascension. A survey of 1509 shows that specialist market areas had appeared: the Neats Market for the sale of young cattle, &#039;le Fleshamills&#039; for butchers and a Woodmarket, one of the widest streets in the west of the town. By 1607 the Neats Market had been joined by a Beast Market, a &#039;Shepemarket&#039;, a &#039;Cornemarkett&#039;, an Iron Market and a Drapery.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Permament shops had also emerged by the 17th century, some selling just one product, for example, hats, but also large general stores (perhaps only one at any one time), selling cloth, groceries and a small number of household items, including writing paper and arsenic.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1790 the market was said to be of &#039;no great note&#039;, and the livestock element suffered a fatal blow when the railway failed to come to the town until 1899.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small weekly market is still held in 2015 in the market square by the 1836 Town Hall. Shops line the High Street, but the main shopping area is along Church Street. Like many small market towns, most of the shops are independently owned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 10:42:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24701 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Feilding Palmer Cottage Hospital</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/feilding-palmer-cottage-hospital</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feilding Palmer Cottage Hospital in Lutterworth opened in 1899, and remains open as a hospital in 2015, providing heathcare services to the local community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 10:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24659 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The land of William Almey in Leire, Leicestershire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/land-william-almey-leire-leicestershire</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research for the VCH towards a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/counties/leicestershire/work-in-progress/leire&quot;&gt;parish history of Leire &lt;/a&gt;has included transcribing two documents held in a private collection detailing the land held by William Almey. These transcripts are now made available here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 10:21:09 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23933 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Loddington Probate Inventories</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/loddington-probate-inventories</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;Loddington is a very small rural settlement and civil parish in east Leicestershire with a population of less than 100.  The settlement lies in a protected hollow, and to the south of the settlement the land slopes down to the Eye Brook, which forms the southern boundary of the parish. The eastern boundary is also the county boundary with Rutland. 


John Nichols (1800) described Loddington as &#039;one of the finest lordships of old enclosure&#039; in the county. W.G. Hoskins saw the area as ‘lovely withdrawn country’, which is ‘more like Devon than Leicestershire’.


Loddington does not have a Parish Council as such but forms a Parish Meeting with Launde civil parish to the north.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2015 16:48:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23477 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ibstock glebe terriers</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ibstock-glebe-terriers</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coal mining and clay extraction have shaped the size and character of present day Ibstock. Probate inventories for this parish can now be found on VCH Explore&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glebe terriers provide details of the land owned by the church (the glebe), used to support its ministry in the parish. Before enclosure, this land lay as strips scattered across the open fields of the parish. Glebe terriers can therefore provide topographical information about the parish. Some can also set out local customs, for example in respect of tithes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2015 10:30:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23278 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Protestant Nonconformity in Buckminster and Sewstern</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/protestant-nonconformity-buckminster-and-sewstern-2</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rural villages of Buckminster and Sewstern, in east Leicestershire, are both in the parish of Buckminster, and are around 10 miles east-north-east of Melton Mowbray.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 22:10:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23275 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Religious Dissent in Queniborough</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/religious-dissent-queniborough</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Queniborough is a small rural parish located within the Wreake Valley of north-east Leicestershire. It is 7 miles north-east of the county town of Leicester and 9 miles south-west of the market town of Melton Mowbray. The village is linear in shape, with the historic core stretching from St Mary&#039;s church at the east end of the village along Main Street. This part of the village has been designated a Conservation Area and contains over 30 listed buildings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 13:02:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23269 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Protestant Nonconformity in Somerby</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/protestant-nonconformity-somerby</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somerby is a small village in east Leicestershire, some 5 miles south of Melton Mowbray.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 23:04:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23219 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Protestant Nonconformity in Ullesthorpe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/protestant-nonconformity-ullesthorpe</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ullesthorpe is a village in south Leicestershire. Nonconformity arrived early, with the first meeting house established in 1723 at the home of a dissenter. Between then and 1800, five more meeting houses were established, all in the homes of dissenters. No indication is given as to their denomination, but evidence from the nineteenth century shows that Independents were present in the village at that time. There is also evidence of a Baptist presence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 14:54:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23169 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
