<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Essex</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/ancient-county/essex</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Reclaiming the Estuary</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/reclaiming-estuary</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The creeks and marshes along the Essex coast contain large areas of salt marsh.  These were used as land to graze sheep in summer, but were often flooded and inaccessible in winter.  However, the land was more valuable if it could be reclaimed from the sea, drained and protected from the salt water by a sea wall which is what happened in the Gunfleet estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mouth of the estuary was probably protected in earlier centuries by a headland (a Ness) at Little Holland Hall and another at Frinton, but these were eroded to create the straighter coastline of today.  It is probable that some land reclamation was already happening in the Medieval and Tudor periods and natural processes such as silting and longshore drift continued to change the size and shape of the estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tendring Level Commissioners, a public body recruited from local landowners, decided to construct a sea wall in the 17th century.  This meant that hundreds of acres of land was reclaimed in the parishes of Great Holland, Little Holland, Frinton, Great Clacton, Little Clacton and Thorpe-le-Soken.  A &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/holland-haven-sluices-and-marsh-shown-1838-ordnance-survey-map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sluice &lt;/a&gt;was built in the wall to allow the river to drain into the sea.  By preventing salt water entering the marshes the land in the estuary would be improved for agricultural use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This changing landscape had an effect on local land use.  Maps of 1594 and 1603 indicate that there was no route at that time across the Gunfleet estuary which still formed a major barrier to land communications along the coast.  As a result, there was probably much communication in small boats across the Gunfleet estuary and along the coast in the sheltered waters of the Gunfleet Channel. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inland, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/andre-and-chapman-map-1777-showing-rice-bridge&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rice Bridge&lt;/a&gt; is the earliest recorded crossing point of the Holland River and was in existence by 1319.  It was probably a timber bridge or causeway at this point and was described as a wooden footbridge in 1783.  The bridge connected the two parishes of Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton. The present brick built Rice bridge dates from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/fan-bridge-shown-chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fan Bridge&lt;/a&gt; is the second recorded crossing and is further downstream than Rice Bridge where the river was wider and the land more liable to flood.  This was certainly a more difficult and marshy location for a bridge, as the name Fan or Fen suggests, and in earlier centuries when the Gunfleet estuary was more open to the sea it may have been an impractical location.  The crossing is first recorded in 1509 and is shown on the 1777 map with a dashed line to indicate the marshy terrain.  New bridges were built in the 18th and 19th centuries with the present brick bridge appearing to date from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/holland-bridge-shown-1838-ordnance-survey-map&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Holland Bridge&lt;/a&gt; is the most recent bridge to cross the Holland River, and is the furthest downstream.  When the reclamation works were considered sufficiently advanced, a causeway was built across the reclaimed land and the new bridge, named Little Holland Bridge, was built, although on the 1777 map the approach road through the marshes is depicted as a series of dashes to mean that the route was rather impermanent or uncertain and liable to flood.  The date of the bridge is uncertain, but it had probably not been built long when it was first recorded in the 1720s.  This bridge was locally significant as it was the first time that a direct road communication existed between Little Holland and Great Holland on the two sides of the old estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can explore&lt;strong&gt; Reclaiming the Estuary&lt;/strong&gt; using the suggested activities and assets below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How has the landscape changed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spot the difference in the landscape using &lt;strong&gt;maps &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1777&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/gunfleet-estuary-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  You can play a game of spot the difference by using two maps and challenging a partner to find as many differences between them as possible.  At the end make a list of what has changed and what has stayed the same.  You could also play this as a question and answer activity, with players trying to work out their partner’s chosen map or map feature by asking and answering questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider the effects of natural processes &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;maps &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1777&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/gunfleet-estuary-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to overlay and trace the physical features of the landscape creating a new map showing how the landscape has changed over time.  Use your knowledge of natural processes (long shore drift, silting, and erosion) to label the new map showing how each has had an impact on the landscape.  Extend this activity by adding in labels for human features (river crossings, roads).  Use the new map to explain the consequences of the physical changes for local people in terms of industry, agriculture, and communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building bridges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;maps &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-map-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1777&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/gunfleet-estuary-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1838&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your team are in charge of building a bridge at Holland Haven in 1594, 1777 or 1838.  It could be a new bridge to cross the river or a replacement for an existing bridge.  The answers to these suggested questions might help you think about where your bridge should be and what it might be built from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you need a bridge? (think about people, jobs, travel)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where is a good place for the bridge? (think about how wide the river is, how marshy the land is)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What will the bridge look like? (think about materials, coast and strength)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a competition to design and build a river crossing for each of the dates.  At the bridge opening each team will need to explain their choices of location, design and materials. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 12:58:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24626 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Feeding the Capital</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/feeding-capital</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet estuary was formerly known as the Gunfleet Haven, the word haven meaning a port or harbour for boats.  This name is used in customs documents and surveys from the reign of Elizabeth I, revealing the role of Gunfleet Haven as a port at that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the past, goods could be easily transported between Essex, London and the rest of the country using the waterways and sea.  Quays, wharves and landing places along the Holland Brook were easily accessible along tracks leading directly from surrounding farmland.  Beaumont Quay, accessible from Hamford Water, is a surviving example of a small local quay and can be used as indication of what the Gunfleet estuary may have been like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corn and hay grown in nearby fields, and cheese that was produced in local dairies called “wicks”, was exported to London from these small quays.  Sheep kept on the marshland surrounding the estuary were kept for wool, meat, and also for their milk which was used to make these large Essex ‘Wicks’ cheeses which were exported as a cheap foodstuff to London.  Jaywick is a good example locally of a place with wick in its name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corn might also be taken from the farms to nearby mills for grinding into flour to make bread.  A good number of these local mills were tide mills located on the coastline, especially around the Colne, Hamford Water and the Stour.  Tide mills rely on the timing and strength of the tides so would need to be worked at night when necessary and in conjunction with a windmill, as at Thorrington and Walton-on-the-Naze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although much of the flour produced would be for local consumption, tide mills had easy access to sea communications and probably all of them had a wharf or quay adjacent which could be used for bringing in corn and exporting flour for use elsewhere. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex County Council own and maintain Thorrington Tide Mill which is restored and open to the public on certain days. It is one of the few tide mills in Great Britain that is still operational and is of national significance in explaining how the natural resources were harnessed to produce power in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barges that sailed to London with goods did not return empty.  The two-way traffic between Essex and the capital is described in a 1727 survey of Beaumont Hall.  The survey noted that there were two &quot;very convenient landing places for bringing chalk rubbish from Kent and carrying of corn or any other thing off to London&quot;.   Chalk was brought as a soil improver from quarries along the Thames estuary in both Essex and Kent, along with another soil improver, horse manure and human &#039;night soil&#039;.   Barges might also bring cargoes of building materials, such as stone, flint or bricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Farmers in Essex wanted to apply chalk to the land to correct high levels of acidity in the soil and improve crop yields.  Chalk could simply be spread on the land but was more efficient when used to create ‘quicklime’.  There was a further demand for lime for use in lime mortars in the building industry in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Producing lime from chalk required a kiln which would have been a natural addition to the facilities alongside many of the small Essex quays, wharves and landing places.  At Beaumont Quay there is a fairly rare East Anglian (mixed-feed) design kiln.  It is a circular red brick building within an earthen mound, and is approximately 2.5 metres high and 13 metres in diameter.  The kiln was probably in continuous use and the quay would have large heaps of chalk and coal around ready for processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heyday of Beaumont Quay was the mid and late 19th century when improvements in agricultural production and yields persuaded the owners to invest in creating a more efficient quay.  In 1831 stone from the demolition of London Bridge was used to build a new quay and a deeper channel or canal was cut.  Along with a basin that enabled boats to turn these improvements meant that the quay was suitable for use by larger vessels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can explore&lt;strong&gt; Essex feeding the capital &lt;/strong&gt;using the suggested activities and assets below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Put Holland Haven in a regional context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/possible-landing-places-gunfleet-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible landing places on the Gunfleet Estuary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, image of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/barges-thorirngton-tide-mill-1929&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;barges at Thorrington Tide Mill &lt;/a&gt;(1929), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/beaumont-quay-surveyed-1727-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beaumont Quay surveyed in 1727&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/lime-kiln-beaumont-quay-exterior&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lime kiln at Beaumont Quay&lt;/a&gt; (1), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/feeding-capital&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thorrington Tide Mill in 1777&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design your own way to illustrate the movement of resources between Essex and London.  Perhaps this could be a circular flow chart or river display.  Make sure that your chosen method describes what is sent to London, from where and why, and what is brought to Essex, from where and why.  Can you demonstrate how the resources coming to Essex contribute to local activity and future exports?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renewable energy in Holland Haven&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use image of &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/barges-thorirngton-tide-mill-1929&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;barges at Thorrington Tide Mill &lt;/a&gt;(1929), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/diagram-typical-undershot-tide-mill-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Diagram of typical undershot of Tide Mill&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/mill-stones-after-restoration&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mill stones after restoration&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/thorrington-tide-mill-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thorrington Tide Mill in 1777&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/possible-landing-places-gunfleet-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Possible landing places on the Gunfleet estuary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a list of as many power sources as you can (include renewables such as wind and water as well as non-renewables such as coal).   Discuss or group these by how these are used today, for example, we use petrol in cars, create electricity from fossil fuels etc) and consider the advantages and disadvantages of each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use the sources for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thorrington-tide-mill-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thorrington Mill&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, powered by the tides, to demonstrate how renewable sources were used in the past to provide power that is now produced in other ways.  What are the advantages and limitations of these sources?  How did the millers at Thorrington overcome any limitations?  Design, make and test your own model mills, either a windmill or watermill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extend this to consider the wider use of local natural resources such as rivers and the coastline as a method of transport and communication network.   How is similar or different to today?  You could use the sources to make your own model windmill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A working Quay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/plan-beaumont-quay-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;plan of Beaumont Quay&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/barge-rose-beaumont-quay-1960s&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The barge Rose at Beaumont Quay &lt;/a&gt;(1), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/lime-kiln-beaumont-quay-interior&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lime kiln at Beaumont Quay &lt;/a&gt;(1 &amp;amp; 2)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are working at Beaumont Quay in the 19th century.  Use the images and plan to think about what work and activity happened at the quay at its peak.  You could ask Who worked or visited here? (boat workers, farmers, kiln workers, customs officials, smugglers) What did it look like?  What did it feel like (smells, sounds, environment)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write or illustrate a day in the life of the quay describing the goods coming through the quay, where they are going to and from and for who, improvements at the quay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 11:12:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24625 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>An introduction to Holland Haven </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/introduction-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, Holland Haven is the place where the Holland River (now the Holland Brook) once ran out into the North Sea between Clacton and Frinton in Essex.  This estuary was called the Gunfleet and it was once wide enough for boats to sail through it and in 1677 for a whale to become stranded there.  Towards the end of the 17th century a sea wall was built across the mouth of the estuary, the land behind the wall was reclaimed from the sea and converted to marshland pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographically, the Essex coastline is characterised by a series of creeks, inlets and estuaries which in the past have allowed access for small boats to sail inland.  When the Gunfleet estuary was open to the North Sea, small boats may have been able to sail up river as far as Thorpe-le-Soken. Small wharves and landing places were built along the banks of Holland River allowing crops grown on nearby farms and other local produce to be loaded easily onto boats and carried along the river, out to sea, into the Thames estuary and into London. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote and out of the way landing places could also be used to avoid customs control and the isolated marshes at Holland were notorious in the past for smugglers even after the estuary was reclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can get an idea of what it would have been like in the Gunfleet estuary by looking at nearby Beaumont Quay on Hamford Water which was used as a landing place for boats from the Middle Ages to the 1930s.  From here barges were loaded with produce such as corn, hay, cheese and timber, and brought return cargoes, mainly building materials or soil improvers such as manure and chalk from London, Kent and Essex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature in this landscape would have been tide mills, different to water mills or windmills as they use the ebb and flow of the tides to power the waterwheel.  The Essex coastline was dotted with this ancient type of mill with sites identified at nearby Thorrington, St Osyth and Walton-on-the-Naze.  The work of tide mills was often supplemented by a nearby windmill such as at Thorrington and Walton-on-the-Naze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that alongside agriculture, the copperas industry was also important locally in the 17th and 18th centuries.  Copperas stones (which were actually iron pyrites) were washed out of the London Clay cliffs onto the shore and converted to copperas (green vitriol) at factories known as Copperas Houses.  Copperas was used for various purposes such as dyes and inks.  The stones were collected by local people all along the coast from Clacton, Frinton and Walton, and were also dredged up from the Copperas Bank off the coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reclaimed estuary is now used for leisure pursuits, including the Holland Haven country park and Frinton Golf Links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	You can explore&lt;strong&gt; An introduction to Holland &lt;/strong&gt;Haven using the suggested activities and assets below.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use maps to introduce your study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a modern map to locate the Holland Haven area by first viewing Europe, UK, East Anglia, the Essex coastline (naming the North Sea, London and the Thames estuary), and finally Clacton, Walton and Frinton.  Use these key places to locate the course of the Holland Brook and notice the marshes, follow the length of the Brook - it looks a bit like a ladder.  Find other places of interest such as your school, local beaches and houses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use one or more of the maps &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Norden 1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chapman and André 1777 &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ordnance-survey-map-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OS 1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ordnance-survey-map-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;to find out what was it like here in the past.  Compare the historic map with your modern map.  You can use the map showing &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/land-liable-flood-holland-levels&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;land liable to flood on the Holland Marshes&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;as an indication of the size of the former estuary.  These are some suggestions to help you explore what is the same and different:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for local place names and spellings.  It might help to read them out loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the shape of the roads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the shape of the coastline and waterways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locate crossings over the river and if you are using more than one map check if they are on each one.  What does this tell us about when they were built?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see any buildings? What are they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extend this activity by tracing or overlaying the maps chronologically to locate, describe and label the changes that have happened in the landscape including the shape of the estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was life like here for people in the past?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use images&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/copperas-pickers-shoreline-harwich&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; “Copperas pickers” on the shoreline at Harwich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;photos&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/thorrington-mill-1929&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thorrington Mill &lt;/a&gt;(1929), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/beaumont-quay-1960-showing-rose-and-warehouse&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beaumont Quay &lt;/a&gt;(1960) &lt;/strong&gt;and documents&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/stranding-monstrous-whale-1677&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;‘A monstrous whale’&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/poaching-holland-marshes-1609-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Poaching on Holland Marshes &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;and&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/possible-landing-places-gunfleet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Possible landing places on the Gunfleet Estuary &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;and choose one or more&lt;strong&gt; maps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about what you would like to know and group your questions under headings (for example, work, food, events).  Look at each source for the information it gives you to answer your questions.  Move on to another source and add in more information.  Remember that there are additional assets for you to use on other parts of the VCH Explore site (link to home?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go on a fieldtrip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a modern map and historic map together to plan a route for a walk or place to visit.  Aim to take in as many of the landmarks and features identified in the previous activities as possible.  Take photos or make sketches and use these to label a copy of the map.  Add labels with the answers from your previous activities, and explain the connections between past and present human and physical features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24612 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Walton&#039;s Copperas House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/waltons-copperas-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Walton was one of the chief places for the production of Copperas or green vitriol (ferrous sulphate), which was used for a variety of purposes including inks and dyes. An important by-product of the manufacturing process was sulphuric acid. The Copperas was manufactured from pyrites (bisulphide of iron, FeS2) washed out of the London clay cliffs at Walton&#039;s Naze onto the shore. There the raw material was collected by &quot;Copperas pickers&quot; - the wives and children of fishermen and other poor people, who were paid in tokens. Some Copperas stones were also dregded up from the sea floor by boats. The material was then taken to a Copperas House (a factory) to be chemically transformed into the green vitriol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chronology at Walton:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not known exactly when Copperas production was established at Walton, but it was probably in the 17th century. Daniel Defoe, writing in 1724, noted that &quot;At Walton-on-the-Naze, they find on the shoar copperas-stone in great quantities; and there are several works, call&#039;d Copperas Houses where they make it with great expence&quot;. Samuel Dale, writing in 1730, stated that there had been two Copperas Houses in 1696, but that one had since been washed away by the sea. Coastal erosion was certainly a constant problem at Walton, although it also provided the raw pyritic material from the cliffs for the Copperas industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copperas Houses were very valuable and most of those in south-east England were controlled by a group of families with strong social links. By 1702 the Walton works were in the hands of the Hopkins family who owned other works including that at Brightlingsea. Rights to the raw Copperas found on the shore were usually owned by the local Lord of the Manor from whom the Copperas manufacturers took a lease to enable them to legally collect it. In 1772 the Lord of the Manor of Walton, the Rt. Hon.  William Henry, Earl of Rochford, of St Osyth Priory, leased the rights to Ephraim Rinhold Seelil (or Seckl) for 21 years at £42 p.a. Seelil owned a similar works at Blackwall (Kent). By the early 19th century the Walton factory had passed to Charles Pearson, a Copperas magnate who attempted to dominate the industry and who controlled 30% of production in southern England by 1808. The attempt failed and the Pearson family were bankrupted c.1835 as the industry began to decline. Although production at Walton ceased sometime in the earlier 19th century, the raw material continued to be collected there until the late 19th century when it was being transported to chemical factories in London and Ipswich.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Copperas House and the manufacturing process:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a detailed inventory of the Copperas House from 1702 indicating that it had a boiler and several coolers, a great variety of tools and equipment and much old scrap iron. The Copperas House was located between Mill Lane and Vicarage Lane, close to Walton Channel, the Tidal Mill and wharves there, a water supply being important for both the manufacturing process and for the export of the final product. The factory needed quite a lot of open space, typically called a Copperas Ground, where the large tanks could be arranged. A set of depositions in a legal case, probably from the later 18th century, records a dispute over the ownership and rights of access to Copperas House Wharf. In 1907 there was still a piece of open ground at Walton saturated with sulphurous matter and having visible remnants of leaden tanks and pipes from the old factory. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An account of the manufacture of Copperas at Walton in the 19th century, recorded in VCH Essex, Volume II, notes the process used. The Copperas was first packed into heaps into which scrap-iron was introduced and then moistened. The action of the air and water then oxidised the copperas into ferrous sulphate of iron (green vitriol or Copperas) and sulphuric acid. Extra scrap iron could be added which reacted with the sulphuric acid to produce more vitriol. The solution was then removed to leaden tanks or boilers and the water evaoprated by heat so concentrating the product. It was then removed again to a cooler, where rods were placed across the product onto which the Copperas crystallized. It could then be gathered and packed into barrels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details of the origins and development of the whole industry see the separate word document provided as an Explore Asset &quot;The Copperas Industry&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office, D/DB T608; D/DHw T19; D/Y 37/2/43; D/DU 5/49, 5/50, 5/62.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre,&lt;em&gt; Map of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S. Dale, &lt;em&gt;The History and Antiquities of Harwich and Dovercourt &lt;/em&gt;(1730)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. George and S. Vincent, &#039;Report of Field Meeting to walton-on-the-Naze and Wrabness&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Tertiary Research&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. 1, No. 3 (June 1777), pp.87-90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J.C. Shenstone, &#039;Copperas Industry&#039;, in W. Page and J.H. Round (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Victoria Hitsory of the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. II (1907), pp. 411-13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T. Allen, M. Cotterill &amp;amp; G. Pike, &lt;em&gt;Copperas. An Account of the Whitstable Works and the first Industrial-scale chemical production in England &lt;/em&gt;(Canterbury Archeological Trust, Occasional Paper, No. 2, 2004).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 18:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24246 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Sands and Channel</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-sands-and-channel</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet sandbank lies off the coastline of Tendring district, directly opposite (east) of the entrance to the former Gunfleet estuary (also known as Gunfleet Haven or Holland Haven). Between the sandbank and the coast was a protected channel and anchorage, but the dangers of the sands have long been known to mariners and large numbers of vessels and their crews have been shipwrecked there over the centuries. From at least the 17th century the sands have been marked by buoys and also by a beacon or lighthouse. In recent years the Gunfleet Sandbank has been used as the site of an off-shore wind farm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name &#039;Gunfleet&#039; was first recorded in 1318 when a vessel was shipwrecked on &#039;Gunfletsond&#039;, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. In the reign of Henry VIII (1509-1542) the &#039;Gonflete&#039; was also recorded as a sandbank, and a map of 1584 marks both the &#039;Gonflet Haven&#039; (the estuary) and &#039;ye gonflit&#039; (the sandbank). Thus the name of the estuary had clearly been appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary&#039;s inlet. The safer water between the sands and the inlet, now known as the Wallet, also seem to have been commonly known as the Gunfleet in the later 17th century when the English or Dutch fleets anchored there during the Dutch Wars. Similar uses of place-names including &#039;fleet&#039; for coastal channels can be found elsewhere, a good example being the Fleet in Dorset, a long narrow channel separated from the English Channel by the major sandbank known as Chesil Bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the former estuary was reclaimed for agriculture from the late 17th century onwards, so the original name was largely forgotten on land and replaced by the name Holland Haven. But off of the coastline the name has been preserved as the Gunfleet Sands into the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s map of Essex (1594).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1935), pp. 13-17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lt.-Co. A.R. Solly, &#039;Gunfleet - Haven, Anchorage and Sand&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Essex Review&lt;/em&gt;, LX (1951), pp.203-06.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 10:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24236 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Barton&#039;s Pans</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bartons-pans</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barton&#039;s Pans lie immediately behind the line of the sea wall built by the Tendring Level Commissioners across the mouth of the Gunfleet estuary. They are located from just west of Chevaux de Frise point running east to Holland Gap towards Frinton. They take the form of rectangular pits, lagoons or pools, filled with water and overgrown with reeds. At least 24 separate pits were shown on an Ordnance Survey map of 1898, and although some have now disappeared or shrunk they are still a very prominent landscape feature. They are not modern because they were mentioned in the Tendring Level Commissioners Minute Book of 1782, as follows: &lt;em&gt;&quot;That part of the wall adjoining to a place called Bartons Pans wants strengthening and heightening and footing for near three hundred yards in length, and that water from the said pans ought to be drained at all times from out of the same.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission&#039;s map of the Level from 1783 also marks the location of the Pans, while the Commissioners minutes from 1786 notes that the sea wall next to Barton&#039;s Pans was &quot;&lt;em&gt;by the violence of the sea becoming ruinous, defcetive and out of repair.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;The &#039;Pans&#039; are also depicted on a military survey of Holland Marsh in 1805 (part of the defence planning aginst the threat of invasion by Napoleon Bonaparte&#039;s French army), being shown as lying between Chevaux de Frise Point and Sandy Point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto the &#039;Pans&#039; do not appear to have been studied, and their origin and purpose is shrouded in mystery. One hypothesis proposed is that material for the earliest sea walls was excavated from them. However, this explanation has not appeared fully convincing. Would suitable material have been available for excavation at the mouth of the old estuary? Also some of the &#039;Pans&#039; depicted on maps also seem too regular in form (rectangular), and at the eastern and western ends do not precisely conform to the line of the sea wall. Other suggestions have been that they represent salt-pans (where salt was produced by heating or evaporation) or oyster-layings or tanks (where the young oyster brood were matured). However,no local documentary evidence has been found of either of these industries on such a large-scale as this site would imply. Also, before the sea wal, the &#039;Pans&#039; would have lain on the open coast in the mouth of the Gunfleet estuary, probably not a suitable site for either salt or oyster production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explanation that currently seems most attractive is that the &#039;Pans&#039; are evidence of the Copperas industry which we know was locally important in the 17th and 18th centuries. Copperas was the name for green vitriol that was manufactured from nodules of bisulphide of iron (otherwise known as pyrites) washed out of the London Clay cliffs onto the shore. It was used for various purposes such as dyes, fixatives and inks. Copperas stones were collected by the local poor people all along the coast from Clacton, Frinton and Walton, and also dredged up from the Copperas Bank off the coast. There were several methods of production, but in one system the Copperas stones were heaped into large open vats or pits full of water and exposed to the elements for a period of time (sometimes several years) before being removed to undergo various manufacturing processes at Coppers Houses, of which there were important local ones at Walton and Brightlingsea, and possibly another one at Frinton. Perhaps Barton&#039;s Pans were established for the Copperas industry after the sea wall was built towards the end of the 17th century?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further evidence that may link Barton&#039;s Pans with the industry comes from the surviving Tokens with which the local poor - the &quot;Copperas pickers&quot; - were paid, and the names of the local landowners who issued them. Tokens survive that were issued by John Kirby at Walton dated 1736, and it seems probable that he was related to the Kirby family who through marriage obtained Great Holland Manor in the later 18th century. A map of 1777 indicates that a track led from Great Holland Hall directly to Barton&#039;s Pans. Copperas also appears to have been collected at Frinton from the mid 17th century onwards, and as early as 1637 the lord of the manor, Sir Harbottle Grimston, was involved in the industry. In 1746 the right to gather Copperas still belonged to Frinton manor, and the lessee of the manor named John Rice minted tokens to pay workers both at Frinton and at &#039;Minster&#039; - either Minster in Thanet or Minster in Sheppey (both in Kent). John Rice&#039;s local involvement is particularly revealing as he may only have taken the lease of the manor to acquire its Copperas rights, as he is probably the same John Rice of Deptford (Kent) who was a member of one of the leading families involved with the industry in Kent and Essex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/ST 2: Tendring Level Commission, Minute Book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 17: Map of the Tendringlevel by W. Cole (1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, T/A 15/2/2; ERO, D/DWv/T80; ERO D/UFw C9/23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, Map of Essex (1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, MPHH 1/548: Major Bryce&#039;s Survey of Holland Marsh, October 1805.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J.C. Shenstone, &#039;Copperas Industry&#039;, in W. Page and J.H. Round (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Victoria Historyof the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. II (1907), pp. 411-13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T. Allen, M. Cotterill and G. Pike, &lt;em&gt;Copperas. An account of the Whitstable Works and the first industrial-scale chemical production in England&lt;/em&gt; (Canterbury Archaeological Trust, Occasional paper, No. 2, 2004), pp. 32, 37-8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 12:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24107 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Tendring Level (Holland Haven)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/tendring-level-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for sea defence and drainage in coastal regions since the early thirteenth century had been allocated to &lt;em&gt;ad hoc &lt;/em&gt;Commissions of walls and ditches (&lt;em&gt;de walliis et fossatiis&lt;/em&gt;) appointed by the Crown. The commissioners were officers who had powers to enforce local communal responsibilities for the maintenance of sea walls, banks and drains, and thus attempt to prevent flooding and the inroads of the sea. They could make local by-laws and raise rates to ensure the essential work was undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such commissioners for Tendring Hundred (equivalent to the modern Tendring district) were first recorded about 1450, when the abbot of St Osyth, John Godmanston, esq., John Green and Robert Tanfield and others were appointed. The powers of such royal Commissions was consolidated by Statute in 1531 in A General Act concerning Commissions of Sewers. This was enacted &#039;considering daily great damages and losses which have happened in many and diverse parts ... by reason of the outrageous flowing surges and course of the sea in and upon marsh grounds and other low places&#039;. Under the 1531 At the Commissions initially only lasted three years, but another Commissions of Sewers Act of 1571 later extended the term to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the Tendring commissioners met infrequently for information about the 15th and 16th centuries is scant, and the extent of the sea defences around the Gunfleet estuary and on the coastline of Great Holland, Little Holland and Frinton remains unknown. A reference to &#039;le level de Gunfletehaven&#039; in 1542 may indicate that some drainage activity had taken place, for the word &#039;level&#039; was often used of partly reclaimed marshlands of the type protected by the activities of commissioners. Other examples of the use of the word are the Somerset Levels and the Gwent Levels of south-east Wales. A document concerning poaching at Little Holland in 1609 referred to &#039;a drowned land called the Flatts&#039;, and the same term was used as an alternative for the Tendring Level in 1703.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would seem that the gradual silting up of the Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook or River that fed it necessitated a response from the commissioners, probabaly stimulated by those whose livelihood was being affected by the flooding and perhaps the loss of trading opportunities. The response was a plan to make a sea wall across the estuary between Little Holland and Frinton, and thus reclaim by drainage the former estuary. It is not known precisely when the sea wall was first constructed, but it appears to have been sometime in the 17th century. A survey of the Tendring Level after the Great Storm of 1703 mentioned a &#039;breach&#039; that had been made, suggesting that the sea wall existed by that date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sluice was included in the new wall which could be opned at low tide to allow the river watre to escape, the sluice gate then being closed to prevent th rising tide from entering and flooding the newly won marshes. The original sluice was at Sandy Point near Frinton which seems to have been the natural outfall of the river water from the Holland Brook, although it was later moved east to the site of the present sluice at Holland Haven. As a result many hundreds of acres of land were reclaimed in the parishes of Great Holland, Little Holland, Frinton, Great Clacton, Little Clacton and Thorpe-le-Soken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K. Walker, &#039;The battle of the Clacton peninsula. Man versus the sea&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Essex Review&lt;/em&gt;, Volume LXIV (1955), pp.103-11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1935), p. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Yelloly Watson, &lt;em&gt;The Tendring Hundred in the Olden Time &lt;/em&gt;(1877), p. 70-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/DHw E14: A true survey of ye Levell or Flatts (1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, Q/SR 189/25: Quarter Sessions, pocahing case, 1609.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, Catalogue explanations under references C191, C225, C226.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 11:48:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24095 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland Brook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-brook-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Holland Brook, sometimes called the Holland River, has been rather overlooked as an important landscape feature of Tendring Hundred (the older name for Tendring district). Even the original name of the watercourse is uncertain, although as the Holland Brook fed into the Gunfleet estuary that may record the original name of the river - the Gunfleet. The names Gunfleet Haven and Holland Haven both seem to refer to the original estuary that was later permanently reclaimed from the sea by the Tendring Levels Commissioners in the 17th and 18th centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brook was regarded as important enough for its course to be described in versions of Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles dating from 1577 and 1587: &quot;Betwixt the Naze also and the mouth of the Colne, is another Ryll which riseth at Little Bentley, and thence goeth to Tendryng thorpe, thorow Clacten parke by great Holland, and east of little Holland into the deepe sea&quot;. The accurate description draws attention to the length of the watercoruse or &#039;rill&#039; from its source near Little Bentley and Little Bromley down to the sea at Little Holland, which virtually divided Tendring Hundred in half. Several features are worthy of note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the original Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook and its valley probably provided an important access route from the coast into the interior of Tendring Hundred both in prehistoric and later periods. There is considerable evidence from cropmarks for early settlement around the upper reaches of the brook in Tendring and neighbouring parishes. The brook may also have had an influence upon the later Anglo-Saxon and medieval patterns of settlement. It may, for example, be no coincidence that the brook leads to the parish of Tendring, which was the central place of the Hundred (the Hundred assembly met on Tendring Heath), and which name is probaby derived from a place-name in Germany transferred to this location by Anglo-Saxon migrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the Holland Brook and the Gunfleet estuary later provided a considerable barrier to east-west road communications. A number of bridges were therefore eventually established, presumably starting furthest inland where the watercourse could be more easily bridged. That at Rice bridge, between Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, seems to have been present by the 14th century. Further downstream that at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, was first recorded in 1509, and that at Holland bridge, between Great and Little Holland, in 1727 (after the former estuary had been reclaimed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the Holland brook and Gunfleet estuary were fed by a number of smaller streams in the parishes along their route, and the system effectively drained much of the centre of Tendring Hundred and many thousands of acres of farmland. Some of the tributary streams were quite small, but others like Picker&#039;s Ditch leading west from the Gunfleet towards Great Clacton were quite substantial. The potential for flooding was therefore very large, and after the Gunfleet or Holland Haven was reclaimed as marshland pasture by the Tendring Levels Commissioners they had to work hard expending money and enforcing maintenance upon local landowners to keep the channels clear so as to prevent major flooding incidents. Even in winter today the course of the brook and the old estuary is often marked by the flooded marshlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(Cambridge, 1935), 17, 325, 351-2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map of Tendring Hundred from P. Morant, &lt;em&gt;The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, I (1768).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles: http://www.english.ox.ac.uk/holinshed/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Explore Asset under this heading: Map of land liable to flood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See other Explore Items on Rice bridge; Fan bridge; Holland bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 10:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24091 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Holland bridge is the most recent bridge to cross the Holland River (or Holland Brook), and the furthest downstream. Maps of 1594 and 1603 indicate that there was no route at that time across the Gunfleet estuary which would therefore have still formed a major barrier to land communications along the coast. Then the first crossing point was at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, some one and a half to two miles inland from the sea. As a result, there was probably much communication in small boats across the Gunfleet estuary and along the coast in the sheltered waters of the Gunfleet Channel (now known as the Wallet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, probably sometime towards the end of the 17th century the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs decided to construct a sea wall across the mouth of the estuary which was becoming silted up. As the former Gunfleet estuary behind the sea wall was converted to marshland pastures (although still liuable to winter flooding), so the course of the Holland River became channelled into a water way, now known as the Holland Brook, that ran through its lowest part. The river water, resulting from the many thousands of acres draining into the Holland Brook, was discharged into the sea via a sluice built in the new sea wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the reclamation works were considered advanced sufficiently, a causeway was built across the reclaimed land and a new bridge, named Little Holland bridge, was built over the brook. The date of the bridge is uncertain, but it was first recorded in 1727. The bridge was locally significant for it was the first time that a direct road communication existed between the settlements of Little Holland and Great Holland on the two sides of the old estuary. Chapman and Andre&#039;s map of Essex in 1777 shows the nature of the land half a century after the bridge was first built. A road led from Little Holland Hall into the marhses and then crossed the Holland brook by the new bridge before travelling northwards through the marshes and up the valley side towards Great Holland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach road to the bridge through the marshes in 1777 was depicted as a series of dashes indicating that the route was rather impermanet or uncertain and liable to flood. Chapman and Andre often depicted roads in this way when they crossed common land or where routes were poorly demarcated; another example is their map of the route through the marshes east of Fan bridge. The present Holland bridge appears to date from the early 20th century and until rceent years it had a metal sign indicating where the Great and Little Holland parish boundaries met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map, 1&quot; (1838).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/ST 20 (Map of part of TendrinG level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tednring Levels Commissioners&#039; Map (early 20th century; in private ownership).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 18:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24008 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rice bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rice-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rice bridge is the earliest recorded crossing point on the river now known as the Holland Brook, and one of the furthest inland. It was in existence by 1319 when an Agnes de Risbregge (Agnes of Rice Bridge) was recorded in a taxation return for Little Clacton. Her name probably meant that she lived at or near the bridge. The bridge also gave its name to the surrounding land as an estate called Risbridge or Rosebridge was recorded in the later 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bridge was built on a route that was probably locally important in the Middle Ages. Not ony did it connect the two parishes of Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, but also the manors on either side of the river that were owned by the bishop pf London and his cathedral church of St Paul&#039;s. In the Domesday Book of 1086 the bishop held the manor of Clacton (comprising both Great Clacton and Little Clacton)  while all of Thorpe-le-Soken, Kirby-le-Soken and Walton-le-Soken were held by the Dean and Chapter of St Paul&#039;s (the cathderal clergy). By 1127 on one side of the bridge lay Little Clacton park, a deerpark owned by the bishop, while on the other side lay Thope park, a deerpark owned by the Dean and Chapter. The road over Rice bridge therefore connected the two church estates and their hunting parks. Possiby the huntsmen ranged across both parks quite freely, otherwise the deer could have swum across the river to safety!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name Rice bridge is itself very informative, as it probably originates in the Old English words &#039;hris&#039; (meaning brushwood) and &#039;brycg&#039; (meaning bridge or causeway). The crossing may therefore have started out as a timber bridge or causeway and it probably continued in that form for many centuries. In 1612 the tenants of Thorpe Park and Clacton Park were ordered to &#039;make&#039; the bridge (perhaps from timber available in the deer parks), and it was still described as a wooden footbridge in 1783. County maps from 1594 and 1603 show a main road from Little Clacton and Weeley towards Thorpe, Kirby and Walton that crossed the Holland River at what must be Rice bridge, although it was not named. A survey of the Holland Levels by the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs in 1703 named Rice bridge, and many maps from the 18th century such as that by Chapman and Andre in 1777 show the same route. The present brick built Rice bridge dates from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (Cambridge, 1935), p. 336.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P. Morant, The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex (1768), Volume II, p. 475.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M. Gibbs (ed), The Early Charters of St Paul&#039;s (Camden Society, 3rd series, lviii, 1939), no. 60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London Metropolitan Archive, Guildhall Library, MS. 25416/3; MS. 9531/6, f.192v.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), Q/SR 199/79, 154, 155 (Quarter Sessions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/DHw E14 (A true survey of ye Levll or Flatts ... several parcells of land endamaged at or near Gun-Fleet Haven, 1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 20 (Map of part of Tendring Level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 17:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24006 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
