<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - City of Brighton and Hove</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/county/city-brighton-and-hove</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>St Peter&#039;s Church, London Road, City of Brighton and Hove</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-peters-church-london-road-city-brighton-and-hove</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;St. Peter&#039;s Church was designed by Charles Barry. It was the third of his churches in this style but is considered to be the most elegant. In the City of brighton and Hove it plays a key role as a landmark at the north end of the North Steine and is visible from the Royal Pavilion. When the gardens were managed to present an eye-catching series of displays between the two buildings, a task managed by a series of local government bodies from the early nineteenth century until the 1970s, the church helped to give the whole area a sense of entity. It also stimulated the development of good quality terraced housing up the sides of the Steine, adding to the wonderful Georgian legacy that had already been built, some of which survives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time that the parish of Brighton had seriously considered building a daughter church, the population of the parish, into which the resort was packed, had reached 24,000. Anglican worship was served by a small medieval church called St Nicholas of Myra which was packed with Georgian pews and galleried and by several privately owned chapels of ease.  Land was given by Thomas Read Kemp and his fellow owners of the pastures and meadows of Brighton. The parish formed a church building committee which held a competition for a design for a new church.  They approved Barry&#039;s design and William Ranger began work at the end of 1823. progress was slow and the church was consecrated in 1828. Built of Portland stone, it cost £21,865 and was one of the most expensive churches built by a parish in this period.  The tower was designed by Barry to provide elegant stairs to the galleries which have been removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elegant north (liturgical west) end was lost when Somers Clarke Jnr and J.T. Micklethwaite extended the nave and added a deep chancel in 1899-1906.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more see Sue Berry &#039;The construction of St. Peter&#039;s Church Brighton c1818-1835&#039; Sussex Archaeological Collections Vol. 148 (2010) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2010 09:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20392 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Pleasure Gardens in the City of Brighton and Hove</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/pleasure-gardens-city-brighton-and-hove-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pleasure gardens an essential part of the life of Georgian resorts but also common in other prosperous towns such as Lewes in East Sussex.  Brighton&#039;s first pleasure garden was carved out of common land close to the sea and called the Steine. This appears on many mid to later eighteenth century images of the resort. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first private garden was The Promenade garden which lasted 1793 until 1802 when the land was sold to the Prince of Wales who was keen to extend the grounds to the Pavilion and also close off East Street which ran right past the main entrance to the Pavilion. To do this he had to offer an alternative road and so part of the Promenade Garden was taken into the grounds and the rest became part of New Road. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1822 the next privately run garden opened. Ireland&#039;s Gardens stood on land owned by Thomas Read Kemp (see separate section about him) and he helped to fund the landscaping to the tune of £2,000.  The gardens were closed in 1833.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find out more about this and the other gardens see Sue Berry &#039;Pleasure Gardens in Georgian and Regency Seaside Resorts: Brighton, 1750-1840&#039; in The Journal of Garden History, 1992, 220-229.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(C) Sue Berry &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 21:33:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20388 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Pleasure Gardens in the City of Brighton and Hove</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/pleasure-gardens-city-brighton-and-hove</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pleasure gardens were essential recreational facilities in spa and seaside resorts before 1840 but the majority did not last long. Many were either modelled on or influenced by the pleasure gardens in London such as Vauxhall. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late eighteenth century and for a combination of reasons, Brighton became the biggest seaside resort in Britain.  Pleasure gardens in this resort fell into two simple categories. The free pleasure gardens ran up from the sea northwards to where St Peter&#039;s Church was built in the mid 1820s, a wonderful eye-catcher from the south. These were maintained by the town&#039;s Commissioners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promenade Grove opened in 1793 in a large garden which had belonged to the Brighton home of Sir Lucas Pepys ( a well known doctor) and his wife (The Countess of Rothes). The land was sold to the Prince of Wales in 1802 when he sought to enlarge his estate and also close the north end of East Street which passed right past the Royal Pavilion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ireland&#039;s Gardens was an enterprise of Thomas Read Kemp (see separate entry) who invested £2,000 in its layout. It was on his newly enclosed land north of St Peter&#039;s Church. Part of the venture later became the park around which Park Crescent now stands. Ireland&#039;s was incomplete in 1824 and in spite of the drawings which show it complete, this may be untrue. In 1833 the gardens had a different tenant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information see Sue Berry &#039;Pleasure Gardens in Georgian and Regency Seaside Resorts: Brighton, 1750-1840&#039; Journal of Garden History, 1991, 220-229.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 18:26:09 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20387 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Declining coastal towns become seaside resorts - the case of Brighton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/declining-coastal-towns-become-seaside-resorts-case-brighton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; Most places have two histories, the actual and the mythical. Some myths become so well-established that they overshadow the history of a place. One of the most pervasive myths about Brighton is that it was a poor fishing village until (depending on the source), either Dr. Richard Russell or George, Prince of Wales arrived here and singlehandedly turned it in to a fashionable resort. This myth started during the 1770s when Dr Russell was credited with this transformation. Some sources then refer to the Duke of Cumberland as the saviour of Brighton. From the 1780s, the Prince of Wales was usually indentified as the accidental promoter of Brighton’s transformation. These stories, mostly promoted in guide books, overstate the role of these men and obscure a very important fact about Brighton which explains why it and not, for example Rottingdean just eastwards along the coast, became a seaside resort in the 1750s and 1760s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, Brighton was a small town with basic shops, a lot of cheap accommodation and high unemployment. For a short period in the mid to later seventeenth century, it was probably the largest town in Sussex, with a population of perhaps 4,000. The town’s economy depended on long distance fishing, particularly for herring in the North Sea. The fishing industry collapsed for a variety of reasons between about 1670 and 1700. Competition from larger fishing vessels in the herring industry in the North Sea, the acceleration of the coastal erosion that bedevilled the town right into the later 1700s were but two, This town’s decline was accelerated by the loss of the long distance coastal carrying trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the other early resorts; Hastings, Margate, Scarborough and Weymouth were also small coastal towns which needed new sources of employment. Why were the early resorts so similar in character? Small coastal towns had reasonable communication networks – both inland and by sea and backers who were prepared to invest in this new business. These towns normally had financial and other links with more prosperous inland centres. During the 1750s and 1760s a considerable amount of the early capital invested in the basic tourism facilities, such as libraries in Brighton, came from Lewes. Russell had a fashionable practice in Lewes. Shergold, who bought a house in Brighton and turned it into the Castle Inn, was an innkeeper from Lewes. The name of the Inn referred to the Castle in his home town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early resorts had very short seasons during which a few hundred people might visit. In Sanditon, her unfinished story about the development of a new resort, Jane Austen points out that trying to build a resort from new was not easy due to the capital cost of new houses, baths, assembly rooms, a library, a theatre, a chapel, a promenade and bathing machines. In old towns, the risk could be spread between many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1750 and 1780, tourism became a lifeline for the town. Had local landowners, businessmen and doctors not become supporters of the development of tourism here, then Brighton would have shrunk back to the village it had once been in the medieval period. There are many communities in Britain where this happened right into the nineteenth century. The idea of keeping declining towns alive by public subsidy is a twentieth century concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The growth of Brighton exerted a profound influence on all of the parishes now in the City. Rottingdean attracted visitors to sea bathe in the 1760s if not sooner. Hove supplied building materials - bricks and tiles and then space for houses. Preston had a tea garden in the 1760s. The archaeological sites in several parishes were popular to visit. The long lost Hove barrow was one. Several of the graveyards of the ancient parish churches became popular places in which to be buried. The grounds of Stanmer House just a short ride north-east of Brighton (revamped in the 1720s and the Park between the 1720s and 1800) were visited by wealthy visitors to Brighton. Some, from the 1770s, were invited to dine. The surviving guest book is a ‘who’s who’ of the period. Guests included Georgiana, Duchess of Devonshire, George Prince of Wales and many prominent Whigs. These were visiting the flourishing resort to which George Prince of Wales was attracted by its reputation and the social standing of the visitors. He did not found the resort, it has been flourishing for more than twenty years when he appeared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further reading – Berry, S., ‘Myth and Reality in the Representation of Resorts; Brighton and the emergence of the ‘Prince and the fishing village’ myth 1770-1824’ Sussex Archaological Collections 140 (2002) 97-112. Berry, S., Georgian Brighton (Phillimore, 2005).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 20:34:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20385 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Thomas Read Kemp, Landowner and Developer</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thomas-read-kemp-landowner-and-developer</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Read Kemp (1782-1844) inherited land in the parish of Brighton from his father in 1811.  By this time, Brighton had been a flourishing seaside resort for around sixty years, thus starting well before the arrival of George, Prince of Wales who is often wrongly said to be the founder of the town&#039;s transformation from a declining coastal town into a resort. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas Read Kemp&#039;s political interests were in Lewes which he represented as an MP for some time but he knew that his land in Brighton should be a good source of income if it was developed. Most of it was intermingled with others and he slowly began to untangle this to ensure that he obtained blocks of freehold land. His first project was villas in Montpelier, an area which today is known for its distinctive albeit later style. His second, villas along the London Road and his third, Kemp Town which was first mentioned in the local press in 1822 when he began to employ workmen to lay it out to the scheme published as by C.A. Busby and A.H. Wilds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All did not proceed smoothly partly due to the recession which hit this resort in the later 1820s but also to the competition which included not only Brunswick Town but other projects dotted about the resort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kemp understood the value of publicity and helped many local ventures, some by giving land. He also had important backers. His first wife was Frances Baring, the fourth daughter of Sir Francis Baring who founded Barings Bank.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to some local claims, Kemp did not die poor nor was he a bankrupt. Both are myths. To read more see Sue Berry  Thomas Read Kemp and the shaping of Regency Brighton c.1818-1845 in the Journal of the Georgian Group Volume XVII (2009) 125-140.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 18:17:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20381 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Brighton and Hove Transformed c.1818-1832</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/brighton-and-hove-transformed-c1818-1832</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; Between about 1818 and 1832, the landscape of Brighton underwent a rapid transformation, much of it around the outer edge of the Georgian resort. The early Georgian facilities and houses were largely untouched although some of the tourist facilities were by then quite old, dating from Brighton’s early development as a resort which had begun in the 1750s, long before the Prince of Wales arrived in the 1780s to see what two of his uncles were up to down here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early developments which still stood included The Castle Inn with its chapel like Assembly Room (largely 1750s and 1760s), the New Inn (1780s, still in North Street, now largely empty again) and the long narrow streets aligned to paul pieces, the strips of farmland over which they were built , such as Charles Street and Broad Street. The only squares were Bedford and New Steine, both begun in 1799. New Steine, being better located was finished first. Until the later 1810s most visitors rented apartments, not whole houses and so lived here as they did in a lot of Georgian towns and cities, renting only the rooms they needed. Take-away food was common. The local bakers and pubs supplied meals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1818 Brighton was in need of more modern projects which suited both the taste for bigger town houses to rent beside the seaside and also the fashion for entertaining at home. The town was spreading into locations where more large plots of land could be bought for development as squares and crescents. The grander schemes included Brunswick and Kemp Towns, Hanover Crescent and Regency Square. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Investment also flowed in for other projects such as the Chain Pier, the York (now reopened) and the Albion Hotels. The latter built there after a debate about whether or not the Commissioners who ran Brighton should and legally could buy the land on which Russell House had stood, in order to open the view from the Steine, then the area where people promenaded. If you look down from the Steine now, it is still possible to see why this idea was mooted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Chapels of Ease were built with the intention that the income from letting the pews should pay for the curate, the building and also make a profit for the owner. Thomas Read Kemp commissioned St George’s from Busby and Charles Barry designed St Andrews in Waterloo Street and St Peter’s as the chapel of Ease for St Nicholas’s Church. St Peters was the only church paid for by rates and loans from the government. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barry won the competition for the design for the Royal Sussex County Hospital, the first part of which was built in this period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New private or subscription gardens opened. Ireland’s Gardens with its cricket and stool ball grounds was the subject of several engravings. Now under Park Crescent, these gardens limped along into the 1830s and 1840s. Queen’s Park was also unsuccessful as gardens and a spa and the owners sought to add villas, a project which also failed to work in spite of quite heavy promotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where did all the capital that flowed into all of these projects come from? That is not easily established. But it was all the work of developers, some building a house or two or finding a builder to do it for them, others simply taking the risk of lending the money as mortgages. Many backers were friends and family, this much emerges from the bankruptcy records which give us an insight into who were the creditors. The loss of builders’ accounts, family accounts and correspondence such as any sources for the prolific Wilds, Amon and Amon Henry who were working in the town by 1818 greatly limits our understanding of who played major roles as developers and arbiters of style. The Wilds built anything they were asked to including the Phoenix Brewery for Richard Tamplin who opened it in 1822 just behind Richmond Terrace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this time, it was not the banks and other bodies we are used to today which funded building development. Planning control was slight and confined mainly to preventing buildings intruding into the road and similar issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rates were paid directly by ratepayers who also attended meetings where the management of the town by the Commissioners and of the poor by the Directors and Guardians was examined. Any extra expenditure was carefully examined. Many owners of houses had bought to let and so needed to keep the town prosperous to make their investment worthwhile. Local businessmen also had a keen interest in maintaining the flow of visitors coming in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ratepayers opted for gas lighting, more powers to widen streets, a proto police force and agreed that both the cliff top to the east of the town centre and a link road right along the front of the old town had to be built. Previously visitors and residents had to detour round North Street to get from the east to the west side of town. This had been the source of complaints and a reason why the western side of the town had been slow to develop. The ratepayers also relocated the Poor House to the north side of town, where Buckingham Place and Albert Road now stand. This was another major piece of organising and a financial pressure on the ratepayers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the great amount of building in Brighton and Brunswick Town in Hove, (together with the revamping of some of the houses in the surrounding villages which are now in the City,) by 1832 the whole area looked prosperous. Yet within the back streets the population was high and in due course, the failure to provide adequate sewerage, fresh water and street cleaning in these areas was to become a major issue which had a profound effect on the reputation of Brighton and Hove. But that is another story.	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© Sue Berry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 15:44:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20374 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Peter&#039;s Church, Preston, City of Brighton and Hove</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-peters-church-preston-city-brighton-and-hove</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; The work for the Victoria County History’s volume on the City of Brighton and Hove has revealed a considerable amount of repair and restoration work on most of the medieval churches between 1830 and 1914. Compared with some of the other churches, St Peters, the medieval parish church of the ancient parish of Preston was treated with a light hand. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tiny church, a well-known landmark on the northern end of Preston Park managed to be mentioned in The Times twice in sixty years. On both occasions the church roof caught fire, at the same end and because of the heating system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1830 some work on the church resulted in the rediscovery of frescos, which are probably from the C13th. The Rev. Charles Townshend ensured that both the Gentleman’s Magazine and the Archaeological Journal received a report from him and excellent drawings by William Twopenny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some time before February 1841, heating was installed in the church. In February 1841, the Sunday afternoon service was stopped by a fire in the roof, which had begun some time before it was spotted by two people passing by. Mainly railway workers who were then building the line from London to Brighton extinguished it. The railway men pulled tiles off the roof to douse the flames with water. Then, buckets of water from local ponds and wells were used to contain and then extinguish the fire. This task was largely complete when the fire engines appeared from Brighton. The event attracted spectators, some of whom stood there telling people what to do. The roof did not fall in, nor were the wall paintings damaged. A ‘bursting of the flue’ for the heating boiler probably caused the fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the late 1860s, more work was needed on the nave and the church required a new organ. The new organ, by Mannington was installed, just before Christmas 1873. Work on the restoration of the nave was completed in September 1874.This cost about £1,200. It was supervised by John Woodman (who designed Holy Trinity in Hove) and undertaken by Bruton. The old roof was replaced with oak beams and red tiles. More whitewash was removed from the walls. The author of an article about the work refers to the fashion for doing this and remarks that Mr. Ruskin would have approved. He notes that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘now the flint and stone walls are seen in their bare beauty, adding considerably to the effect of the church’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brickwork used to block up the lower parts of the windows was removed, the floor was tiled, the box pews shown in the print by Nibbs were replaced with seats (which seem to have been chairs, not benches) the pulpit replaced and a new reading desk provided. The south door, which had opened on to a footpath, was closed and a small vestry added.  A porch was added to the north door. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the work, ‘Clark’s Patent Multitubalar Heater’ which consisted of several long pipes under the floor heated by a furnace, also beneath the building, was installed. Vere and Ellen Bennet-Stanford then undertook some repair work to the chancel for which they employed Ewan Christian in 1877-78. The stencil decoration survived the fire mentioned below. The Vestry did consider enlarging the church in 1899 and commissioned a report from Sir Arthur Blomfield.  He was asked to consider two options, whether to enlarge St Peters or build a new church. The change in attitude towards extending churches and the resultant loss of old fabric appears to have played a major role in the rejection of the idea of extending St Peter’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blomfield designed St John the Evangelist in Knoyle Road to the north of St Peters which became the parish church in 1908.TheVestry then had to consider what to do with St Peters. Weddings and funerals were thought to be ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1906 the little church was so badly damaged that it was newsworthy. Postcards showing the damage were sold. The fire began below the organ and gallery and spread along the roof and into the tower. The fire did not damage the chancel but the interior was badly affected by smoke and by water. P.M.Johnston, a local architect, supervised the restoration by H.J.Penfold and Co. The new stained glass windows were by A.H.J.Westlake. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Declared redundant in 1997, the church is now cared for by the Churches Conservation Trust. The key can be borrowed from the Crown and Anchor pub. Local members of the CCT open the church at weekends. There are some very interesting memorials in the graveyard; some to people who died in Brighton whilst here to sea bathe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© Sue Berry&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2010 20:28:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20365 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Country Houses in the City of Brighton and Hove</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/country-houses-city-brighton-and-hove</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The City of Brighton and Hove has spread over a dozen ‘ancient’ parishes on the South Downs (Aldrington, Brighton, Falmer, Hangleton, Hove, Ovingdean, Patcham, Portslade, Preston, Rottingdean, Stanmer and West Blatchington). During the early 1500s, the village of Brighton began to expand and became a town, which by the early-mid 1600s numbered around 3,500, more residents than Lewes or Chichester. This was thanks to long distance fishing. The town’s residents packed into a tiny area beside the sea close to their net shops and capstans, which stood below the town’s low and crumbly cliff front. The surrounding parishes were entirely rural. They produced wheat and barley as cash crops and ran large flocks of sheep. This type of agriculture was most efficient on large farms some of which became the core of down land estates. Thus, the population of many of the villages and hamlets declined due to lack of work. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, between about 1530 and 1700 the South Downs was dotted with new country houses. Several are now within the bounds of the City.  By the 1500s, the Downs were popular for hunting and, as a means of travel between the east and west ends of Sussex. By 1700, country houses stood every few miles along them. The number of houses declined from the 1760s, when the larger estates began to expand by acquiring smaller ones or buying those with owners in debt. Then surplus country houses were either demolished or became farmhouses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before 1500 the only ‘country’ house used in this area by gentry was Benfield, a large hunting lodge used by the wealthy Covert family with estates in Slaugham to the north in the Sussex Weald (see picture). The Bellingham family built Hangleton Place (now a pub) in the mid 1500s in a courtyard style.  They sold to the Earl of Dorset in the 1590s. It ceased to be a country house although for a while a wing was reserved for the use of the owners as they travelled to Halnaker House in West Sussex.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard Shelley, a son of the owner of Michelgrove (a massive house that stood on the Downs in the parish of Clapham, West Sussex) bought land in Patcham. He probably built Patcham Place before 1552. Anthony Stapley (who signed the death warrant for Charles Ist) then bought the Patcham estate. The substantial older house is hidden behind a facade of black mathematical tiles. They disguise the extension of the older house between the 1760s and 1780 by the Paine family. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shirley family demolished the ancient house at Preston and built Preston Place in stone and timber in the 1590s. The Western family turned the house ninety degrees to face north south in the 1730s and in the 1760s added wings which can be seen most clearly now from the north side. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Pelham, one of the influential Pelhams of East Sussex whose best known relative was Thomas Pelham-Holes, the Duke of Newcastle commissioned Nicholas Dubois to design the austere 1720s Stanmer Place in sandstone from Lindfield and demolished the extensive living quarters of the old house.  The building accounts, which include the partial demolition of the older building survive. The work was completed by his brother who was nicknamed ‘Turkey’ Pelham because that is where he was sent to earn his keep by his father by trading.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1783, Nathaniel Kemp (the uncle of Thomas Read Kemp of Kemp Town) owned land in Ovingdean. Ovingdean Place built by him in 1792-3, the estimate for the work and some of the fitting out was 2653..10shillings. The facade is cream mathematical tiles. Meanwhile, Nathaniel and his first wife rented Preston Place which was sold by the Western family to William Stanford. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today the only house we have lost is Benfield. The rest survive, though Preston Place (now Preston Manor) was greatly altered and the service wing for Stanmer has been demolished. Hangleton Place is now the Hangleton Manor pub and much smaller than it was in the reign of Elizabeth Ist. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2010 20:18:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20361 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
