<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Person</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/person</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Gower&#039;s Iron Foundry, Hook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gowers-iron-foundry-hook</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former iron foundry in Hook run by the Gower family on the London Road, opposite the Old White Hart Inn started production in 1826. It has intermittently come within Odiham and Newnham parishes, but being located in the centre of the village it employed men and boys from Hook as well as Nately Scures and Newnham. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From their origins in Suffolk, the Gower family created a thriving business with award winning, innovative designs of seed drills, turnip and mangold cutters and other agricultural equipment having many distinguished customers across England. The foundry survived an arson attack in 1851 and was taken over in 1912 by the Hazell family who retained the Gower name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final closure date is unknown but in 2004 the site was sold and 74 houses built on the site named Foundry Close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed history and images of some of the equipment click on the link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2019 15:22:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25710 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dummer Water Supply</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-water-supply</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dummer village benefitted from a clean and reliable water supply due to its location on chalk with clear springs and also from the generosity and innovation of the lord of the manor living in Dummer House.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wells, standpipes and taps were situated in the two main streets for general use fed by a system of pipes leading from underground tanks. One well is of particular interest as it is protected by a Grade II Listed well house and contains a large treadwheel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately wells were dangerous places and there are two reports of children falling down the shafts and one of an adult who committed suicide by lowering himself into a well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed report on the Dummer water supply with photographs and maps, click the link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 15:53:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25651 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Housekeeper, Public Servant and Suffragist: The Productive Life of Mrs Isabella Raynbird (nee Webb) of Basingstoke 1837 -1925</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/housekeeper-public-servant-and-suffragist-productive-life-mrs-isabella-raynbird-nee-webb</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the time of her death, Isabella Raynbird was praised as somebody who ‘took a keen interest in everything for the good of the parish in which she lived, and, always ready to help any in need, she was greatly beloved by all’.* Such compliments were undoubtedly justified since she had lived a very full and productive life of 87 years. Born in Mapledurwell, her father was a prosperous farmer and Isabella undoubtedly experienced a relatively privileged upbringing. During her childhood and adolescence, she also became familiar with a farming way of life. Thus, unsurprisingly, for many years she was ‘housekeeper’ to Samuel Sparshatt, who farmed in the parish of Weston Patrick. Following his death in 1884 Isabella inherited not only his farming responsibilities but also his public service role of churchwarden and parish overseer, which she retained until her death. In 1890, at the age of 52, Isabella married widower Hugh Edward Raynbird, who was steward to Lord Bolton of Hackwood Park and head of the auctioneering firm, Raynbird and Son. Following her marriage she moved to Old Basing and from 1898 to 1922 served as one of the parish’s two poor law guardians, at a time when most members of boards of guardians were male. As a guardian, Isabella’s particular interests included the welfare and education of Workhouse children and staffing matters. She also attended a number of poor law conferences in Winchester and London. Throughout, she demonstrated her competence in what was, in part at least, a political role, thereby strengthening the case for the increased involvement of women in the public realm. This was also reflected in her support for those campaigning for women’s suffrage. She identified, however, with the moderate suffragists as opposed to the militant suffragettes. After some initial reluctance, in 1910 Isabella accepted the chairmanship/presidency of the Basingstoke and District Women’s Suffrage Society. In promoting the cause, she spoke at, and chaired, meetings and was a member of a deputation which met with the local MP in 1912 to secure his support. Some of Isabella’s intellectual interests, which she shared with her husband, were pursued through membership of the Hampshire Field Club and Archaeological Society. Looked at in the round, her life exemplified the increasing self-confidence of women as the 19th century gave way to the twentieth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite an extensive search, no photographs of Isabella have been found. Consequently it has been necessary to use an image of her husband to illustrate this item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For the source of the quotation, please see the PDF link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;September 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 17:29:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25648 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Census 1881</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-census-1881</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The whole of the 1881 census for Basingstoke parish has been transcribed by the New VCH Hampshire volunteers, based in the town. This information will be used for a detailed analysis of the population, households, age, occupations and migration etc. Because of the large number of inhabitants a complete spreadsheet is rather unwieldy so the data has been recorded on separate sheets, one for each of the 11 Districts enumerated. A link to the spreadsheet is below together with the enumerators’ descriptions of their walks around the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The total number of people counted on 3rd April 1881 is 6,769 which can be compared with 4,262 residents recorded in 1851, also on line together with comments and analysis:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-census-1851&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has to be remembered that this is just a snapshot of one night and many inhabitants may have been visitors, lodgers or even away from the town. Further work on the analysis of this data will be published in the future but it is interesting to note the inns (many of which are no longer in existence), employees in the clothing trade, iron foundry, breweries and railway but farmers and agricultural labourers are still evident presumably providing supplies to the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 13:08:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25588 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A Taunton vicar&#039;s letters from the front</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/taunton-vicars-letters-front</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A remarkable correspondence had begun by 1915 between parishioners and the vicar of Taunton St Mary Magdalene and other church officers. Although the originals are missing many were copied into the parish magazine or extracts were printed. There were letters about killed and missing men, appeals for food from prisoners of war and sometimes quite graphic accounts of life in the trenches. There were letters from France, Burma and naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 13:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25527 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>1939 National Register for Dummer</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/1939-national-register-dummer</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The National Register of 1939&lt;/strong&gt;[1] shows the occupations of Dummer residents (population 360 ) to consist largely of those associated with the land (landowner, farmer, smallholder, labourer, gardener, market gardener, forestry worker, gamekeeper, shepherd, cowman, poultryman, carter, sawyer and tractor driver), in trades related to an agricultural economy (carpenter, wheelwright, blacksmith, haulage contractor, brick layer) and in services supporting the community (grocer, shopkeeper, roundsman, newsagent, plumber/pipe layer, inn keeper, bus proprietor, petrol station owner and road labourer). Four men worked at an aeronautical instrument maker, one each as a telephone linesman engineer, a paper mill hand and a watchman at a motor works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professional and government officers included the rector, an undersecretary of state for agriculture, elementary school teacher, sub-postmistress, government officer (health) and a police constable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women were largely recorded as unpaid domestic workers in their own homes with the exceptions of a foster mother, a café assistant, a tailoress in a clothing factory, a school cleaner and a small number who were employed as domestic servants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Domestic service was limited to six properties: Dummer Grange where there was a butler/chauffeur, gardener, two domestic servants and a children’s nurse; Dummer House with a groom, chauffeur/gardener, cook, parlourmaid and housemaid; Clump House with a cook and housemaid; the Rectory, Dummer Down farm and Dummer Grange farm each with one domestic servant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The golf course established in 1928 gave rise to the new occupations of professional golfer, stewardess and groundsman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty children, twelve retirees, five invalids and four people of independent means are listed in the register but 81 entries are blanked out (listed as A.N.Other) and relate to residents who may still be alive in 2018 and whose identity is protected under the 100 year rule. The total number of children may be assumed to have been very much higher than shown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Dummer register was compiled by Gertrude Maud Weekes on 14 October 1939, a few weeks after the outbreak of World War 11. It identifies 15 ARP wardens, four Red Cross members, three Special Constables, a Billeting Office and a Land Army organiser as well as the first evacuee. Dubbed ‘The Wartime Domesday Book’ it is said to be the most comprehensive survey of the population of England and Wales ever undertaken. The National Registration Act, 1939 which ordered the register introduced compulsory identity cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Images of an original registration card are below as well as the transcription of the register.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1]  &lt;em&gt;1939 England &amp;amp; Wales Register&lt;/em&gt;, Hampshire, Basingstoke RD, EEDU, accessed via Ancestry.co.uk.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Sue Lane &amp;amp; Jennie Butler&lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2018 14:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25446 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Betty Dewberry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/betty-dewberry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twice married, long-lived and one of the wealthiest women in the parish of Bishops Hull, Betty Dewberry’s life spanned almost the whole 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2018 14:52:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25426 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Julia Blackmore dentist of Taunton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/julia-blackmore-dentist-taunton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long before any woman formally qualified in dentistry Taunton had a female dentist. Most dentists learnt on the job assisting a dentist or serving an apprenticeship. The first woman to be licensed to practice dentistry in England was Lilian Lindsey in 1895, over half a century after Julia Blackmore began work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 09:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25251 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mary Sweet and her Hotel</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mary-sweet-and-her-hotel</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mary Sweet was the creator of the western side of the present Castle Hotel, Taunton in the 1830s. She gave Taunton probably its first luxury hotel. She was one of many female hoteliers in Somerset in the mid 19th century creating high-class family hotels often out of traditional inns or as  in Mary’s case creating a new business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 12:31:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25246 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rectors of Dummer, Hampshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rectors-dummer-hampshire</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wills of the Rectors of Dummer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A church at Dummer is mentioned in the Domesday Survey[1] whilst the first known rector was Geoffrey, son of Ralph Dummer, who was parson of the church in 1198.[2] The roll of rectors who followed Geoffrey included other members of the Dummer family who were patrons of the living until the latter part of the 16th century. John de Donmere (Dummer), was presented to the church in 1304[3] and another John de Donmere became rector in 1334.[4] Richard Dummer presented Roger Golde to the church in 1524.[5] His will and inventory is the earliest probate material included in this item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During wars with France in the 14th century Nicholas Middleton, or Gervays, rector of Dummer from 1316-1330 ‘farmed’ (leased) two churches on the Isle of Wight, Arreton and Freshwater, the King having commanded the Bishop of Winchester to send foreign clergy living near the sea inland to avoid suspicion. Middleton took the income and would have been responsible for providing for the cure of souls.[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 18th century some well-known clergy served the parish. Charles Kinchin was rector from 1736-1742. A friend of John and Charles Wesley at Oxford he was one of the ‘Oxford Methodists’.[7] Two curates during his tenure at Dummer were George Whitefield who became a noted preacher on both sides of the Atlantic[8] and James Hervey, ‘one of the most widely read writers of the evangelical revival’.[9]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eight wills and two inventories survive for rectors who ministered in Dummer and died in or near the parish. They provide an insight into the lives and interests of the clergy involved, of particular note is their generosity in legacies to the poor of the parish and to the education of poor children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A glossary of unusual words appears below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wills:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1564  Roger Gold/Golde, will &amp;amp; inventory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1588  William White, will &amp;amp; inventory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1624  Richard Marritt/Merriott, inventory &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1656  William Wither, will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1723  Thomas Terry, will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1730  William Oades, will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1848  Michael Terry, will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1882  Sir William Dunbar, bart., will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;all&quot; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;em&gt;Domesday&lt;/em&gt;, Alecto, 108.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;[2] Feet of Fines Hants, East. 28 Eliz.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[3] &lt;em&gt;Reg. Pontissara&lt;/em&gt;, 177.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[4] &lt;em&gt;Reg. Stratford&lt;/em&gt; i, 1258.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[5] Reg. Fox v, 98.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;em&gt;Reg, Stratford &lt;/em&gt;ii, 620/1.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[7] Isabel Rivers, ‘Hervey, James (1714-1758)’, ODNB (Oxford, 2014) article 13113. accessed 6 Aug&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;   2017.      &lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[8] Boyd Stanley Schlenther, ‘Whitefield, George (1714–1770)’, ODNB (Oxford, 2004) article 29281,     &lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;   accessed 6 Aug 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
	
	
		&lt;p&gt;[9] Isabel Rivers, ‘Hervey, James (1714-1758)’, ODNB (Oxford, 2014) article 13113. accessed 6 Aug                      &lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;   2017.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
	

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 15:33:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25203 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
