<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Bristol</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/bristol</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>29 Queen Square</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/29-queen-square</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;English Heritage now have their regional headquarters at number 29 and it is the best preserved of the original buildings in the square. This is illustrated by its forecourt gates and railings and internal panelling and staircase. The house was built in 1709 for Alderman Nathanial Day who part owned a number of slave ships and who later became Bristol&#039;s Mayor in 1737. Day petitioned against a proposed tax on slaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By mid century, number 29 was the home of Henry Bright, a prominent Merchant Venturer and slave trader. On his death in 1771 he left &quot;an annuity of £10 per annum, chargeable on the house where I now dwell, to my black servant, Bristol&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 10:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20217 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Names, People and Places</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/names-people-and-places</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many Bristolians had toponymic surnames in the 13th and 14th centuries, that is, names that denote a place or region. There were 33 individuals bearing surnames relating to places in northern France or the Netherlands, and 27 and 10 relating respectively to Welsh and Irish origins. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This trend is mainly due to trade ties between the regions. However, the scarcity of Celtic names among this group is noteworthy. With few exceptions, there are no obviously Gaelic or Welsh names. While such appellations as Hiberniensis (Irishman) or &#039;le Walse&#039; may conceal a Gaelic or Welsh identity, most of the bearers of these surnames have the usual Anglo-Norman Christian names, such as John, William or Thomas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12698 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Bristol Italians</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bristol-italians</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometime in the 1800s, a small number of largely impoverished Italians, some from the mountainous regions of Northern Italy (mainly around Tuscany), made their way to England on foot. A few seem to have come to Bristol earning a living as street musicians and street traders with an increasing number from Southern Italy by the century’s end. Their distinctive traditional costumes made a vivid impression on the locals, as this illustration of Bristol’s cathedral choirmaster dating from later in the century demonstrates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12696 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Black Victorians</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/black-victorians</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;While numerically insignificant, the existence of Black Bristolians is important to document, as they bridge the gap between what we know about the black presence in the city when it was a slaving port and when it was the destination of 20th-century migrants from the Caribbean and West Africa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although a number of visiting African-American anti-slavery campaigners such as Frederick Douglass and Ellen Crafts were lionised when they visited the city and Black entertainers were also accorded a genuinely warm, if patronising, welcome, those who lived permanently in Bristol seem generally to have been poor and of low status.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12695 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bristol&#039;s 18th-century Jewish community</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bristols-18th-century-jewish-community</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1766 Bishop Newton recorded a total of 42 Jews in the city, 40 of whom lived in Temple. Whilst the synagogue provided the focus for most of the community, there were others who must have assimilated into society at large. However, very few Jews seem to have formally converted to the Church of England, if the baptismal records are trustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the law, descendants of any mixed faith marriage would not be considered Jews.  Records indicate, however, exceptions were made and family names were not reliable means to trace families, thus making the task of tracing Jewish heritage in Bristol difficult. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12694 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Apprentices</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/apprentices</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the period 1532 to 1552 a total of 3,139 apprentices were registered, of whom 766 came from within Bristol, and 456 from Wales. Welsh apprentices therefore constituted 14.5 per cent overall, but 19.2 per cent of non-Bristolians. A large number of Welsh masters took on Welsh apprentices; these examples indicate some form of prior connection, either familial or commercial. In general, however, the lack of an exact correlation between the family and ethnic background of the majority of masters and apprentices strongly suggests that there was no general desire for Welsh youngsters to be apprenticed within an ex-patriot community: there was no Welsh ghetto in early-modern Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, many youngsters in hopes for an apprenticeship come from the smaller towns of South Wales.  Carmarthenshire contained one of the three largest towns in Wales, yet only 26 came to Bristol.  However, 84 came from Pembrokeshire in the far west.  Perhaps this is due to the good communications between Pembrokeshire and Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12693 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Adam of Bristol</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/adam-bristol</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The earliest of the European ritual child murder, or bloodguilt, accusations was raised at Norwich in 1144, where the Jewry was accused of crucifying the 12-year-old William. There is no evidence that this actually happened, yet the Gloucester story may have influenced Bristol’s own crucifixion legend. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story goes that Adam, young son of William the Welshman, resident of St Mary Redcliffe parish, is seduced into entering the house of Samuel the Jew by the offer of apples and then crucified. The story was probably composed in Bristol, since it displays detailed knowledge of local features. The story conveys interaction between Jews and Christians, which was a fear of the church at that time.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12692 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Oral history - collecting reflections</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/oral-history-collecting-reflections</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oral testimony is a means of identifying issues or events that might otherwise go undocumented.  Those who come to this country to seek a new life bring with them their existing values and experiences.  A dilemma which oral history poses has to do with the way testimony is gathered and the status of the knowledge it yields. Although oral testimony cannot always be depended upon for factual accuracy, it is a good way of getting some insights into the way people view the world, how they structure their lives and how they regard others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12663 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The 1851 Census and immigration</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/1851-census-and-immigration</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The 1851 census can help us to identify parishes inhabited by first-generation immigrants. In 1851, nearly half of Bristol&#039;s 137,000 residents, some 45 per cent, are estimated to have come from outside the city boundaries. Even if they only came from the neighbouring county, historians class them as immigrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The census returns tell us their place of birth and enables us to see that, as in the late 20th century, immigrants to Bristol were often more widely distributed throughout the city than popularly supposed.  Outside the old city area of Bristol, new suburbs like Bedminster were rapidly springing into existence. Still partly rural, its largely working-class population is noticeably less ethnically diverse than either Bristol as a whole or the quayside parishes of the old city.  The 1851 census affords us a valuable snapshot of where people were born, where in the city they settled, with whom they lived and, to some extent, what they did for a living.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12662 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Tax returns and aliens in the 16th Century</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/tax-returns-and-aliens-16th-century</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surviving tax returns for Bristol identify resident alien (foreign) taxpayers for the 1520s, 1540s, and the period from 1571 to 1590. They give the street or ward in which the taxpayer lived.  In this case, it is interesting how few aliens were assessed and that their numbers had not increased significantly since the preceding century. Nor was there an alien ghetto: the small size of Bristol&#039;s alien community hardly allowed for the formation of a &#039;foreign quarter&#039; in any case. The origins of these aliens offer few surprises. Most are French (including Bretons) or Dutch (including Flemings and Germans).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12661 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
