<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Military</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/military</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Norton Fitwarren War memorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/norton-fitwarren-war-memorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Norton Fitwarren has an unusual war memorial in the form of the gate pillars outside the village club house, now the village hall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jul 2018 14:09:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25506 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Thornycroft in Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/thornycroft-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thornycroft, the commercial vehicle manufacturer, was the biggest employer in Basingstoke for much of the 20th century. Therefore the fluctuations in its fortunes had a considerable impact on the economy of the town. There was a dramatic drop in trade in the early 1920s when 700 men were discharged and the weekly wage bill fell from just under £8,000 to a little over £4,000. Employment peaked during the two world wars when Thornycroft diversified into munitions work and over 30 per cent of its workforce were women. During the Second World War Thornycroft was employing 2,500 people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a more detailed history see the link below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 07:14:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25388 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Basing (Basing) Probate Material 1521 to 1700</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1521-1700</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;About half of the parish of Old Basing lies on chalk, with the sands and gravels of the Reading beds running through the centre of the village from NW to SE, separating the chalk uplands (up to 100m OD) in the south from the low-lying London clays (c.60m OD). The river Loddon flows from the chalk just west of Basingstoke through the village towards Reading, the River Lyde, another eventual tributary of the Thames, touches the parish on the south and east. Petty’s Brook, another tributary, forms part of the boundary. The variety of soils has had an impact on the agricultural richness of the parish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The parish is not heavily wooded, most of the woodland being on the clay soils, or plantations within Hackwood Park in the south. The river Loddon has determined the form of the village which grew up mainly on the south bank above the flood plain between the two best crossing points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basing parish had four manors: Basing, Byfleet, Hackwood and Lychpit. One of the earliest references to the place-name is the Battle of Basing in the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle in 871 when Alfred (before he became king) was defeated by the Danes. In Domesday, it formed part of the holding of Hugh de Port, the family who retained lordship living in Basing for a long time. It passed to the Paulet family and William Paulet in the 16th century rose to great heights in the government and rebuilt Basing House so that it became the grandest private residence in the land, visited by all the Tudor monarchs. In the 17th century it was famous for the stalwart defence of the house for King Charles during the civil wars by the fifth Marquis John Paulet. It was finally taken by Oliver Cromwell in October 1645 and was completely destroyed by Act of Parliament. It is said that houses in the village were built using bricks from Basing House. In the 18th century, the main Hampshire seat of the family, by then Dukes of Bolton, moved across the park to Hackwood House, which is not in Basing parish. The estate remained an entity until the mid 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wills and inventories survive for Old Basing in Hampshire Record Office (HRO) and The National Archives (TNA). These are being transcribed by the Wills Group of the New Victoria County of Hampshire project based in Basingstoke and will be published in the near future. These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by HRO and TNA.  Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Old Basing is described as Basing being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;glossary&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words and links to the documents are below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1521-40&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1521-40&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1541-60&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1541-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1561-1580&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1561-80&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-basing-probate-material-1581-1600&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1581-1600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-basing-probate-material-1601-1620&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Old Basing Probate Material 1601-20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 10:36:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24989 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Amesbury Airfield</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/amesbury-airfield</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stonehenge airfield landing ground between the Shrewton &amp;amp; Exeter roads west of Stonehenge was opened in 1917 for training bomber pilots. Hangers and other buildings were erected north &amp;amp; south of the Exeter road. The airfield was closed in 1920, some of the buildings were used for farming and all had been demolished by the 1930’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blackcross down south east of the town Boscombe Down (initially red house farm) airfield was opened in 1917 for training pilots. Buildings were erected by 1918 extended in 1919 but the airfield was closed in 1920. Reopened in 1930 and was used mostly by bomber squadrons until 1939 when the aeroplane &amp;amp; armament experimental moved there. The evaluation establishment was still at Boscombe down in 1992, main work was to test aeroplanes &amp;amp; weapons. The airfield was greatly expanded after WWII new buildings were erected in the 1950’s. By 1937 9 houses in Allington way and had been erected for commissioned officers, 4 in main road for warrant officers and 33 in lamber road and main road for airmen. After WWII several housing estates were built on the west side of the airfield.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:16:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21405 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Trowbridge Barracks</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/trowbridge-barracks</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trowbridge Barracks was erected in Bradley Road in 1794 by contractor John Scobell. A troop of cavalry was stationed in building, which housed 4 officers, 58 soldiers of other ranks, 63 horses and had hospital accommodation for 10. The barracks was abandoned after the close of the Napoleonic Wars in 1815. Troops returned to Trowbridge in 1826 and were billeted in the town’s inns. This was unpopular and in 1837 a petition demanded that neighbouring towns should share the cost. Six-monthly quartering’s in Trowbridge, Bradford upon Avon and Frome were introduced in 1838. Because of the Chartist disturbances 1838-9, the Government decided to provide proper military quarters and bought back the barracks in 1839. From the late 19th century the barracks housed the Royal Artillery.  By 1903 the barracks could hold 150 men; it was extended in the 2nd World War but was later demolished and replaced with housing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Boer Wars occurred in South Africa and took place between the British and the descendants of the Dutch settlers. The first war dates from 1880 -1 while the second dates 1899-1902. The Wars resulted in a British victory as the Boer Republics were brought to an end in the peace settlement. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 10:41:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21399 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Castle</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-castle</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; The wooden castle was built by William the conqueror as his invasion force came to the West Country in 1086. It later became to be strengthened by Roger, bishop of Salisbury in 1100 and was later rebuilt in stone. The history of the structure of the castle is interesting and the details of its strengthening and rebuilding throughout the centuries show us that the castle was highly valued by both monarchs and their officials and powerful locals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Important individuals feature in the castles history the first being Agelric who was the bishop of the South Saxons. He was held hostage in the castle in 1070 after William came to successfully conquer the West Country in 1068. The royal history of the castle does not finish here as the castle became a royal residence and the royal court often visited. Savernake forest and the neighbouring wood of Aldbourne chase were favourite royal hunting grounds. Notable figures linked to the castle are as follows. John of Gaunt, son of Edward III had a hunting lodge in the middle of the chase. Henry I spent Easter there in 1110. Henry III was married there and in 1245 his mother died there. On his death the castle became part of the dowry of his widow, Queen Eleanor and on her death was conferred by Edward I on his own Queen. Edward II bestowed it on his favourite Hugh Le Despencer in 1308; on his fall his wife Queen Isabel obtained it. In the reign of Edward III the castle was held by various wardens for the King’s sister. Richard II granted it to Sir William Scrope – on his execution in 1399 it reverted back to the crown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The castle was allowed to fall into ruin after the Wars of the Roses. The wise policy of Henry VII strengthened the crown so great castles were no longer needed to keep the peace. Old feudal fortresses became valueless, as explosives were now in use and castles were defenceless against gunpowder. Edward VI, last royal owner of the castle, passed it on to the Seymour family as this was his mother’s line. Today the site of the castle belongs to Marlborough College.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 11:29:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21311 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fovant Cap Badges</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fovant-cap-badges</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During World War I, military units were based throughout Salisbury Plain for training before deployment to the front. Several regiments were based in Fovant and the neighbouring parishes, and soldiers of these regiments carved the designs from their regimental cap badges into the sides of the local chalk downs. Covered over during World War II, these badges were maintained and cared for by the local communities and the Old Comrades Association. A Fovant Badges Society was created in 1961.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven cap badges can be seen on Fovant Down today: 6th Battallion, City of London Regiment; the Australian Imperial Force Badge; the Devonshire Regiment; the London Rifle Brigade; the Post Office Rifles; the Royal Corps of Signals; the Royal Wiltshire Yeomanry; and the Wiltshire Regiment. Another two, those of the 7th Battalion, City of London Regiment and the Royal Warwickshire Regiment, have been allowed to grow over. There was also an emblem of the YMCA, which has also been allowed to grow over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2013 13:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21275 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Drill Hall, Sarum Hill, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/drill-hall-sarum-hill-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This building at the top of Sarum Hill, Basingstoke, was erected in July 1883 by Colonel John May of May’s Brewery as a Drill Hall for K Company, 1st Hants Rifle Volunteers. It was the largest hall in town, 100 ft deep by 50 ft wide at the front, with a capacity of 250 dancing couples. In 1884 Colonel May also built the Masonic Hall next door, which had communicating doors to the Drill Hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colonel May allowed the hall to be used for many public meetings, entertainments and dinners and for events like a grand “Reformation Times bazaar” under the auspices of London Street Congregational Church in 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1925 the theatrical entrepreneur Edwin George Casey opened the hall as the Pavilion dance hall and in 1937 he converted it to become the Plaza Theatre (a cinema).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this closed in 1955 it was taken over as the Co-operative Furnishing Store and later the Masonic Hall was incorporated into the store for hardware, both continuing in use until 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both buildings were pulled down when there were plans to make a roundabout, which never happened. The new building there is now the offices of Sovereign Kingfisher, who retained the foundation stone of the Masonic Hall in a garden feature.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 02 Apr 2012 10:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20812 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Americans at Codford</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/americans-codford</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although (as in the First World War) many regiments of British Servicemen were garrisoned at Codford, during the Second World War they were also joined in 1943 by servicemen from the American Third Armoured Brigade. New camps were built nearby the old First World War camps. The Americans were stationed at A Camp and and B Camp and Cherry Orchard Camp just north of the High Street.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12658 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Codford&#039;s Second World War Landscape</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/codfords-second-world-war-landscape</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When war returned in 1939 Codford was again chosen as a military garrison for many regiments from the British armed forces who were joined in 1943 by servicemen from the American Third Armoured Brigade. Camps were built close to or alongside the sites of their First World War predecessors, north of St Peter&#039;s and near St Mary’s church, with Hindon Lane, which links Codford and Stockton, acquisitioned by the military.   Chitterne Road, which was heavily used during the First World War when army camps were built to the east of it, was widened in 1942 and 1943, with washing bays and turning places for the up to 200 tanks that were parked along it. The many heavy armoured vehicles which used or crossed the road damaged its surface and deposited hazardous quantities of mud along it.   Fewer postcards depicting Codford survive from the Second World War, although several structures from the period can still be found in the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12654 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
