<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/overton</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Overton Markets and Fairs</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/overton-markets-and-fairs</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article traces the history of the fairs and markets from 1218 to the present day, including the commodities traded, how the markets were regulated and the revenues due to the Bishop of Winchester as lord of the manor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 19th century, the annual sheep fair was moved from the main street to a more convenient field and the local gentry formed an ‘Overton Sheep Fair Society’ with prizes for the best entries and a sumptuous dinner. Both initiatives resulted in a substantial increase in business with up to 100,000 animals changing hands. As with all the country fairs, however, the coming of the railways eventually resulted in its demise, as the sellers moved their sheep by rail to the major cities where prices were higher. The associated pleasure fair was revived in 2000. It is held every four years and attracts thousands of visitors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 12:56:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25353 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Portals Paper Mills, 1718-1995: Papermakers to the Bank of England</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/portals-paper-mills-1718-1995-papermakers-bank-england</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Portals paper mills have had a profound economic and social effect on Overton parish. In the south of England, it is most unusual to find a single dominant industrial employer over such a long period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Portal, a Huguenot refugee from France, was awarded the contract to make hard-wearing banknote paper for the Bank of England in 1724. The company grew steadily, eventually outgrowing the limited space at Laverstoke Mill, 1km beyond the boundary of Overton parish, and a new factory was built at Overton Station in 1924. Portals became the largest security paper company in the world, employing about 1,550 people in the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 18:14:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25258 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Settlement and buildings in Overton, Hampshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/settlement-and-buildings-overton-hampshire</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;These articles trace the history of the settlement from the earliest times to the present day, including the new town established by the bishops of Winchester in 1218, the historic hamlets along the River Test at Southington, Quidhampton and Polhampton and the settlement at Northington, deserted in the 15th century. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building styles and materials in Overton Conservation Area are described along with selected listed and non-listed buildings which illustrate the character of the settlement. An account is given of the continual process of demolition, rebuilding and in-filing as well as expansion beyond the historic core of the village in the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2018 16:10:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25254 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Boundaries, landscape and communications of Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/boundaries-landscape-and-communications-overton-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article describes how the Anglo-Saxon manor of Overton included the valley of the River Test for habitation, pasture and mills as well as chalk downland for arable crops, woodland and heath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routes through the parish included the Harrow Way, a Neolithic era track, a Roman road on the northern boundary, the main east-west route, which became the preferred coach road from London to Exeter, and a north- south route connecting Winchester and Newbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach traffic declined almost immediately after the opening of the London to Southampton railway and Micheldever Station in 1840. Overton Station, on the line from London to Exeter, opened in 1854.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article traces how people travelled, on foot, by bicycle, bus and car in succeeding generations and continues with a summary of communication by post, telegraph and telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several estimates of the population of Overton prior to the first census are reviewed. In 1801, the population of the parish was 1,130 and there were 230 houses.  The population grew rapidly until 1841 when it began to decline by outward migration which coincided with loss of agricultural jobs and the closure of the silk mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1901, the population had been restored to the 1841 level with increasing industrial employment at Portals paper mills. It has risen in every decade since, with increasing numbers of people commuting to work outside the parish. The population was 4,315 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the fall in average household size, the numbers of houses doubled between 1911 and 1951, doubled again by 1991 and stood at 1,863 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCH Overton Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 15:37:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25226 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Boundaries, landscape and communications of Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/boundaries-landscape-and-communications-overton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article describes how the Anglo-Saxon manor of Overton included the valley of the River Test for habitation, pasture and mills as well as chalk downland for arable crops, woodland and heath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routes through the parish included the Harrow Way, a Neolithic era track, a Roman road on the northern boundary, the main east-west route, which became the preferred coach road from London to Exeter, and a north- south route connecting Winchester and Newbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach traffic declined almost immediately after the opening of the London to Southampton railway and Micheldever Station in 1840. Overton Station, on the line from London to Exeter, opened in 1854.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article traces how people travelled, on foot, by bicycle, bus and car in succeeding generations and continues with a summary of communication by post, telegraph and telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several estimates of the population of Overton prior to the first census are reviewed. In 1801, the population of the parish was 1,130 and there were 230 houses.  The population grew rapidly until 1841 when it began to decline by outward migration which coincided with loss of agricultural jobs and the closure of the silk mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1901, the population had been restored to the 1841 level with increasing industrial employment at Portals paper mills. It has risen in every decade since, with increasing numbers of people commuting to work outside the parish. The population was 4,315 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the fall in average household size, the numbers of houses doubled between 1911 and 1951, doubled again by 1991 and stood at 1,863 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCH Overton Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 15:37:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25225 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Overton Silk Mill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/overton-silk-mill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overton Silk Mill was built on the river Test in 1769 and was the first water- powered industrial silk mill to be built in the south of England, converting imported raw silk into thread for the silk weavers of Spitalfields in London. About 200 women and child apprentices were employed, the children starting work at about the age of six. In 1797 the hours were from 6 o’clock in the morning to 7 or 8 o’clock at night for six days of the week. The fortunes of the mill fluctuated with changes of fashion and variations in import and export tariffs during and after the wars with France. By 1848, it was no longer profitable and was completely demolished to pay creditors. By this time the workforce consisted predominantly of young women, many of whom found alternative work at the silk mill in Whitchurch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 19 Nov 2017 18:06:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25217 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Overton Poor Law to 1848</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/overton-poor-law-1848</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1686, the Overton vestry authorised a poor-house in the parish, which continued until the rapidly rising costs of poor relief resulted in a new House of Industry which opened in about 1800. The inmates made sacking but the income did not result in any reduction in the poor rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating under Gilbert’s Act of 1782, the overseers also paid outdoor relief for food, clothes and shoes, widows’ pensions, arrears of rent, money for those who were ill and could not work, for funerals and graves, travel to the county hospital and relief for poor travellers on the road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1834, the Poor Law Amendment Act abolished outdoor relief and deterred the able-bodied from seeking relief in workhouses. The Overton poor rates dropped by half.  The Overton House of Industry became part of the Whitchurch Union and was closed in 1848.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2017 19:26:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25189 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
