<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Beaumont</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/beaumont</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Beaumont Quay Lime Kiln</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/beaumont-quay-lime-kiln</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beaumont Quay and similar landing places along the Essex coast were chiefly used for the export of local agricultural produce to London. However, the barges also brought back return cargoes and these were mainly building materials (such as stone, flint or bricks) or soil improvers such as manure and chalk (limestone). The manure was collected in London (both from the capital’s horses and human ‘night soil’) and the chalk on the return journey from quarries along the Thames estuary in both Essex and Kent. The main reason that farmers wanted to apply chalk was to correct high levels of acidity in the soil and therefore improve the uptake of major plant nutrients such as nitrogen and to maximise crop yields. It could also provide a source of calcium and magnesium for growing plants. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the chalk could simply be spread on the farmland it was more efficient burn the chalk at high temperature in a kiln which led to the release of carbon dioxide and created a product called ‘quicklime’. When the ‘quicklime’ was mixed with water (a process known as ‘slaking’) it was turned into a stable powder form of lime which could then be spread on the land. The use of lime for agricultural purposes was described in Sir Anthony Fitzherbert&amp;#039;s Boke of Husbandrye, in 1523, but these activities became increasingly important during the age of agricultural improvement in the 18th and 19th centuries. There was also demand for lime for use in lime mortars in the building industry in the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lime kilns were therefore a natural addition to the facilities alongside many of the small Essex quays, wharves and landing places. Although many were built only a few have survived, and the kiln at Beaumont Quay is built to an East Anglian (mixed-feed) design which is fairly rare. It is a circular red brick building within an earthen mound, and is some 2.5 metres high and about 13 metres in diameter. From the main entrance you can access a barrel-vaulted circulation passage around a central combustion chamber. On the other side of the mound another smaller rectangular opening was probably a ventilator that allowed the operators to regulate the draught to the kiln. The central combustion chamber had an opening for lighting the kiln, two others for raking out the lime and ash. The kiln was fired with wood and coal, and alternative layers of fuel and chalk would be added from outside via the opening at the top of the kiln. The chalk would turn to lime at about 900° C and fall to the bottom of the kiln where it could be raked out. The kiln was probably in continuous use, and the quay would have large heaps of chalk and coal ready for processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;br /&gt;
J. Moore, ‘Beaumont Quay’, Colchester Archaeological Group Bulletin, 54 (2014), pp. 8–12.&lt;br /&gt;
English Heritage Listing: Beaumont Quay, Hamford Water: a 19th century quay and lime kiln. List entry Number: 1020688 (See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://list.historicengland.org.uk/&quot;&gt;http://list.historicengland.org.uk/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 18:59:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23922 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Beaumont Quay</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/beaumont-quay</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The historic site known as Beaumont Quay is an important survival showing the nature of the small quays and wharves that were once very common and busy along the Essex coast. It is located right at the end of the tidal Landermere Creek, on the northern bank, which provided access for boats to Hamford Water and then to the North sea. The site is now owned by Essex County Council and is a scheduled ancient monument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological material has revealed settlement in this area in the Iron-Age, Roman and early medieval periods, as well as evidence for salt-making. There was probably also a landing place or wharf which served the large and valuable medieval manor of Beaumont Hall. In the Middle Age the overlords of the manor were the de Vere family, the earls of Oxford, while the local lords (manorial tenants) were the Berners family. In 1577 a list of all the ports, havens, creeks and landing places on the Essex coast recorded a creek, three landing places and four customs deputies at Thorpe-le-Soken and Beaumont. One of those landling places is likely to have been near Beaumont Quay and another one at Landermere Wharf in Thorpe. Such landing places were used to export agricultural produce such as corn, hay, and cheese from local farms like Beaumont Hall to London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 16th century the manor passed to the crown, and in 1551 King Edward VI granted it to Sir Thomas Darcy of St Osyth. Ownership of the estate then descended in the Darcy family, who became the earls Rivers, until it passed, probably by sale, to Francis North, 2nd Baron Guildford (d. 1729). Shortly before he died Francis sold the estate and the quay to the governors of Guy&#039;s Hosptal, London. The governors were investing heavily in Essex property having been left the enormous sum of £220,000 (about £28 million in today&#039;s money) by Thomas Guy as an endowment for their institution. In 1727 they commissioned a survey of Beaumont Hall prior to their purchase, which not only recommended it as a very good buy, but noted that there were two &quot;very convenient landing places for bringing chalk rubbish from Kent and carrying of corn or any other thing off to London&quot;. This neatly describes the two-way traffic to London, with corn being taken to market and soil improvers being brought back as the return cargo - in this case chalk but just as often horse manure and &#039;night soil&#039;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1727 survey had also noted that the two landing places could only be used at very high tides, probably because the natural water channel of the Creek was rather shallow and emptied too quickly on the ebb. By the early 19th century agricultural production and yields had improved and the governors decided to invest in creating a more efficient quay. In 1831 London bridge was demolished and replaced, and Thomas Guy&#039;s Hospital acquired some of the old stone blocks which it transported to Beaumont to build a new quay in the following year. The quay was about 80 metres long, partly of stone (unmortared) and partly of timber. In addition, the governors paid for the digging of a new channel or canal called Beaumont Cut, two metres deep and about 1km long which linked the quay to deeper water in Hamford Water. A basin at the quay allowed barges or other vessels to turn around, and in 1848 it was described as navigable for vessels up to 70 tons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heyday of the quay was in the mid and later 19th century, when it saw a busy trade. There were buildings at the quay by 1838, probably including an arcaded brick warehouse that survived until the later 20th century. The tenant of Beaumont Hall, Mr Sewell, also built a kiln besides the quay, for the production of lime for agricultural purposes. The kiln ceased production in the mid 1920s, and the last trading barge used the quay in the 1930s. A 42-ton barge called the &lt;em&gt;Rose&lt;/em&gt;, built in 1880, was towed to the basin in the early 1960s for conversion to a house boat, but later became derelict and damaged in a fire. Its wreck is still visible, slowly subsiding into the mud. Some of the buildings at the quay were demolished soon afterwards, but one store house has survived as does the kiln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Moore, &#039;Beaumont Quay&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Colchester Archaeological Group Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, 54 (2014), pp.8-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Buckley, &#039;Lost and Found: The Archaeology of the Essex Coast&#039;, in A. Aberg and C. Lewis (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Rising Tide. Archaeology and Coastal Landscapes &lt;/em&gt;(Oxbow Books, 2000), pp. 5-16 (pp.10-11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. White&#039;s, &lt;em&gt;History, Gazetteer and Directory of the County of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1848).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office, D/DGh E1. Survey, 1727.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, SP12/117 (31), Oct. 1577. John Lord Darcy of Chiche and others. List of all ports, havens, creeks and landing places and list of deputies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map 1&quot; (1838 edition).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 14:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23907 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
