<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Hill Deverill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/hill-deverill</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Deverill valley road</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/deverill-valley-road</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the 1850s, the road from Longbridge Deverill along the Deverill valley only went as far as the manor house of Hill Deverill. Beyond that, tracks ran south on either side of the river, and the river bed itself was also used at times. During the winter, when the river ran higher, the main route for heavy traffic was along a track that ran over Badbury Hill and on towards Warminster; it survives today as a bridleway. The modern road from Longbridge Deverill through Hill Deverill to Brixton Deverill was completed with public subscription in 1855.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 00:46:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20578 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cold Kitchen Hill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cold-kitchen-hill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cold Kitchen Hill stands at the centre of the Deverill valley. This modern place name is derived from the Celtic &lt;em&gt;Col Cruachen&lt;/em&gt;, the &#039;Hill of the Wizard&#039;.  The rich array of archaeological finds, including building materials, painted wall plaster, human bone, coins, jewellery and votive objects suggests a great temple complex stood there within a rectangular enclosure. This was in use from late Prehistory to the Romano-British period. A fine bronze figurine of Mercury, c. 80 mm x 23 mm across the shoulders, was found nearby.  The evidence suggests that Cold Kitchen Hill was the focal point of early settlement in the Deverill valley.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 16:32:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20574 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Hill Deverill Manor House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/hill-deverill-manor-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rebuilt and much altered &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;. 1700, Hill Deverill manor house is a two-storey stone house of medieval origins. The house is on a site that may previously have been occupied by a water mill. It was rebuilt by the Coker family, who had acquired the manor in the late 17th century through marriage. There were extensive alterations to the manor house and its site for use as a tenant farm in the 18th and 19th centuries, and had been divided into two dwellings by 1894. The house continued to be occupied by farmers until 1940, when it was converted to a private residence. Attached to the house is a 14-bay barn of a later date, into which modern owners have expanded the house.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The house is part of a much larger complex, across the river from the parish church and main road. There were also numerous outhouses, stables, orchards, a dovecote and fishponds. Chantry Cottage, opposite the manor house, is all that remains of an earlier manor house built for the Ludlow family. The arms of John Ludlow and his wife Phillippa Bulstrode indicate that it was built sometime between 1488 and 1519. When the current manor house was renovated for the Cokers &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;. 1700, the mill leat and other water features were redesigned as moated gardens fed by the river. During the later 19th century, the fishponds were filled in and many of the outhouses were pulled down, but an ornamental lake has been restored in modern times.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 09:30:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20570 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
