<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Marlborough</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/marlborough</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Inns</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-inns</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prosperity came from the town’s many inns catering for travellers on the main London to Bristol road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chief among them from 1456 to 1730 was the Hart (Old Hart) on the north side of the High Street. Coach trade exploded in the early 18th century with the development of Bath and to a lesser extent Marlborough itself. Principal inns on the south side were the Angel, the Black Swan and the Duke’s Arms (pre 1843 known as the Ailesbury arms). On the north side there was the Castle &amp;amp; Ball. In 1797 coaches ran daily from the Duke’s Arms and the Black Swan to London and Bath, three each way from the Castle daily and one each way from the Castle &amp;amp; Ball on Mondays, Wednesdays and Fridays. Nightly mail coaches ran to London and daily coaches to Exeter. There was a daily service in 1833 from the principal inns to London, Bath, Bristol, Cheltenham, Frome and Reading. Isambard Kingdom Brunel’s Great Western Railway line from London – Bristol was opened in 1841 and damaged the coaching trade. In 1844 only three coaches a day ran to London, and one to Bath and Bristol.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 12:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21317 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Industry </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marlborough’s position on the main London to Bristol road made it a centre of trade and industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Middle Ages burel, a coarse woollen cloth was manufactured as clothing for the poor and the cloth industry continued to the 19th century. A major tanning industry also began in the Middle Ages, processing sheepskins and cow hides from animals reared in Savernake Forest. From the 1600s hemp, or flax, was processed and made into rope, sacking and sailcloth until the 1960s. Pin making also took place from the 16th to the 18th centuries and luxuries – clay pipes, bone lace and clocks were manufactured for transport to urban markets. Cheese was also made for the London market and seven cheese factories were recorded in 1797 and 1844. Despite less demand from London from 1680 onwards, Marlborough remained a centre for the sale of cheese until at least 1907.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 12:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21316 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Common </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-common</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marlborough common exists at the heart of the settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1194 the burgesses of Marlborough paid 10s yearly to rent a pasture from the King, who was lord of the borough. In King John’s reign the burgesses gave up that pasture in exchange for Marlborough Common, for which they paid the same rent. Byelaws passed in 1577 decreed that each burgess could keep no more than two cows or bullocks there; and they were to pay 8d yearly to the mayor for each animal. The mayor paid the costs of keeping a common bull until 1836 when the costs were met from the borough fund. In 1836 rights of pasturage on Marlborough Common were extended to all the inhabitants of Marlborough. The bull could be hired for 8d to service a commoner’s cattle until the custom ceased in 1904.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The common was levelled and reseeded in 1958, and is now used chiefly for grazing and recreation.           &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 12:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21315 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Market </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-market</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A market has occured in Marlborough throughout its history as was vital to trading in the town. It orginates in 1204 when King John granted Wednesday and Saturday markets to the town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A weekly market was held in Swindon from 1260 onwards and this reduced the profits made at Marlborough. When the borough was incorporated in 1576 the mayor of Marlborough became clerk of the market and was empowered to regulate the market by passing by-laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market place in 1289 (or earlier) was between the east end of the High Street and the high or the Market Cross. The high cross was probably a timber building set in a stone base which contained the market house. In the early 17th the cheese &amp;amp; butter market was held under it and the town hall occupied the site from 1630 onwards. The wool market was then held in the premises. Saturday markets were always more important than Wednesdays and sometimes the smaller market would lapse; no Wednesday market was held in the later 17th century when Saturday market was an important cheese market attended by London cheesemongers in 1797.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The market sold meat, eggs, poultry, fruit, toys, confectionary, and farm animals (pigs, sheep, cattle &amp;amp; horses).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 11:46:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21313 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Castle</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-castle</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; The wooden castle was built by William the conqueror as his invasion force came to the West Country in 1086. It later became to be strengthened by Roger, bishop of Salisbury in 1100 and was later rebuilt in stone. The history of the structure of the castle is interesting and the details of its strengthening and rebuilding throughout the centuries show us that the castle was highly valued by both monarchs and their officials and powerful locals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Important individuals feature in the castles history the first being Agelric who was the bishop of the South Saxons. He was held hostage in the castle in 1070 after William came to successfully conquer the West Country in 1068. The royal history of the castle does not finish here as the castle became a royal residence and the royal court often visited. Savernake forest and the neighbouring wood of Aldbourne chase were favourite royal hunting grounds. Notable figures linked to the castle are as follows. John of Gaunt, son of Edward III had a hunting lodge in the middle of the chase. Henry I spent Easter there in 1110. Henry III was married there and in 1245 his mother died there. On his death the castle became part of the dowry of his widow, Queen Eleanor and on her death was conferred by Edward I on his own Queen. Edward II bestowed it on his favourite Hugh Le Despencer in 1308; on his fall his wife Queen Isabel obtained it. In the reign of Edward III the castle was held by various wardens for the King’s sister. Richard II granted it to Sir William Scrope – on his execution in 1399 it reverted back to the crown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The castle was allowed to fall into ruin after the Wars of the Roses. The wise policy of Henry VII strengthened the crown so great castles were no longer needed to keep the peace. Old feudal fortresses became valueless, as explosives were now in use and castles were defenceless against gunpowder. Edward VI, last royal owner of the castle, passed it on to the Seymour family as this was his mother’s line. Today the site of the castle belongs to Marlborough College.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 11:29:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21311 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
