<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Anglo-Saxon / Early Medieval (AD410-1066)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/period/anglo-saxon-early-medieval-ad410-1066</link>
 <description>AD410-1066</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Estuary and Holland Haven</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-estuary-and-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet was the name of the large estuary fed by the Holland River or brook, which formerly ran into the sea between Frinton and Little Holland. The name is probably Anglo-Saxon in origin, as the second element ‘fleet’ is derived from the Old English word fleot meaning ‘stream’ or ‘creek’. A similar well known example is the River Fleet in London, a tributary of the River Thames which was fed by streams on Hampstead Heath and which used to have a tidal inlet and docks at its lower end. The origin of the first element of the name ‘Gun’ is currently unknown, but it possibly derived from an Anglo-Saxon personal name, so the meaning of the whole name could be something like ‘Gunna’s creek’. An alternative suggestion that has been made is that the first part of the name could be a corruption from the Count of Guisnes who possessed the manor of Little Holland in 1210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the name was not recorded until 1320 when a vessel was shipwrecked on ‘Gunfletsond’, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. It seems probable that a name originally applying to the estuary was appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary’s inlet. A map of 1584 in the British Library marks both the ‘Gonflet haven’ (the estuary) and the ‘ye gonflit’ (the sandbank). Other maps from that period, such as maps of Essex by Norden (1594) and Speed (1610) show the Gunfleet as a large, unreclaimed, estuary that was open to the sea at its southern end. The use of the name ‘haven’ would seem to imply the use of the estuary for trade, and the ‘Ganflete’ was also named as a port between Walton and St Osyth in Holinshed’s Chronicles (1586). The substantial marshlands along the estuary were also used by the inhabitants of surrounding parishes like Great and Little Holland as grazing for their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1542 ‘the level of Gunflete haven’ was recorded, perhaps indicating that estuary’s marshland later known as Holland Levels had started to be reclaimed. Although the estuary continued to be marked on coastal maps and sea charts for a long time, it was becoming blocked perhaps by the effects of coastal erosion and long-shore drift. In 1677 a whale was stranded in the narrows at what was probably the entrance to the Gunfleet estuary then described as a ‘creek’. Probably soon afterwards it was decided to reclaim the estuary by constructing a sea wall across its mouth, with a sluice provided to allow the river water to drain away to sea. The intention was to prevent salt water entering the marshes along the Holland River, and thus to improve their agricultural potential and value. It is not known when the first wall was built, but in 1703 a survey was taken of ‘ye Levell or Flatts being several pieces or parcells of land endamaged by a breach at, or near Gunfleet Haven’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The records of the Tendring Levels Commissioners, a type of local government body charged with flood defence, survive from 1727 and show how they maintained the drained marshlands of the level, the sea wall and the sluice through which the Holland River then emptied into the open sea. By the 1760s the area was sufficiently drained to allow a new road link to cross the former estuary from Holland on Sea to Great Holland, although the extensive tracts of land were still liable to flood as shown by the marshes depicted on the Chapman and André map of 1777 and the one inch Ordnance Survey map (1838 edition). The Commissioners continued to be responsible for maintaining the sea wall and the Levels until the 1930s, and their maps reveal the outline of the old estuary through the land that had to pay rates to maintain the sea defences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (1935), pp.13–17. K. Walker, various notes. Calendar of Close Rolls, Edw. II, A.D. 1318–23 (HMSO, 1895), p.249. Holinshed, An Historicall Description of the Iland of Britaine (1586), Book I, Chapter XVII: Of such ports and creeks as our sea-faring men doo note for their benefit upon the coasts of England. British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584) J. Norden, Speculi Britanniae Pars (1594), ed. H. Ellis (Camden Society, London, 1840), map. J. Speed, Map of Essex (1610) J. Chapman and P. André, A Map of Essex (1777). Ordnance Survey map, 1” to 1 Mile (1838) Essex Record Office, D/DHw E14, ‘A true Survey of ye Levell or Flatts’, 1703. ERO, D/ST 1 to 6, Tendring Levels Commissioners, minute books, 1727–1932 ERO, D/ST 17 to 20, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps, 1783 ERO, T/M 565/1, 2, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps c.1901–25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 13:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Test Asset</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/test-asset</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Test Asset Caption&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Matthew  Bristow&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;This is a test asset&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2015/03/10/075_nro_cdc_tube_24_the_lincolners_possibly_end_of_1971.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1587537&quot;&gt;075_nro_cdc_tube_24_the_lincolners_possibly_end_of_1971.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 16:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23385 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Sarum</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-sarum</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum in Wiltshire is well known as notorious rotten borough pre the 1832 reform act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum was the original site of the settlement of Salisbury but the population moved to a nearby site as the original site was not big enough to satisfy the local needs. The rotten borough had 7 votes for just 3 houses and 1 MP represented these voters despite no MP’s for many of the new industrial cities such as Birmingham, Sheffield and Manchester. In the last election of 1831 11 votes were cast all from land owners who didn’t live in the borough.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The settlement moved a mile and a quarter to the south away from the natural hill fortress so the site could be easily expanded. It was mentioned in the doomsday book and was owned by the bishop of Salisbury the books mentions 50 hides and land for 32 ploughs in 1086. Cathedral foundations were found within the hill fort. The settlement was named as Sorbiodunum and was one of ten British cities that had particular privileges such as a castle and good roads. The city was established in 1220 in this new location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:27:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21320 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Plan of St Stephen&#039;s Church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/plan-st-stephens-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Plan of St Stephen&#039;s Church&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/%5Bsite-date-yyyy%5D/%5Bsite-date-mm%5D/%5Bsite-date-dd%5D/StSteph.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=48468&quot;&gt;StSteph.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 15:03:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>EmilyD</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21128 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Map showing the influence of geology on the settlement of Gnosall</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/map-showing-influence-geology-settlement-gnosall</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Map showing the influence of geology on the settlement of Gnosall&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Ben Cunliffe&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Ben Cunliffe&lt;p&gt;The village of Gnosall is situated close to a significant geological boundary. To the north and east lies an area of Mercian Mudstone that gives rise to the more fertile and easily worked soils, and is the most likely location for the medieval community’s arable fields. Closer to the village and extending to encompass Audmore is an area of Devensian Till giving rise to land that is moderately fertile, but seasonally wet and, therefore, better suited for pasturing animals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The village itself is appropriately located on a well drained, but relatively infertile, site. The references to heath and moor in local place-names are indicative of rough grazing, while meadow land bordering the water courses to the west of village would have provided hay for the feeding of livestock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several local place-names incorporate the term leah, (e.g. Doley, Cowley, Knightley), which is thought to have meant woodland pasture, where trees were widely spaced and livestock, such as cattle, goats, sheep, pigs etc. were kept. Plardiwick, which is first recorded in 1199 AD, may also be associated with stock rearing, as it possibly incorporates the term heord(e)wic indicating a sheep farm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2012/04/05/gnosall_geological_map.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=590884&quot;&gt;gnosall_geological_map.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 08:41:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20848 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Landscape of the Prebendal Manor of Gnosall</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/landscape-prebendal-manor-gnosall</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The earliest surviving record of Gnosall is in the Domesday Book of 1086, where the name is written as&lt;em&gt; Geneshale.&lt;/em&gt; However, it is likely that Gnosall had been in existence for a long time prior to this date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The place-name ‘Gnosall’ incorporates both native British and Old English elements describing the local topography. The place may have been originally called Geneu by the British, referring to the narrowing of a valley, of which there are several possible examples in the immediate vicinity. To this name was added the element halh; in this instance probably indicating ‘low-lying land by a river’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time of the Domesday survey, Gnosall was a modestly sized settlement consisting of 8 ‘villein’ households - tenants who held land in return for labouring on behalf of their lord, and 4 ‘bordars’ or smallholders. Domesday records that there was sufficient arable land to keep two ploughs in work and that these local people had two ploughs. However, there seems to have been some over-capacity in this respect, because there were another four ploughs owned by the lords of the manor, presumably the nine priests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a water mill for grinding corn. Gnosall seems to have been a fairly poor, but improving, community; its value had increased from 2 shillings in 1066 AD to 15 shillings in 1086 AD. However, this higher value only placed Gnosall in the middle of the range for the county as a whole, and Staffordshire was a relatively poor county.&lt;br /&gt;
	The Domesday Book gives only a partial account of local agriculture, making no reference to other resources, such as pasture, meadow or woodland, yet it is clear that livestock farming was probably as important to the area as growing crops. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2012 08:09:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MatthewBlake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20845 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Anglo Saxon Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/anglo-saxon-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Anglo-Saxon boundary&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;This stream, a tributary of the Devon Yeo and the boundary between Molland and Twitchen, may have been the ancient western boundary of the Anglo-Saxon royal manor and hundred of Molland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2010/04/09/http___www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk_resources_assets_B_Boundary_of_Molland_and_Twitchen_4367.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=52051&quot;&gt;http___www.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk_resources_assets_B_Boundary_of_Molland_and_Twitchen_4367.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2010 09:42:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">19712 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Complete Text</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/complete-text-38</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Alan Thacker / Brennan Smith&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Discovered built into the wall above the chancel arch of St Peter’s in 1864, the Anglo-Saxon sculpture now stands against the north chancel wall. A single, tapering block of Bath stone from the Chalfield area (north Wiltshire), 1.25m high and split lengthwise, it was probably carved on all its faces; one broad face was lost when the stone was split. The carving is deep-cut and the detail well-preserved. It is likely that the unweathered stone has always been within a church on the site of the present St Peter’s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Office document icon&quot; title=&quot;application/msword&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/x-office-document.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2010/03/22/The_anglo-saxon_sculptured_stone.doc&quot; type=&quot;application/msword; length=134144&quot;&gt;The_anglo-saxon_sculptured_stone.doc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2010 15:42:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">18213 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Anglo-Saxon strap end</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/anglo-saxon-strap-end</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Anglo-Saxon strap end&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Anglo-Saxon strap end from Cranborne&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2010/03/22/cranbourne_strap_end.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=349506&quot;&gt;cranbourne_strap_end.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2010 13:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">16939 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Sheffield Stone</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/sheffield-stone</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;The Sculptured Sheffield Stone&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;The British Museum&lt;p&gt;An Anglo-Saxon Sculptured Stone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2010/03/22/sheffield.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=77083&quot;&gt;sheffield.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 22 Mar 2010 13:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">16937 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
