<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Norman (1066-1154)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/period/norman-1066-1154</link>
 <description>1066-1154</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Estuary and Holland Haven</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-estuary-and-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet was the name of the large estuary fed by the Holland River or brook, which formerly ran into the sea between Frinton and Little Holland. The name is probably Anglo-Saxon in origin, as the second element ‘fleet’ is derived from the Old English word fleot meaning ‘stream’ or ‘creek’. A similar well known example is the River Fleet in London, a tributary of the River Thames which was fed by streams on Hampstead Heath and which used to have a tidal inlet and docks at its lower end. The origin of the first element of the name ‘Gun’ is currently unknown, but it possibly derived from an Anglo-Saxon personal name, so the meaning of the whole name could be something like ‘Gunna’s creek’. An alternative suggestion that has been made is that the first part of the name could be a corruption from the Count of Guisnes who possessed the manor of Little Holland in 1210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the name was not recorded until 1320 when a vessel was shipwrecked on ‘Gunfletsond’, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. It seems probable that a name originally applying to the estuary was appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary’s inlet. A map of 1584 in the British Library marks both the ‘Gonflet haven’ (the estuary) and the ‘ye gonflit’ (the sandbank). Other maps from that period, such as maps of Essex by Norden (1594) and Speed (1610) show the Gunfleet as a large, unreclaimed, estuary that was open to the sea at its southern end. The use of the name ‘haven’ would seem to imply the use of the estuary for trade, and the ‘Ganflete’ was also named as a port between Walton and St Osyth in Holinshed’s Chronicles (1586). The substantial marshlands along the estuary were also used by the inhabitants of surrounding parishes like Great and Little Holland as grazing for their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1542 ‘the level of Gunflete haven’ was recorded, perhaps indicating that estuary’s marshland later known as Holland Levels had started to be reclaimed. Although the estuary continued to be marked on coastal maps and sea charts for a long time, it was becoming blocked perhaps by the effects of coastal erosion and long-shore drift. In 1677 a whale was stranded in the narrows at what was probably the entrance to the Gunfleet estuary then described as a ‘creek’. Probably soon afterwards it was decided to reclaim the estuary by constructing a sea wall across its mouth, with a sluice provided to allow the river water to drain away to sea. The intention was to prevent salt water entering the marshes along the Holland River, and thus to improve their agricultural potential and value. It is not known when the first wall was built, but in 1703 a survey was taken of ‘ye Levell or Flatts being several pieces or parcells of land endamaged by a breach at, or near Gunfleet Haven’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The records of the Tendring Levels Commissioners, a type of local government body charged with flood defence, survive from 1727 and show how they maintained the drained marshlands of the level, the sea wall and the sluice through which the Holland River then emptied into the open sea. By the 1760s the area was sufficiently drained to allow a new road link to cross the former estuary from Holland on Sea to Great Holland, although the extensive tracts of land were still liable to flood as shown by the marshes depicted on the Chapman and André map of 1777 and the one inch Ordnance Survey map (1838 edition). The Commissioners continued to be responsible for maintaining the sea wall and the Levels until the 1930s, and their maps reveal the outline of the old estuary through the land that had to pay rates to maintain the sea defences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (1935), pp.13–17. K. Walker, various notes. Calendar of Close Rolls, Edw. II, A.D. 1318–23 (HMSO, 1895), p.249. Holinshed, An Historicall Description of the Iland of Britaine (1586), Book I, Chapter XVII: Of such ports and creeks as our sea-faring men doo note for their benefit upon the coasts of England. British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584) J. Norden, Speculi Britanniae Pars (1594), ed. H. Ellis (Camden Society, London, 1840), map. J. Speed, Map of Essex (1610) J. Chapman and P. André, A Map of Essex (1777). Ordnance Survey map, 1” to 1 Mile (1838) Essex Record Office, D/DHw E14, ‘A true Survey of ye Levell or Flatts’, 1703. ERO, D/ST 1 to 6, Tendring Levels Commissioners, minute books, 1727–1932 ERO, D/ST 17 to 20, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps, 1783 ERO, T/M 565/1, 2, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps c.1901–25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 13:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Morwenstow church north arcade</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/morwenstow-church-north-arcade</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Morwenstow church north arcade&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt; The western three bays of the North aisle are 12th-century decorated with beakheads, zig-zags and  pellets while the spandrels contain carved heads including a ram. The remainder of the arcade dates from the 13th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2014/10/13/morwenstow_church_n_arcade_19_sep_2014.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1677650&quot;&gt;morwenstow_church_n_arcade_19_sep_2014.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 13:31:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23119 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Morwenstow church south porch and doorway</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/morwenstow-church-south-porch-and-doorway</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Morwenstow church south porch and doorway&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;The south doorway dates from the 12th century. The original outer layer of moulding carved in polyphant stone has been moved to create the arch of the porch. It consists of a row of flower heads, now much damaged, above fine zig-zag carving&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner doorway retains arches of beakheads and zig-zags. There are  birds and pine cones carved on capitals, some may have been recut but the porch has protected the doorway from the worst of the weather for several centuries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2014/10/13/morwenstow_church_s_porch_19_sep_2014.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1628537&quot;&gt;morwenstow_church_s_porch_19_sep_2014.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 13:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23118 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The south door of Kilkhampton church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/south-door-kilkhampton-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Kilkhampton church south door&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Within the 1567 porch with its fine granite doorway inscribed on the datestone as the &#039;porta celi&#039; or gate of heavenis a magnificent Romanesque south doorway of the 12th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2014/09/29/kilkhampton_church_s_door_22_sep_2014.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2308608&quot;&gt;kilkhampton_church_s_door_22_sep_2014.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 15:28:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23099 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Trowbridge Industry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/trowbridge-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The town was held by Brictric, a Saxon in 1086 after his father had held it at the conquest of William the conqueror in 1066. Brictric was the most important Saxon landowner in Wiltshire therefore showing us that Trowbridge was a desirable settlement to own in this period of time. The settlement had increased economic activity in the 13th century as the building of the castle, the holding of honour courts, the presence of a garrison and at times of the baron and his retinue all were an economic burden on the settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The town’s staple trade is the cloth industry and it began in the 15th century although the prosperity of this trade would last several centuries. John Leland came to Trowbridge shortly after 1543 he was impressed by the towns trade when he stated ‘the towne flourishith by drapery.’ The prosperity of certain individuals at this time can be realised when looking at the vast personal wealth that they held. When Thomas Bailey, a clothman died in 1543 he left 1000 marks to his wife and vestments to the churches of Wingfield and Keevil. The quality of his grand house also needs to be considered as his fine timber-framed house survived for four centuries after his death; it was located in Fore Street.        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cloth industry continued to be the town’s main employment trade into the 20th century and mills sprung up in and around the town. Trowbridge was known as the Manchester of the west and exported its cloth worldwide. Unfortunately the industry declined in the later 20th century and the mills was demolished and they could no longer achieve a profit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 12:43:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21403 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Castle Coin</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/marlborough-castle-coin</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Marlborough castle coin&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Becky Rousell&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Wiltshire &amp;amp; Swindon History Centre&lt;p&gt;Here is a coin displaying an image of Marlborough Castle.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2013/02/20/marlborough_p17719_0.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2922052&quot;&gt;marlborough_p17719.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 11:33:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21312 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Marlborough Castle</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/marlborough-castle</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; The wooden castle was built by William the conqueror as his invasion force came to the West Country in 1086. It later became to be strengthened by Roger, bishop of Salisbury in 1100 and was later rebuilt in stone. The history of the structure of the castle is interesting and the details of its strengthening and rebuilding throughout the centuries show us that the castle was highly valued by both monarchs and their officials and powerful locals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Important individuals feature in the castles history the first being Agelric who was the bishop of the South Saxons. He was held hostage in the castle in 1070 after William came to successfully conquer the West Country in 1068. The royal history of the castle does not finish here as the castle became a royal residence and the royal court often visited. Savernake forest and the neighbouring wood of Aldbourne chase were favourite royal hunting grounds. Notable figures linked to the castle are as follows. John of Gaunt, son of Edward III had a hunting lodge in the middle of the chase. Henry I spent Easter there in 1110. Henry III was married there and in 1245 his mother died there. On his death the castle became part of the dowry of his widow, Queen Eleanor and on her death was conferred by Edward I on his own Queen. Edward II bestowed it on his favourite Hugh Le Despencer in 1308; on his fall his wife Queen Isabel obtained it. In the reign of Edward III the castle was held by various wardens for the King’s sister. Richard II granted it to Sir William Scrope – on his execution in 1399 it reverted back to the crown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The castle was allowed to fall into ruin after the Wars of the Roses. The wise policy of Henry VII strengthened the crown so great castles were no longer needed to keep the peace. Old feudal fortresses became valueless, as explosives were now in use and castles were defenceless against gunpowder. Edward VI, last royal owner of the castle, passed it on to the Seymour family as this was his mother’s line. Today the site of the castle belongs to Marlborough College.&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 11:29:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21311 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Church of St Stephen, showing tower, from west</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/church-st-stephen-showing-tower-west</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Eric Berry&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Church of St Stephen, showing tower, from west&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/%5Bsite-date-yyyy%5D/%5Bsite-date-mm%5D/%5Bsite-date-dd%5D/Church%20of%20St%20Stephen%2C%20showing%20tower%2C%20from%20west.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1105758&quot;&gt;Church of St Stephen, showing tower, from west.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 16:14:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>EmilyD</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21156 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Church of St Stephen: porch from south</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/church-st-stephen-porch-south</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Eric Berry&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Church of St Stephen: porch from south&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/%5Bsite-date-yyyy%5D/%5Bsite-date-mm%5D/%5Bsite-date-dd%5D/Church%20of%20St%20Stephen-%20porch%20from%20south.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1518763&quot;&gt;Church of St Stephen- porch from south.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 16:13:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>EmilyD</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21155 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Church of St Petroc: nave and aisles from chancel</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/church-st-petroc-nave-and-aisles-chancel</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Eric Berry&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Church of St Petroc: nave and aisles from chancel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/%5Bsite-date-yyyy%5D/%5Bsite-date-mm%5D/%5Bsite-date-dd%5D/Church%20of%20St%20Petroc-%20nave%20and%20aisles%20from%20chancel.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=770313&quot;&gt;Church of St Petroc- nave and aisles from chancel.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 16:03:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>EmilyD</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21154 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
