<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - North East</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/region/north-east</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Customs duties and the Sunderland coal trade</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/customs-duties-and-sunderland-coal-trade</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1700 Sunderland was &#039;noted for its sea coal trade&#039;, supplying a &#039;great quantity of coals&#039; and employing &#039;great numbers of ships yearly in carrying coals...&#039; Most was transported along the east and south coasts of England and some to Scotland.  Customs duties were collected on all coal shipped out of Sunderland, so quantities were recorded. Some of the lists survive, from which these graphs have been draw.  Even though incomplete and sometimes unclear, the graphs show a dramatic rise in total coal sales over the century, and a matching increase in overseas exports.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12667 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Witney Street (south): No. 12 (Bull Cottage)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/witney-street-south-no-12-bull-cottage</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This small early 14th-century house, though heavily remodelled, may be Burford&#039;s earliest surviving domestic building, and is documented from the 1390s. A watercolour of 1840 shows that it had a two-centred arched doorway to the street and an adjacent window with ballflower decoration, whose top half was cut off in the 16th or 17th century when a floor was inserted. Part of a medieval column and capital survives just below the eastern (left-hand) apex of the roof, perhaps relating to an earlier roof structure. Fourteenth-century features inside include archways, a chimneypiece, and more ballflower decoration, while the rear wing has a raised cruck truss with arched braces to a collar. A Decorated (14th-century) chimneystack shown on the eastern gable in 1840 belonged to the neighbouring house (No. 14), which has been largely rebuilt. Presumably the stack escaped demolition because the gable was shared with No. 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1396 John Cakebread left the house to his wife Matilda and others. Later owners included Thomas Spicer (1402), John Hill or Prior (to 1492), and Thomas Poole of London (1492–c.1504). By 1628 the house was a tavern or inn called the Talbot, run apparently by the cooper George Fowler who was tenant by the late 1590s. A 17th-century remodelling of the front may have taken place around that time. The name Talbot continued in use until the early 18th century, although named tenants included London gentry and a Burford clothier rather than innkeepers. If it was indeed still an inn, presumably they sublet it to local publicans. From 1707 it was held with the neighbouring Bull Inn and became associated with its stabling, which probably saved it from more radical rebuilding; in the 1850s it was inhabited by agricultural labourers, and from the 1870s by ostlers. It was brought back into full domestic use in the 20th century, when the present 17th-century-style windows were inserted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Photo by Richard Shaw, Oxfordshire Buildings Record) &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See: M Laithwaite, &#039;The Buildings of Burford&#039;, in A Everitt (ed), Perspectives in English Urban History (1973),  plate I, 74–7; Listed Building Description; RH Gretton, The Burford Records (1920), 333–6, 339–40, 342–3, 345, 351, 353, 355, 358–9, 366, 420–1; R Moody, The Inns of Burford (2007), 23–4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12539 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sunderland Wills and Inventories</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sunderland-wills-and-inventories</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Almost 500 wills and inventories, pertaining to Sunderland in the period 1549-1700, have now been identified and transcribed thanks to the sterling work of our Washington volunteers, led by John Smith. The probate records range across a broad section of local society – from the Hilton family at the top of the social scale down to labourers and poor widows at the lower end. As such this material provides a wealth of information regarding the occupations, living standards and communal and family relationships of the inhabitants of Sunderland during the period under consideration.   Most of the wills and inventories identified were proved in the Durham diocesan probate court, which had jurisdiction where the deceased’s entire estate fell within the diocese of Durham. The records of these are held in Durham University Library, Archives and Special Collections section. See the Library’s online probate project, North East Inheritance,  for further detailed information on these sources. In a small number of cases however, where the estate of the deceased encompassed more than one diocese, probate was granted in the Archdiocesan Prerogative courts of Canterbury or, on occasion, York. The probate records of the former are held in The National Archives and the latter in the Borthwick Institute, York.   &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12252 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>North Prospect of the town of Sunderland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/north-prospect-town-sunderland</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;rteleft&quot;&gt;Samuel Buck&#039;s North Prospect of the Town of Sunderland, engraved about 1720, presents a lively and vivid image of the town and port and provides an insight into the development of the port and town of Sunderland from the late 16th to the early 18th centuries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12250 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A New Parish</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/new-parish</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the early 1700s the wealthy urban élite of Sunderland were complaining that  most pews in Bishopwearmouth were owned by local landowners. Well-placed seats in St Michael and All Angels were at a premium, valued so much that rights to them appeared in a marriage contract, that of Richard Richardson jun. of Sunderland and Thomasine Holmes in 1704. St Michael’s could accommodate only a quarter of parishioners. When Stockton was given a new parish in 1712, Sunderland was prompted to lobby for its own. An appeal for funds raised pledges of £1,000, and land on the town moor was allocated for Holy Trinity church and graveyard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12246 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Sunderland Quayside</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sunderland-quayside</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The changing face of the Sunderland quayside&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12245 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A Growing Town</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/growing-town</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;With some 6,00 or so people living around the mouth of the Wear in 1719, Sunderland now stood within the middle rank of English towns, although still much smaller than its near neighbour Newcastle. Within the borough, the population crowded around High Street and Low Street although the built-up area was expanding west to the Panns and southwards towards the Town Moor&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12244 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Glass Making Industry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/glass-making-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Glass making was one of the industries which developed in later 17th century Sunderland, taking advantage of the supply of otherwise unsaleable coal, raw materials brought in cheaply as ballast and the excellent links to extensive markets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12243 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Early Wearmouth Settlements</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/early-wearmouth-settlements</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until 1719, the area that was to become Sunderland was divided into two parishes which served administrative as well as religious purposes. These parishes in turn were subdivided into a number of townships or vills, with small settlements distributed throughout the townships. The two parishes took their names from the larger villages near the mouth of the river where medieval parish life was centred. South of the river the pre-Conquest South Wearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wiremuthe australem&lt;/em&gt;)eventually became known as Bishopwearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wermouth Episcopi&lt;/em&gt;) since this township, together with the small medieval borough of Sunderland and the outlying vills of the parish were held by the bishop of Durham. On the northern bank of the river the site of the Anglian monastery, formerly known as Wearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wiremuthe&lt;/em&gt;), subsequently became known as Monkwearmouth (&lt;em&gt;Wermouth monachorum&lt;/em&gt;) since this settlement and its two adjacent townships were, from the late 11th century, in the hands of Durham priory.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12242 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Shipbuilding in Sunderland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/shipbuilding-sunderland</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The later 17th century records of goods imported and exported in Sunderland show existing industries expanding and new ones developing. The extraordinary growth of the coal exporting trade stimulated much of this. Shipbuilding with its associated trades was one such trade which was closely linked with and directly supplied the coal trade.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12241 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
