<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Street</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/street</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Housing in Street</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/housing-street-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;After an outbreak of fever in 1853 caused by poor drainage, lack of sanitation, and water pollution and some very bad housing Street Board of Health was formed under the chairmanship of Cyrus Clark. It had a salaried clerk, a treasurer, a medical officer of health, a surveyor, and an inspector of nuisances assisted by two people in each of the four districts into which the parish was divided. The board was originally responsible for drainage, water supply, refuse collection, and road repair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The report that led to the setting up of the Board of health revealed the poor conditions in which many of workers had been living probably and led to the provision of housing by the Clark family for their shoemakers. Superior cottages were built in the 1850s in Somerton Lane followed by the development of new roads off High Street including Cranhill and Orchard roads, lined with long terraces of workers housing and Wilfrid Road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See volume 9 of the Victoria County history of Somerset for a full history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2012 14:53:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20905 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Education in Street</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/education-street</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 1800s there were several denominational Sunday schools and dame schools. Attempts to set up a joint Anglican and nonconformist day school failed in 1827 because of religious differences between the promoters Frances Clark and Susannah Hawkins, but in 1831 the Street and Walton British school was started in Teetotal Row, later West End. In 1833 only 47 boys and 42 girls received a daily education at voluntary schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A National School had been established by 1839 when it taught 52 children on weekdays and 42 on Sundays but by 1847 it took infants only and it was said that the school declined after 1850. However it remained open probably until 1874 when the school board was formed. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th-century Street pioneered co-educational secondary education, training in cookery and housewifery for girls going into service and special needs education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See volume 9 of the Victoria County History of Somerset for a full history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2012 23:03:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20878 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
