<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Sussex</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/county/sussex</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Georgian Chancel of Laughton Church in East Sussex</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/georgian-chancel-laughton-church-east-sussex</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sir Thomas Robinson designed Glynde Church for Richard Trevor, the Bishop of Durham who rebuilt it in 1763-65. he employed John Morris of Lewes, a surveyor and stonemason who also designed buildings such as the stable block at Glynde Place. When Thomas Pelham-Holles, Duke of Newcastle decided to rebuild the chancel below which many members of his family were buried at Laughton, he employed a &#039;Mr Robinson&#039; to design it. There were two Robinsons working during htis period but as Sir Thomas was employed at Glynde it seems likely that this design may be by him.  The Duke let his very competant agent, Abraham Baley get on with the project.  He recommended John Morris who did the work in  1764-65. Baley recommended to the Duke that the design was modified, remarking that the intended one seemed too ambitious. The evidence suggests that the design was amended by John Morris.  The Gothick style chancel survives. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the detail and a discussion abut other churches in the Lewes area which were designed and built by builders and surveyors see Sue Berry, &#039;Laughton Church Chancel and other major church alterations in and around Lewes, East Sussex, c.1740-1810. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 12 Dec 2010 21:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20390 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bishopstone Tide Mills East Sussex</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bishopstone-tide-mills-east-sussex</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; This Georgian tidemill stood east of Newhaven in East Sussex very close to the coast. A few pieces of the foundations of the buildings and concrete platforms from later uses survive. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remains of a long shingle spit provided shelter for stretches of a redundant river course, once the main outlier of the River Ouse which flows through the South Downs to its present outfall at Newhaven.  For a long time the river had meandered along its coastal floodplain to Seaford which is why that town was a medieval port.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bishopstone Tidemills lies between Newhaven and Seaford close to Bishopstone railway halt.  The landscape is now changing so quickly that older Ordnance Survey maps and the Tithe Map, old photographs and the ninteenth century census enumerators’ schedules are the best sources of information about the scale of this business. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possibility of a tidemill arose when in 1731-1733 a cut was made through the shingle at Castle Hill, Newhaven and secured by piers.  This worked, whereas previous attempts to make a cut here had not. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The creek formed by this work lay in the parish of Bishopstone and was owned by Thomas Pelham-Holles, Duke of Newcastle.  It was leased by him to three corn merchants and in 1761, a private Act of Parliament passed which enabled them to build a dam for the mill across the creek.  Tidemills were not a novelty in the south east.  John Challen and William Woods were Chichester corn merchants  and John Woods of Chilgrove (near Chichester) and should have known the tidemill at Emsworth just west of Chichester. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1768 the mill was standing for then a French army officer mistook it for barracks.  In 1791, John Woods advertised the mill for sale with a description of it.   A Mr. Barton bought the mill in 1792 and in 1795 he entered a partnership with Edmund Catt.  In 1801, Barton was replaced by William Catt. William  had run a small mill in Lamberhurst (Kent) before he moved to Bishopstone.  In 1808 he bought out Edmund Catt with the help of Edmund Cooper of Norton Farm (in Bishopstone)  and Thomas Farncombe of Bishopstone Farm, both wealthy tenant farmers.  The profits of the mill, which Catt extended, came from the demand for milled grain during the Napoleonic Wars not only in Sussex where the seaside resorts such as Brighton expanded but also for the many barracks such as the one at Seaford.  Catt and Cooper invested at Shoreham and in Brighton, thus developing new markets for their products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(C) Sue Berry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To read more see Sue Farrant (now Berry) ‘Bishopstone Tidemills’ Sussex Archaeological Collections Vol.113 (1975) 199-202.  &lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2010 14:09:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>SueB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20372 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>From Family House to Open House at Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/family-house-open-house-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major events in the life of a country house often leave little trace upon the building. The experience of those who have lived through them has to be recovered from diaries, letters, written recollections, and oral testimony. The transitory impact of the Second World War on Parham is recorded in photographs and in the memoirs of Veronica, one of the Pearson children who first knew the house as a family home but who returned during the war and stayed to welcome, with her mother, the first visitors to the house in 1948.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12681 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Walled Garden</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/walled-garden</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structural features of gardens, such as buildings and walls, can be permanent and outlive plant life.  A detailed history of these gardens is preserved only with those who tended to, and experienced personally how these gardens evolved under their care.  The walled garden at Parham was probably created in the 18th century and paths and brick walls survive from that period. It must always have been a productive garden, supplying food and flowers for the household.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12680 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Country house design</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/country-house-design</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The desire to introduce fashionable features, such as a top-floor long gallery, into country houses demanded new solutions to make them possible. At Parham, the roof over the main range was designed to create an unobstructed attic with sufficient head room, so to be used as one of the most important and most visited rooms in the house. It was decorated in a style similar to that of the hall and great chamber. The original roof is a remarkable survival of Elizabethan carpentry, though the plaster ceiling decorated by Oliver Messel is 20th-century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12679 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Seeking the medieval village of Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/seeking-medieval-village-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the medieval village of Parham was cleared and its inhabitants moved to nearby Rackham as recently as 1778-9; no record exists of where the village stood within the parish of Parham, or of where buildings that belonged to the monastic grange of Westminster Abbey might have been located. Geophysical surveys in 2006 and 2008 have provided tantalising clues about the nature of the site when Robert Palmer acquired it in 1540 and during the following three centuries. The surveys identified some features which suggest the area has been occupied perhaps since prehistoric times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geophysical survery and trial excavations carried out in the picnic area to the east of the house identified a series of damp, roughly circular features. These features could represent rubbish pits or the result of water pooling in the centre of rooms where houses may have stood. At the very least these findings seem to represent fragmentary evidence of occupation, if not the site of the medieval village of Parham.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The area south-west of the house was surveyed in 2008 by the Worthing Archaeological Society, and a number of features associated with the medieval parish church were identified. Within an area of drier ground, rows of damp, rectilinear, low resistance features almost certainly represent the grave cuts of its churchyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also discoveries that could suggest the previous existance of a pre-1578 house, whose site lay within the footprint of the present house, or at least a garden wall belonging to a phase before the lawn and ha-ha were laid out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the limited success of an initial campaign of excavations, it is hoped that further work might lead to the discovery of medieval pottery in the excavation trenches, and that Parham&#039;s lost medieval village might eventually be found.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Women of Parham House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/women-parham-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women have featured strongly in the succession of owners at Parham although, until the Married Woman&#039;s Property Act of 1882, a woman&#039;s property passed automatically to her husband on marriage. Parham was most recently descended through the female line to Lady Emma Barnard, who lives there with her family now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women, and particularly heiresses, played an important part in the fortunes of landed estates such as Parham. Marriages between estate owners and  women from wealthy families brought new sources of finance to many estates. Sometimes such alliances contributed not only money but also land to the heiress&#039;s new family. When William Palmer, son of the first owner, married Elizabeth Verney of Fairfield, Somerset, he acquired her family estate, which soon after became the Palmers&#039; main home. In the 17th century the marriage of two Oxfordshire heiresses to Bisshopp owners provided new funds to draw on. Sometimes owners overestimated the wealth of their brides. Emily Wilmot-Horton unfortunately did not bring as much money to Parham as her husband, Robert Curzon junior, had expected when he married her in 1850. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to document female influence on the way that Parham developed and was used, as it is with most country houses . Most evidence survives in the form of diaries, letters and oral testimony. The diaries of Lady Catherine Pechell provide vivid pictures of life at Parham in the early 19th centuryand recollections about changes made to the house by her forebears.  The memories of Barabara Frankland and her brother recall what the house was like early in the 20th century when it was owned by their grandmother, Mary Frankland Curzon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can use written evidence and old paintings, photographs and architectural plans to assess how Parham changed as women&#039;s role in society evolved. For example, old photographs of a sitting room show its feminine character - a trait that can be seen in depictions of rooms in many other houses. The transfer of the kitchen from the basement to a more convenient position nearer the dining room on the ground floor indicates that there was more direct involvement by the mistress of the house in the preparation of meals after the Second World War, when fewer servants were employed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12619 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Coppicing at Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/coppicing-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The very best oak building timber at the end of the 16th century came from woods which were specifically managed to produce tall, straight trees for posts, beams, and rafters. Such oaks, known as ‘standards’, were grown in the company of species such as hazel which were cut almost to the ground on a regular, cyclical basis and used for necessities such as fuel and fencing. This system of regular cutting is known as coppicing. It not only ensures an almost constant supply of wood which can be harvested again and again as soon as it reaches an appropriate size, but also provides the perfect environment for growing trees suitable for building timber. Between harvests, the coppiced wood grows rapidly — as anyone who has pruned a young tree or shrub will know. The dense new growth forces the young standard timber trees to grow more swiftly than they would in the open, as they are competing for light. The oaks form a crown high above the level of the coppice, unable to throw out lower branches because of the surrounding undergrowth, so lessening the risk of knots which can weaken structural timbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; [i]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[i] O. Rackham, Trees and Woodland in the British Landscape (London, 1976), 8.(Image courtesy of the Woodland Trust Picture Library) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12618 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parham and the Second World War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parham-and-second-world-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Second World War had a great impact on the restoration of the country house.  A hiatus in the works planned by the Pearsons, combined with the use of the house by the army and as a home for evacuees, meant several steps back had to be taken before they could move forward. Work eventually began in earnest in 1949.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12617 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Pearsons</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/pearsons</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Pearsons came to Parham in 1922 neither as members of a nouveau riche ‘smart set’ nor from the old landed aristocracy. Clive Pearson, born on 12 August 1897, was the second son of the industrialist Weetman Pearson (who became the 1st Viscount Cowdray in 1917) and Annie Cass, daughter of a former lord mayor of Bradford. The Pearson family empire had its roots in Bradford in the firm of S. Pearson and Son, building contractors, in the mid-19th century. In the course of Clive’s lifetime the company grew to become the biggest of its kind in the world, famous for its harbours, railways, electrical plants, and oil installations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12616 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
