<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Penwith</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/penwith</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Probate Records - Paul Parish - 1700s</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/probate-records-paul-parish-1700s</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using volunteers the probate records of Paul Parish, held in the Cornwall Record Office, were studied and extracts transcribed to help build the picture for Dr Mattingly as she compiled a research data base from various sources.  These transcriptions were typed and are now being checked for accuracy before being uploaded to this site.  This work is also being undertaken by a volunteer, so progress is slow.  Eventually extracts from all 700 or so wills and associated documents used in the study will appear here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12094 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Probate Records - Paul Parish - late 1800s - early 1900s</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/probate-records-paul-parish-late-1800s-early-1900s</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using volunteers the probate records of Paul Parish, held in the Cornwall Record Office, were studied and extracts transcribed to help build the picture for Dr Mattingly as she compiled a research data base from various sources.  These transcriptions were typed and are now being checked for accuracy before being uploaded to this site.  This work is also being undertaken by a volunteer, so progress is slow.  Eventually extracts from all 700 or so wills and associated documents used in the study will appear here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12093 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>An exhibition based on Mousehole</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/exhibition-based-mousehole</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We were delighted when Penlee House Gallery &amp;amp; Museum agreed that as a finale to Joanna Mattingly&#039;s &quot;Penwith&quot; project we could include some of her findings in the exhibition to celebrate the centenary of the Mousehole Male Voice Choir.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12092 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Nineteenth century housing development in Newlyn</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nineteenth-century-housing-development-newlyn</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The period 1800-1914 created the settlement of Newlyn as we see it today. Until the 1870s structural change was minimal - a few villas and a new church. However, from the 1870s, hillside terraces were built and thatch became slate, transforming the visual look of each place.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1801 Newlyn had a population of about 1,360 people and in 1901 this had increased to 3,750 people. Most houses were small with two-thirds being of four rooms or less in 1891. Parents slept in one room and children in the other. However by the standards of other fishing towns this was not overcrowding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Street an Nowan villas and terraces were built for the new middle classes, from the 1850s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12089 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Nineteenth century Mousehole</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/nineteenth-century-mousehole</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By the 19th century Mousehole was just one distinct settlement. Its population growth was small, from 1461 in 1841 to 1655 in 1901. It had been overtaken economically and through population growth by Newlyn.  However, as its Victorian landscape shows, Mousehole was still a focus of intense building activity in the late 19th century.The main area of expansion were Raginnis Hill, Paul Hill and the coastal road towards Newlyn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mousehole&#039;s harbour as it appears today was created in 1868-71 at a cost of £5400. The harbour area was now double its 1838 size and the gap between the two quays could be closed by wooden baulks in stormy weather.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12088 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Prehistory Archaeology</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/prehistory-archaeology</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the area later occupied by Paul and its neighbouring parishes, prehistoric settlement was concentrated in the upland areas away from the coast. Here there are stone circles, fogous (underground passages), menhirs and burial mounds. Extensive marshes in the central part of the land beside Mount&#039;s Bay deterred habitation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finds from the neighbourhood of later Mousehole include a greenstone pounder from Raginnis of Neolitic date and a copper axe head from Penolva of the late Neolithic or early Bronze Age.  Bronze Age burial urns of c.2500-1400 BC were dug up in the south-west of the parish at Tresvennack and Trevelloe. The most intriguing, but now lost find was a gold lunula (neck ornament) from a high status site in Paul or Madron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first identifiable settlements in Paul parish were Iron Age or Romano- British settlements  of c.150 BC-400AD. There was a hill fort at Tredavoe with 14 rounds (circular defensive enclosures). There was also a courtyard house found near to Castallack round.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12087 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Turkish Pirates</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/turkish-pirates</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trade and fishing were affected by Turkish raids on west Cornwall, which began in 1625. &#039;Turks&#039; were of many nationalities including disgruntled Europeans. They made the north coast of Africa their base in 1598 with ports at Algiers, Tunis, Tripoli and Salee. Christian prisoners were sold into slavery in north Africa and ransoms had to be paid for their release. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 16 June 1640, in one of the worst raids, 60 people were taken from five fishing boats and four other vessels near Mousehole. Stories that men, women and children were taken from their beds by the Turks were widely believed, though probably unfounded. There were also Spanish, French, Dutch and local pirates, too.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12086 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Newlyn Quay</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/newlyn-quay</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Newlyn town had a quay since medieval times, but it appears to have collapsed. William Arundell rebuilt and extended it on new foundations in 1732 at a coast of £300.  The new quay was described as a &#039;broad hedge&#039; and was built of vertically set stones rather than huge boulders (the medieval method).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To prevent the quay from falling again, it was agreed that the sand could only be taken for ballast at the head of the pier. Two local fishermen came to an agreement with Arundell in 1744 to keep the new quay in repair in return for low quay dues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12085 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Fradgan</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fradgan</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Fradgan area, originally the Ox way, expanded in the 18th century. It was close to the harbour and quay it was ideal for warehouses and fishermen&#039;s cottages. &#039;Park an Fradigan meadow&#039; was the site of a new building in 1730.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12084 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Street an Nowan</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/street-nowan</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This was one of the smaller settlements that made up Newlyn. The place-name &#039;Street an Awan&#039; (street of the Oxen) was first found in Thomas Chiverton&#039;s will of 1604, when the area was still farmland. Building began here on farmland soon after the Spanish raid of 1595.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Street an Nowan was a new town which grew up  in the 17th century in a triangle of land between Newlyn Town, Paul Hill and the beach. As the settlement grew, it linked Newlyn Town, with the previously separate coastal settlement of Tolcarne just half a mile north. Street an Nowan therefore helped double the area and population of Newlyn in the early to mid 17th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic focus of Street an Nowan was the beach. Here Breton merchants dried their fish, and fish were landed at low tide. There was a quay, later known as Gwavas Quay after the fish tithe owner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meadows and orchards on the outskirts of Newlyn Town and Street an Nowan began to disappear below stone and mortar in the early 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12083 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
