<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - South East</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/region/south-east</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Gower&#039;s Iron Foundry, Hook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gowers-iron-foundry-hook</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The former iron foundry in Hook run by the Gower family on the London Road, opposite the Old White Hart Inn started production in 1826. It has intermittently come within Odiham and Newnham parishes, but being located in the centre of the village it employed men and boys from Hook as well as Nately Scures and Newnham. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From their origins in Suffolk, the Gower family created a thriving business with award winning, innovative designs of seed drills, turnip and mangold cutters and other agricultural equipment having many distinguished customers across England. The foundry survived an arson attack in 1851 and was taken over in 1912 by the Hazell family who retained the Gower name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final closure date is unknown but in 2004 the site was sold and 74 houses built on the site named Foundry Close.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a detailed history and images of some of the equipment click on the link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2019 15:22:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25710 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Wesleyan Methodism in Basingstoke c1870 to 1939</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/wesleyan-methodism-basingstoke-c1870-1939</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;From putting down permanent roots in the 1870s until the outbreak of the Second World War, Wesleyan Methodists made a notable contribution to the religious life of Basingstoke. Throughout this period their principal place of worship was in Church Street, opposite the Parish Church of St Michaels. Their first chapel, dating from 1876, was moved to Cliddesden in the early 1900s and replaced by a much larger and more imposing edifice opened in 1905.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the lead church of the Basingstoke Wesleyan Methodist circuit, the Church Street congregation had the privilege of hearing the superintendent minister preach more frequently than those of the other churches. Ministers included the Revd William P. Ellis who in 1872 was appointed by the Wesleyan Conference as ‘the first home missionary’ in the town, where he served until 1876; the Revd Samuel Miles (1876-79) under whose ‘faithful labours the little cause became well rooted’; the Revd J. Robinson Cleminson (1884-87) ‘a prince of builders’ who oversaw substantial improvements to the chapel; the Revd Samuel Oliver (1890-93) whose ‘winning manners and courteous gentlemanly demeanour … made him easily accessible even to the humblest member of his flock’; the Revd Harold Chapman (1903-08) ‘a cultured and devoted minister’, who had the privilege of being in post when the new church was opened;  the Revd Walter Barnes (1912-15) for the ‘strong leadership he provided’; the Revd James Ash Parsons (1927-31) ‘a fine example of muscular Christianity’; and the Revd Walter Weddell (1936-44) remembered for his ‘kindness, sympathy, cheerfulness and manliness.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wesleyans were also fortunate in having some long-serving and committed laymen such as Edward Kynaston, who served as Sunday School Superintendent for many years in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, and William Higgs, the Circuit Chapel Secretary during the same period. They enabled the Church to support a wide variety of affiliated organisations, such as a thriving Sunday school; from 1897, a branch of the Wesley Guild; for a number of years in the late 1870s/early 1880s, a Mutual Improvement Association; and for women a Ladies Sewing Party/Meeting and Women’s Bright Hour. These together with the regular services and those for special occasions and many ad hoc activities, including support for both home and overseas missions, offered both social and spiritual sustenance to many residents of Basingstoke. While major fund raising events provided a welcome diversion from the routine of everyday life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;right&quot;&gt;April 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 17:15:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25706 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Engagement of Churches in Social Welfare and Related Provision in Edwardian Basingstoke - 1903</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/engagement-churches-social-welfare-and-related-provision-edwardian-basingstoke-1903</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to the emergence of the Welfare State, churches made a valuable and valued contribution to social welfare provision either alone or collaboratively. In prioritising the needs of others, churches were seeking to give practical expression to Christ’s injunction to ‘love your neighbour as yourself.’ By the Edwardian era this had become formalised in the concept of ‘the social gospel’ with adherents claiming that ‘good works’ were as legitimate a pursuit for the churches as the saving of souls. Drawing upon examples from Edwardian Basingstoke during a single year, 1903, three main forms of church engagement in social welfare can be identified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there was the sponsorship of slate clubs, which were essentially savings/insurance schemes to assist members in times of financial need, such as sickness. Here a good example was the club sponsored by London Street Congregational Church’s Pleasant Sunday Afternoon Society. Established in 1901, 366 members joined the club during 1903.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, there was fund raising for good causes. In January, a two day bazaar and entertainment was organised by the Young Helper’s League to raise funds in ‘support of a “Basingstoke Cot” ’ at the Stepney Causeway homes of Dr Barnardo. A second example, was a concert given by the members of the Bethesda Male Voice Choir in May. This was a cross-denominational initiative, with the aim being to raise funds to ameliorate the suffering of the Penrhyn Quarrymen, who were on strike, and their families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, there were various kinds of what may be loosely described as ‘direct action’. One involved the establishment of a Lads Institute prompted by what was seen as a duty to provide ‘some form of attractive and healthy recreation, combined with a modicum of useful instruction, for the lads who … [spent] their spare time in the streets for want of a better place.’ Another was the extensive support given to the cause of temperance seen as a means of alleviating the social distress resulting from the excessive consumption of alcohol. This took a variety of forms, such as campaigning to ban the opening of public houses on Sundays and to reduce the number of licensed premises in the town, and facilitating the work of temperance organisations, such as the Women of the White Ribbon, the Band of Hope, the Total Abstinence Union and the British Women’s Temperance Association. On a smaller scale, following a flower service at the Congregational Church in July, the children’s offerings were ‘sent to the Cottage Hospital, the almshouses, and to the Flower Mission.’ Similarly at Harvest time the Cottage Hospital received gifts of flowers, fruit, vegetables and cash from a wide variety of churches in the neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As these examples illustrate, without the involvement of churches, life in Edwardian Basingstoke for those disadvantaged and or in need would have been poorer. By giving attention to ‘good works’, church members sought to make a difference and although on issues, such as temperance, there would have been strongly held differences of view within the community, at the very least churches were motivated by a desire to ensure that spending on alcohol was not at the expense of the wellbeing of family members, particularly women and children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 16:12:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25702 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>‘Basingstoke Churches and the People’</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/%E2%80%98basingstoke-churches-and-people%E2%80%99</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The title of this item is taken from the headline of reports which appeared in the 21 March and 4 April 1903 editions of the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt;. In the first the findings of a census of churchgoing undertaken in Basingstoke by the newspaper were presented. While in the second the results were compared with those from a earlier census carried out in 1882, with attention being drawn to the fact that in the 21 years between them the population of Basingstoke had gone up by 43.5 percent, while the increases in attendance at places of worship in the morning and evening were only 1.9 percent and 14.5 percent respectively. The observation was also made that ‘of all the denominations in the town’, it was the Established Church that ‘had made the greatest advance.’ Nevertheless, the censuses did show that at the time they were undertaken many denominations were represented in the ecclesiastical landscape of Basingstoke, thereby contributing to the diversity and richness of the religious heritage of the town. The results of the two censuses, together with those of the 1851 national religious census, provide historians with valuable insights into the relative strength of the churches both collectively and individually during the second half of the nineteenth century and the early years of the twentieth. It is a great pity that similar surveys were not undertaken in subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For full details of the censuses please see the asset)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill, March 2019&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 16:02:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25698 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Thomas&#039; Home for the Friendless and Fallen, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-thomas-home-friendless-and-fallen-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 2019 St Thomas’ Care Home in Darlington Road, Basingstoke was a dementia care home. St Thomas&#039; has an interesting history as a centre for caring for the less fortunate of the county. In January 1863 the Bishop of Winchester gave his approval to Admiral Ryder’s idea to establish a home for women whose lives were ruined by prostitution or abuse by providing them with work as laundresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1930 OS map calls St Thomas’ the Mount Tabor Certified Institution which was a different kind of home, sheltering people under the terms of the 1913 Mental Deficiency Act. In 1951 St Thomas’ got its old name back as the School for the Deaf which occupied the site until it was closed in the mid-1980s. After that the premises were used as a night-shelter for the homeless but suffered some vandalism and fires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complex was threatened with demolition for re-development in 1989 but local residents fought to save it and achieved statutory Grade II* listing for the chapel built in 1884 and also saved the residential block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a full history and timeline of St Thomas’ see the links below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2019 17:55:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25693 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dummer Boundary and Milestones</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummer-boundary-and-milestones</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local trusts were obliged to erect milestones on turnpike roads by law in 1773. Some of these stone markers can still be seen along many main roads. Dummer has three such stones on its western boundary on the A30, all of which are Grade II Listed monuments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boundary stones are less common but Dummer has two that survive on the edge of woodland demarking its parish from that of Popham and the Candovers.  Boundaries were inspected by meresmen who would agree the extent of the parish with neighbouring officials and check the condition of ditches, hedges and fences. The old custom of beating the bounds dates back to the importance of passing on the knowledge of the parish limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The link below contains photographs and a more detailed account of the stones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2019 18:34:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25689 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dummer&#039;s Lost Windmills</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dummers-lost-windmills</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at a modern map there are no signs that Dummer ever had any windmills. By researching 18th and 19th century maps there is evidence of two. These must have been dominant in the landscape at the time and provided a valuable service to the local farmers. Documents show that grain was also brought from other parishes to be milled here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little documentation is available for Dummer Clump windmill which stood in the east of the parish on the highest point in Nutley Lane. The history of Little Manor Farm windmill is more complete, but this was destroyed in 1833 by an arson attack, possibly a victim of the Swing Riots in Hampshire at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A full history of the mills and images of the maps are in the link below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 18:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25686 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The day the vicar locked the council out of the parish church of Basingstoke.</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/day-vicar-locked-council-out-parish-church-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Basingstoke made headlines in the national and provincial press in 1907 when the vicar of Basingstoke, Revd Boustead, sent an intemperate letter to the town clerk. He told the clerk that the Mayor and Corporation and the police, fire brigade and other public and voluntary bodies would not be welcome to hold the annual Civic Service in the Parish Church if they intended, in line with tradition, to hold a similar service in one of the nonconformist churches. He said that such an action would, ‘degrade God’s Church to the level of one of the 350 man-made sects’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revd Boustead’s letter was reprinted with a brief introduction in dozens of provincial newspapers from the &lt;em&gt;Cornishman&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;Aberdeen Press and Journal&lt;/em&gt; under various headlines, including ‘Strange Situation at Basingstoke’, ‘Mockery of Religion’, ‘Not wanted at Church’ and ‘Another Clerical Bigot’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mayor decided not to hold the Civic Service in the Parish Church. However, the following year he decided that the custom of the Civic Service should continue, but when the procession reached the church, the vicar had locked the church door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the full story, please see the attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 12:16:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25681 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Baptists in Basingstoke: c.1867 to 1939</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/baptists-basingstoke-c1867-1939</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were no Baptist causes in Basingstoke recorded in the religious census of 1851. Sixty years later, however, there were two - a Strict (also known as Ebenezer and Particular) Baptist dating from about 1867 and an Open Baptist from 1908. The Strict Baptists had a chapel in Church Street and one of their leading members was Thomas Burberry, the founder of what has become a global brand in the fashion industry. It is not known precisely when the Strict Baptist cause came to an end but the chapel was sold to the Basingstoke branch of the Post-War Brotherhood Movement in 1936 and the building was renamed Brotherhood Hall (later ‘Moose Hall’, ‘one of the local halls for meetings, dances, wedding receptions and other activities’).                                                                                  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Open Baptist cause principally owed its establishment to the efforts of the Revd Alfred Bird an evangelist from Whitchurch who, with assistance from the Southern Baptist Association, guided the fledgling Church during the first couple of years of its existence. For its premises the cause acquired the old British School buildings on Sarum Hill, which were converted into a place of worship. In addition, a number of the institutional markers of church life, such as a Sunday school, women’s group and Christian Endeavour Society were soon established. The Church also formed a close bond with the other major Nonconformist denominations in the town. Served by a succession of diligent ministers the cause thrived during the War years and into the 1920s and 30s. As well as leading and guiding the Church, some ministers were active in other spheres of community life. For example, the Revd Frederick West (1910-12) was a supporter of the cause of women’s suffrage; the Revd Sydney Wing (1925-32), served as a borough councillor from 1926 to 1930, topping the poll on both occasions when he sought the support of the electors; and, following the outbreak of the Second World War, the Revd John Hill (1935-39) resigned in December 1939 to begin a ‘new life as a medical orderly in the R.A.M.C. [Royal Army Medical Corps].’ As the &lt;em&gt;Hants and Berks Gazette&lt;/em&gt; observed Hill’s ‘action must arouse the keenest admiration of the townsfolk.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point during the 1930s the Church ‘severed its connection’ with the Baptist Union, the Hants Baptist Association and the Baptist Missionary Society and affiliated instead to the Fellowship of Independent Evangelical Churches. However, it continued to be known as “Sarum Hill Baptist Church”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 15:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25669 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Primitive Methodism in Basingstoke c.1830 to 1932/9</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/primitive-methodism-basingstoke-c1830-19329</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the Methodist Re-Union in 1932, the Primitive Methodists remained a distinctive feature of Basingstoke’s ecclesiastical landscape. They did, however, enjoy good relations, and collaborated closely, with the other Nonconformist denominations in the town. Indeed, their ministers were often described as brotherly and served not only their church and circuit but also the wider community. They included the Revd Charles Portnell (1868-70 and 1883-6), whose ‘preaching was plain but forceful’; the Revd Henry Yeates (1869-73), who ‘was especially gifted to stir and edify a congregation’ and later returned to Basingstoke, serving as a borough councillor from 1884 to 1887; the Revd Joseph Beal (1898-04), who ‘in his six years at Basingstoke … preached over four hundred and fifty sermons and retained his reputation for freshness’ and also superintended the erection of the new church; and  the Revd Ezra Ramm (1928-33), ‘a man sent from God, as a preacher fearless and true’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In leading their church and circuit, these ministers needed the support and encouragement of a large number of lay people, who performed most of the key roles in the organisations that the church sponsored. From Sunday schools to a flourishing Christian Endeavour society; from brass bands to the choir; and from women’s groups to a Peoples’ Pleasant Hour, such organisations cemented the loyalty of members and served as a means of reaching out to those unattached to any church. Indeed, evangelism was the &lt;em&gt;leitmotif&lt;/em&gt; running through much of the life of the Church. Its anniversary celebrations, missions, camp meetings and concerts and entertainments served the dual role of affording opportunities for fellowship amongst church members and affiliates and for drawing in the outsider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In November 1938 the Church (since the Methodist Re-Union in 1932, simply Sarum Hill Methodist Church) hosted the civic service, a particularly significant event since it ‘was the first occasion on which a member of the … Church, … [had] attended as mayor.’ Also present at the service were all the other civic dignitaries as well as representatives of the Territorials, Fire Brigade and Police. The minister, the Revd Harold Pope, preached on a verse from Revelation, Chapter 21:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I, John, saw the holy city, new Jerusalem, coming down from God out of heaven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service was clearly indicative of the extent to which what had originally been a religious group that aroused hostility had now become part of the socio-cultural establishment of the town. In the process, however, it could be argued that it had lost something of the ‘spiritual cutting edge’ that had previously characterised Primitive Methodism. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For the source of the quotations please see the pdf link below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roger Ottewill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October 2018&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2018 11:37:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25661 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
