<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Somerton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/somerton</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Somerton parish church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/somerton-parish-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The church of St Michael and All Angels, Somerton was probably built in the 13th century but enlarged in the 14th including the South aisle and its windows. The clerestorey was added in the 15th century when the west window was inserted. The church was heavily restored in 1889. Unusually it has a south transeptal tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of the church will be found in volume three of the Victoria County History of Somerset&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 08:43:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20990 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Somerton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/somerton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no evidence for the oft repeated claim that Somerton was the capital of Wessex but it was an important town as the Witan met there in 949. In 1278 the shire courts were moved there from Ilchester and in 1280 the county gaol was sited in Somerton. However, in 1366 the court moved back to Ilchester and Somerton gaol ceased to be the county prison by 1371. So ended Somerton’s brief period as the county town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remained a small market town and is today an attractive and flourishing little town with a variety of independent shops, private and public services, four churches and several public houses, and cafes despite its proximity to Langport and Ilchester. The railway cuts through the heart of the town but there is no longer a station, however most road traffic has been diverted away from the centre and its many historic buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See volume 3 of the Victoria County history of Somerset for a full history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2012 07:51:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20986 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
