<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Wiltshire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/county/wiltshire</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Highworth pot</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/highworth-pot</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Roman Highworth ceramic pot was discovered in the village of Highworth in June 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its location is just 4 miles away from &quot;Ermin Street&quot; which was a main Roman road which was a vital connection between the settlements of Gloucester, Silchester and Circencester. The pot was found with other smaller Roman artefacts and was positioned in an upright position suggesting it had been placed in the pit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is of a significant heavy weight as it takes several people to lift. The pot measures 2ft tall by 1 1/2 feet wide, with a 12 inch diameter mouth. The pot was used for storing milk this has been proven by the residue. It is going to be put on display in the Swindon Museum and Art Gallery.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 18:57:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21548 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Wiltshire and Swindon History Centre</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/wiltshire-and-swindon-history-centre</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Wiltshire and Swindon History Centre is located in Chippenham. It holds a vast amount of material on the history of Wiltshire and Swindon. It is open to members of the public who are interested in tracing ancestors, the history of their parish or town, educational projects and other heritage based matters. The centre holds over 40,000 photographs of the county as well as newspapers dating back to the 18th century and detailed maps from 1773 to the present day. These show changes in infrastructure and population density of all Wiltshire settlements. The Centre has different departments which are accessible to all. These include archives, local studies, archaeology, conservation, Wiltshire Buildings Record and the Victoria County History.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WSHC is open Tuesday to Friday 9.30am – 5.30pm and then 9.30am – 5.00pm each week and more details are provided on their website: www.wiltshire.gov.uk/history-centre.htm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 15:50:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21410 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Amesbury Industry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/amesbury-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the 17th century Amesbury was an important centre for the manufacture of clay pipes, quality of its products became famous far beyond the local needs it provided. Earliest known example of a “fox” pipe (believed to have been made here) names of four pipe makers are recorded as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Edward Fox&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Robert Smith&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Gabriel Bayley&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Gabriel Gauntlet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two early writers speak favourably of Gauntlet pipes – “&lt;em&gt;the best tobacco pipes in England” – &lt;/em&gt;Aubrey and “&lt;em&gt;the best for shape &amp;amp; colour” – &lt;/em&gt;Fuller&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amesbury attracted the industry due to the vast local supplies. A quarry has since been found showing the rich clay in the local soil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:52:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21409 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Amesbury Agriculture </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/amesbury-agriculture</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the later 12th century the demesne of Amesbury manor included several pastures for cattle and in the early 13th century extensive several pastures for sheep. Nearly all of Amesbury’s other land including some meadow &amp;amp; pasture for cattle was evidently used in common. Until the arrival of military establishments in the 20th century, agriculture was the mainstay of the Amesbury economy &amp;amp; the principal occupation. Before 1750 the pattern of agriculture had changed little for centuries the large common fields still being known by their medieval names and still divided into acres. Enclosure was not carried out by act of parliament at Amesbury so cannot be pinned down to a single date. The whole of Amesbury was controlled by one landowner, the duke of Queensberry and he was free to enclose his land without legal sanction. It is clear that the majority of the manor was enclosed between 1742 &amp;amp; 1771.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1771 most land owned by the manor had been divided between 6 farms in order of size; Red House farm, South Ham farm, Earl’s farm, Countess Court farm, West Amesbury farm and Kent House farm. Along with the abbey mansion controlled 5105 acres of pasture, meadowland and arable land. In 1824 only 4 farms remained. Incorporation of South Ham into Red House and parts of Kent House into Countess and west Amesbury. Increased efficiency of agriculture in 19th century caused by enclosure, machinery and irrigation. The controlled flooding created early grass crops which led to more fertile soil. In more recent years competition from abroad killed off the profit to be made in farming.           &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:43:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21408 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Amesbury Church </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/amesbury-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Church of St Mary &amp;amp; St Melor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Church of the abbey dissolved in 1177; it had a central tower, north transept (with east chapel), south transept, and nave (with south aisle). Nave is of earlier 12th century while the remainder was built in the early 13th century. In the late 15th century much of the church was reroofed and a new east/west window was inserted. In 1852/3 the church was restored to designs by William Butterfield, he intended to remove all features later than 1400. The east window was replaced by one in a 13th century style. In the south transept the early 18th century windows were replaced by lancets similar to 13th century ones.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Records have been kept from the church in baptisms from 1624-40 and then from 1660 onwards, burials from 1610-36 and then from 1660 onwards and marriages 1610 – 39 and then from 1661 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:36:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21407 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Amesbury Markets and Fairs</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/amesbury-markets-and-fairs</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thursday market was granted in 1219 &amp;amp; 1252 to the lord of Amesbury manor, Saturday market in 1317 to Amesbury priory, Wednesday market in 1614 to the lord of the Ealdon &amp;amp; Priory manors although unlikely that Amesbury ever had more than one weekly market; evidently a general market for food &amp;amp; agricultural produce. In 1635 weekly market held on Fridays, market house stood at the west end of the market place. 1759 market house was repaired &amp;amp; taken down in 1809 – it was not revived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 3 day fair at the fest of St Melor, (patron saint of church) granted in 1252 to the lord Amesbury manor, similar festival but different days were granted in 1317 to Amesbury priory. St Melor’s day is 1st October but the fair was probably held on and about the date of 6th may. 2 new fairs to be held on 11th June &amp;amp; 23rd December were granted to Lord Hertford in 1614. Also May fair, long fair and short fair continued into the 19th century. After 1752 May fair held on the 17th long fair on 22nd/23rd June and short fair held on 17th December, from 1760 later on the first Wednesday after the 12th December. In 1830 fairs were for trade in cattle &amp;amp; horses, in 1842 they were poorly attended and by 1888 had been discontinued.     &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:20:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21406 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Amesbury Airfield</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/amesbury-airfield</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stonehenge airfield landing ground between the Shrewton &amp;amp; Exeter roads west of Stonehenge was opened in 1917 for training bomber pilots. Hangers and other buildings were erected north &amp;amp; south of the Exeter road. The airfield was closed in 1920, some of the buildings were used for farming and all had been demolished by the 1930’s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blackcross down south east of the town Boscombe Down (initially red house farm) airfield was opened in 1917 for training pilots. Buildings were erected by 1918 extended in 1919 but the airfield was closed in 1920. Reopened in 1930 and was used mostly by bomber squadrons until 1939 when the aeroplane &amp;amp; armament experimental moved there. The evaluation establishment was still at Boscombe down in 1992, main work was to test aeroplanes &amp;amp; weapons. The airfield was greatly expanded after WWII new buildings were erected in the 1950’s. By 1937 9 houses in Allington way and had been erected for commissioned officers, 4 in main road for warrant officers and 33 in lamber road and main road for airmen. After WWII several housing estates were built on the west side of the airfield.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 14:16:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21405 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Trowbridge Industry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/trowbridge-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The town was held by Brictric, a Saxon in 1086 after his father had held it at the conquest of William the conqueror in 1066. Brictric was the most important Saxon landowner in Wiltshire therefore showing us that Trowbridge was a desirable settlement to own in this period of time. The settlement had increased economic activity in the 13th century as the building of the castle, the holding of honour courts, the presence of a garrison and at times of the baron and his retinue all were an economic burden on the settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The town’s staple trade is the cloth industry and it began in the 15th century although the prosperity of this trade would last several centuries. John Leland came to Trowbridge shortly after 1543 he was impressed by the towns trade when he stated ‘the towne flourishith by drapery.’ The prosperity of certain individuals at this time can be realised when looking at the vast personal wealth that they held. When Thomas Bailey, a clothman died in 1543 he left 1000 marks to his wife and vestments to the churches of Wingfield and Keevil. The quality of his grand house also needs to be considered as his fine timber-framed house survived for four centuries after his death; it was located in Fore Street.        &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cloth industry continued to be the town’s main employment trade into the 20th century and mills sprung up in and around the town. Trowbridge was known as the Manchester of the west and exported its cloth worldwide. Unfortunately the industry declined in the later 20th century and the mills was demolished and they could no longer achieve a profit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 12:43:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21403 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Trowbridge Chartists</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/trowbridge-chartists</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chartism was nationwide movement for voting reform in Victorian England. The first Chartist demonstration in Trowbridge took place on the 19th November 1838 when 3000 people marched by torchlight from the disused barracks to the town centre. The absence of the military from the town encouraged the chartists to hold large meetings of men and women there in 1839. The influence of the notable Trowbridge Chartist William Carrier made the town the centre of Wiltshire’s Chartism, before he was arrested on 7th June 1839.  In the winter of 1839-40 collections were raised for the Chartists and their causes. In 1842, 2 delegates from Trowbridge were sent to the universal suffrage conference in Birmingham and Fergus O Conner the leader of the Chartists visited Trowbridge himself. The last recorded meeting of the chartists was in November 1845 before the movement died out after contributing to the growth of political democracy.                &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 12:00:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21402 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Benjamin Lansdown</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/benjamin-lansdown-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Benjamin Lansdown was born in Trowbridge in 1819 and was the son of a woollen mill employee. Benjamin did not enjoy this line of work; so he was apprenticed as a printer with Mr John Sweet, the Trowbridge printer whose grandfather Edward had set up the first printing press in the town around 1760. In 1853 he took over his former masters business buying his hard press and type for £12 10s 0d. In the following year he started his newspaper The Wiltshire Times in his printing shop on Church Street. He established a newspaper and stationer shop at number 6 Silver Street in 1860 and moved his printing shop to Duke Street in 1876. Before his death in 1884 he had taken his sons James and George into partnership.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2013 11:20:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21401 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
