<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Dunster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/dunster</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s Migrants</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-migrants</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Dunster&#039;s economy rose and fell people came and went. Most migration was from Ireland and Wales but also from Flanders in the medieval and early modern period. After the loss of the cloth industry the young especially left in search of a better life in London, Australia, Canada and south Wales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 10:04:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23552 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s water supplies</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-water-supplies</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Water is not only vital for life and domestic comfort but for centuries was the main source of power for much of England&#039;s industry. It has always been a source of dispute over ownership, availability, cost and pollution. Once used water also presents problems of disposal and has itself long been used to dispose of waste. Dunster preserves a surprsing amount of evidence of the history of its water supplies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 10:03:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23067 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Street Lighting in Minehead and Dunster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/street-lighting-minehead-and-dunster</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We take street lighting for granted but it was slow to reach many parts of Britain and some communities have never had street lighting and do not desire it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the mid 19th century the area’s growing popularity with visitors, often from towns where street lighting was commonplace, probably fuelled demands for lighting in the area. One of the main reasons for creating the Minehead Gas Light and Coke Company in 1868 was to provide street lighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minehead is fortunate is having many preserved early street lamp standards both gas and electric.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 10:22:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23045 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s market and fair</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-market-and-fair</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before 1800 Dunster had the most important market in West Somerset serving a wide area of the Brendons and Exmoor as well as the coastal communities. In the 16th century it was ‘very celebrate’ and traders came from a wide area including Milverton, 14 miles to the south-east. By the early 17th century traders from Taunton and even Bodmin in Cornwall thought it worth their while to come to Dunster market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 13:47:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22858 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster surnames</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunster-surnames</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The people of medieval Dunster came from many places, which has left traces in their surnames. A list of burgesses in 1266 is very revealing about how origins, occupations and other characteristics gave rise to surnames.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 14:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22840 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s cloth industry</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-cloth-industry</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cloth was woven at Dunster by 1266 and cloths known as Dunsters were exported from the mid 16th century. Local sheep, and later Welsh and Irish wool, sustained an industry that must have employed many people from carders and spinners to weavers and finishers and even retailers and garment makers.&lt;/p&gt;
 
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2014 10:11:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22800 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s streets</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-streets</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dunster is a compact settlement west of the Avill and the Tor between Grabbist Hill to the south and Conygar Hill to the north and seems to have developed as an urban settlement without farmsteads. Dunster was not walled but had bars recorded from 1266 last recorded in 1502.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High Street has the appearance of a planned borough with a broad market and was possibly part of a medieval created landscape with an alignment chosen to give attractive views as well as enabling the castle to dominate the town and market below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several streets were densely packed with houses by the late Middle Ages although there were a few gardens recorded. Houses recorded in the early 18th century comprised three rooms below and three chambers above but none appears to have been single storey. Several, especially inns, had three storeys.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 11:24:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22476 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster and civil war</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunster-and-civil-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dunster was held for the Crown in the 1640s and was the last Royalist stronghold.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 12:29:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22277 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster in the First World War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunster-first-world-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like most communities Dunster suffered heavy losses in the First World war although at least one man survived only to die during the Second World War.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 12:11:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22274 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster in the Second World War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunster-second-world-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dunster&#039;s community was heavily engaged during the war with soldiers at Dunster Beach, coastal defences and civil defence besides feeding servicemen locally and overseas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 11:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22271 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
