<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Late Medieval (1398-1485)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/period/late-medieval-1398-1485</link>
 <description>1398-1485</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Bailiff&#039;s accounts for the manor of Down Hatherley, 1428-9</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/bailiffs-accounts-manor-down-hatherley-1428-9</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Cheltenham Local History Society Latin Group&lt;p&gt;A stray roll of bailiff&#039;s accounts for the manor of Down Hatherley 1428-9, including an indenture for the lease of the manor for 6 years by Katherine Beauchamp to William Wyllyes of Twigworth, Glos.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;PDF icon&quot; title=&quot;application/pdf&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/application-pdf.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2019/02/10/hatherley_court_7_henry_vi_10_feb_final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=591350&quot;&gt;hatherley_court_7_henry_vi_10_feb_final.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 21:22:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25685 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Down Hatherley manorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/down-hatherley-manorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Down Hatherley is a rural parish to the west of Cheltenham&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 21:19:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25684 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Queen Camel font</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/queen-camel-font</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Queen Camel font&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Many if not most of the people recorded in the vicar&#039;s book would have been born in the parish and baptised in this 15th-century font. The older ones would have lived through the religious turbulence that may have seen the defacing of the images on it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2015/09/11/qc_font2.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=677320&quot;&gt;qc_font2.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 08:04:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24658 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Tendring Level (Holland Haven)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/tendring-level-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for sea defence and drainage in coastal regions since the early thirteenth century had been allocated to &lt;em&gt;ad hoc &lt;/em&gt;Commissions of walls and ditches (&lt;em&gt;de walliis et fossatiis&lt;/em&gt;) appointed by the Crown. The commissioners were officers who had powers to enforce local communal responsibilities for the maintenance of sea walls, banks and drains, and thus attempt to prevent flooding and the inroads of the sea. They could make local by-laws and raise rates to ensure the essential work was undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such commissioners for Tendring Hundred (equivalent to the modern Tendring district) were first recorded about 1450, when the abbot of St Osyth, John Godmanston, esq., John Green and Robert Tanfield and others were appointed. The powers of such royal Commissions was consolidated by Statute in 1531 in A General Act concerning Commissions of Sewers. This was enacted &#039;considering daily great damages and losses which have happened in many and diverse parts ... by reason of the outrageous flowing surges and course of the sea in and upon marsh grounds and other low places&#039;. Under the 1531 At the Commissions initially only lasted three years, but another Commissions of Sewers Act of 1571 later extended the term to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the Tendring commissioners met infrequently for information about the 15th and 16th centuries is scant, and the extent of the sea defences around the Gunfleet estuary and on the coastline of Great Holland, Little Holland and Frinton remains unknown. A reference to &#039;le level de Gunfletehaven&#039; in 1542 may indicate that some drainage activity had taken place, for the word &#039;level&#039; was often used of partly reclaimed marshlands of the type protected by the activities of commissioners. Other examples of the use of the word are the Somerset Levels and the Gwent Levels of south-east Wales. A document concerning poaching at Little Holland in 1609 referred to &#039;a drowned land called the Flatts&#039;, and the same term was used as an alternative for the Tendring Level in 1703.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would seem that the gradual silting up of the Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook or River that fed it necessitated a response from the commissioners, probabaly stimulated by those whose livelihood was being affected by the flooding and perhaps the loss of trading opportunities. The response was a plan to make a sea wall across the estuary between Little Holland and Frinton, and thus reclaim by drainage the former estuary. It is not known precisely when the sea wall was first constructed, but it appears to have been sometime in the 17th century. A survey of the Tendring Level after the Great Storm of 1703 mentioned a &#039;breach&#039; that had been made, suggesting that the sea wall existed by that date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sluice was included in the new wall which could be opned at low tide to allow the river watre to escape, the sluice gate then being closed to prevent th rising tide from entering and flooding the newly won marshes. The original sluice was at Sandy Point near Frinton which seems to have been the natural outfall of the river water from the Holland Brook, although it was later moved east to the site of the present sluice at Holland Haven. As a result many hundreds of acres of land were reclaimed in the parishes of Great Holland, Little Holland, Frinton, Great Clacton, Little Clacton and Thorpe-le-Soken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K. Walker, &#039;The battle of the Clacton peninsula. Man versus the sea&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Essex Review&lt;/em&gt;, Volume LXIV (1955), pp.103-11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1935), p. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Yelloly Watson, &lt;em&gt;The Tendring Hundred in the Olden Time &lt;/em&gt;(1877), p. 70-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/DHw E14: A true survey of ye Levell or Flatts (1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, Q/SR 189/25: Quarter Sessions, pocahing case, 1609.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, Catalogue explanations under references C191, C225, C226.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 11:48:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24095 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rice bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rice-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rice bridge is the earliest recorded crossing point on the river now known as the Holland Brook, and one of the furthest inland. It was in existence by 1319 when an Agnes de Risbregge (Agnes of Rice Bridge) was recorded in a taxation return for Little Clacton. Her name probably meant that she lived at or near the bridge. The bridge also gave its name to the surrounding land as an estate called Risbridge or Rosebridge was recorded in the later 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bridge was built on a route that was probably locally important in the Middle Ages. Not ony did it connect the two parishes of Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, but also the manors on either side of the river that were owned by the bishop pf London and his cathedral church of St Paul&#039;s. In the Domesday Book of 1086 the bishop held the manor of Clacton (comprising both Great Clacton and Little Clacton)  while all of Thorpe-le-Soken, Kirby-le-Soken and Walton-le-Soken were held by the Dean and Chapter of St Paul&#039;s (the cathderal clergy). By 1127 on one side of the bridge lay Little Clacton park, a deerpark owned by the bishop, while on the other side lay Thope park, a deerpark owned by the Dean and Chapter. The road over Rice bridge therefore connected the two church estates and their hunting parks. Possiby the huntsmen ranged across both parks quite freely, otherwise the deer could have swum across the river to safety!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name Rice bridge is itself very informative, as it probably originates in the Old English words &#039;hris&#039; (meaning brushwood) and &#039;brycg&#039; (meaning bridge or causeway). The crossing may therefore have started out as a timber bridge or causeway and it probably continued in that form for many centuries. In 1612 the tenants of Thorpe Park and Clacton Park were ordered to &#039;make&#039; the bridge (perhaps from timber available in the deer parks), and it was still described as a wooden footbridge in 1783. County maps from 1594 and 1603 show a main road from Little Clacton and Weeley towards Thorpe, Kirby and Walton that crossed the Holland River at what must be Rice bridge, although it was not named. A survey of the Holland Levels by the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs in 1703 named Rice bridge, and many maps from the 18th century such as that by Chapman and Andre in 1777 show the same route. The present brick built Rice bridge dates from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (Cambridge, 1935), p. 336.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P. Morant, The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex (1768), Volume II, p. 475.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M. Gibbs (ed), The Early Charters of St Paul&#039;s (Camden Society, 3rd series, lviii, 1939), no. 60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London Metropolitan Archive, Guildhall Library, MS. 25416/3; MS. 9531/6, f.192v.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), Q/SR 199/79, 154, 155 (Quarter Sessions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/DHw E14 (A true survey of ye Levll or Flatts ... several parcells of land endamaged at or near Gun-Fleet Haven, 1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 20 (Map of part of Tendring Level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 17:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24006 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ridge and furrow in Leire</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ridge-and-furrow-leire-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Ridge and furrow in Leire&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2015/04/24/leire_ridgefurrow_snow.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2723464&quot;&gt;leire_ridgefurrow_snow.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 10:30:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23936 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Estuary and Holland Haven</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-estuary-and-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet was the name of the large estuary fed by the Holland River or brook, which formerly ran into the sea between Frinton and Little Holland. The name is probably Anglo-Saxon in origin, as the second element ‘fleet’ is derived from the Old English word fleot meaning ‘stream’ or ‘creek’. A similar well known example is the River Fleet in London, a tributary of the River Thames which was fed by streams on Hampstead Heath and which used to have a tidal inlet and docks at its lower end. The origin of the first element of the name ‘Gun’ is currently unknown, but it possibly derived from an Anglo-Saxon personal name, so the meaning of the whole name could be something like ‘Gunna’s creek’. An alternative suggestion that has been made is that the first part of the name could be a corruption from the Count of Guisnes who possessed the manor of Little Holland in 1210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the name was not recorded until 1320 when a vessel was shipwrecked on ‘Gunfletsond’, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. It seems probable that a name originally applying to the estuary was appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary’s inlet. A map of 1584 in the British Library marks both the ‘Gonflet haven’ (the estuary) and the ‘ye gonflit’ (the sandbank). Other maps from that period, such as maps of Essex by Norden (1594) and Speed (1610) show the Gunfleet as a large, unreclaimed, estuary that was open to the sea at its southern end. The use of the name ‘haven’ would seem to imply the use of the estuary for trade, and the ‘Ganflete’ was also named as a port between Walton and St Osyth in Holinshed’s Chronicles (1586). The substantial marshlands along the estuary were also used by the inhabitants of surrounding parishes like Great and Little Holland as grazing for their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1542 ‘the level of Gunflete haven’ was recorded, perhaps indicating that estuary’s marshland later known as Holland Levels had started to be reclaimed. Although the estuary continued to be marked on coastal maps and sea charts for a long time, it was becoming blocked perhaps by the effects of coastal erosion and long-shore drift. In 1677 a whale was stranded in the narrows at what was probably the entrance to the Gunfleet estuary then described as a ‘creek’. Probably soon afterwards it was decided to reclaim the estuary by constructing a sea wall across its mouth, with a sluice provided to allow the river water to drain away to sea. The intention was to prevent salt water entering the marshes along the Holland River, and thus to improve their agricultural potential and value. It is not known when the first wall was built, but in 1703 a survey was taken of ‘ye Levell or Flatts being several pieces or parcells of land endamaged by a breach at, or near Gunfleet Haven’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The records of the Tendring Levels Commissioners, a type of local government body charged with flood defence, survive from 1727 and show how they maintained the drained marshlands of the level, the sea wall and the sluice through which the Holland River then emptied into the open sea. By the 1760s the area was sufficiently drained to allow a new road link to cross the former estuary from Holland on Sea to Great Holland, although the extensive tracts of land were still liable to flood as shown by the marshes depicted on the Chapman and André map of 1777 and the one inch Ordnance Survey map (1838 edition). The Commissioners continued to be responsible for maintaining the sea wall and the Levels until the 1930s, and their maps reveal the outline of the old estuary through the land that had to pay rates to maintain the sea defences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (1935), pp.13–17. K. Walker, various notes. Calendar of Close Rolls, Edw. II, A.D. 1318–23 (HMSO, 1895), p.249. Holinshed, An Historicall Description of the Iland of Britaine (1586), Book I, Chapter XVII: Of such ports and creeks as our sea-faring men doo note for their benefit upon the coasts of England. British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584) J. Norden, Speculi Britanniae Pars (1594), ed. H. Ellis (Camden Society, London, 1840), map. J. Speed, Map of Essex (1610) J. Chapman and P. André, A Map of Essex (1777). Ordnance Survey map, 1” to 1 Mile (1838) Essex Record Office, D/DHw E14, ‘A true Survey of ye Levell or Flatts’, 1703. ERO, D/ST 1 to 6, Tendring Levels Commissioners, minute books, 1727–1932 ERO, D/ST 17 to 20, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps, 1783 ERO, T/M 565/1, 2, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps c.1901–25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 13:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Kilkhampton church interior</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/kilkhampton-church-interior</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Kilkhampton church interior&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;The tall perpendicular arcades give an imporession of great height and lightness to the church interior. There is a good set of 16th-century benches similar to those at Launcells [qv] and a font of similar date as are the church doors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2014/09/29/kilkhampton_church_interior_22_sep_2014.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1785533&quot;&gt;kilkhampton_church_interior_22_sep_2014.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 15:37:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23100 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Wall painting of St Christopher in Poughill church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/wall-painting-st-christopher-poughill-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Poughill church St Christopher&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;The church contains wall paintings that may have 15th century origins but have been entirely repainted by Frank Sailsbury. This painting of St Christopher is on the north wall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2014/09/29/poughill_ch_st_christopher_wall_painting_23_sep_2014.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1693323&quot;&gt;poughill_ch_st_christopher_wall_painting_23_sep_2014.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 14:38:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23095 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Poughill church interior</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/poughill-church-interior</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Poughill church interior&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Most of Poughill church is Perpendicular dating from the 15th century but the north aisle is probably older. The arcades were built largely of Caen stone. The early 16th-century bench ends carry symbols of the passion. The 15th-century waggon roofs survive with carved bosses and wallplates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2014/09/29/poughill_church_arcades_23_sep_2014.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1498861&quot;&gt;poughill_church_arcades_23_sep_2014.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 14:24:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23094 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
