<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Little Holland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/little-holland</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Sands and Channel</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-sands-and-channel</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet sandbank lies off the coastline of Tendring district, directly opposite (east) of the entrance to the former Gunfleet estuary (also known as Gunfleet Haven or Holland Haven). Between the sandbank and the coast was a protected channel and anchorage, but the dangers of the sands have long been known to mariners and large numbers of vessels and their crews have been shipwrecked there over the centuries. From at least the 17th century the sands have been marked by buoys and also by a beacon or lighthouse. In recent years the Gunfleet Sandbank has been used as the site of an off-shore wind farm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name &#039;Gunfleet&#039; was first recorded in 1318 when a vessel was shipwrecked on &#039;Gunfletsond&#039;, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. In the reign of Henry VIII (1509-1542) the &#039;Gonflete&#039; was also recorded as a sandbank, and a map of 1584 marks both the &#039;Gonflet Haven&#039; (the estuary) and &#039;ye gonflit&#039; (the sandbank). Thus the name of the estuary had clearly been appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary&#039;s inlet. The safer water between the sands and the inlet, now known as the Wallet, also seem to have been commonly known as the Gunfleet in the later 17th century when the English or Dutch fleets anchored there during the Dutch Wars. Similar uses of place-names including &#039;fleet&#039; for coastal channels can be found elsewhere, a good example being the Fleet in Dorset, a long narrow channel separated from the English Channel by the major sandbank known as Chesil Bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the former estuary was reclaimed for agriculture from the late 17th century onwards, so the original name was largely forgotten on land and replaced by the name Holland Haven. But off of the coastline the name has been preserved as the Gunfleet Sands into the 21st century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s map of Essex (1594).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1935), pp. 13-17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lt.-Co. A.R. Solly, &#039;Gunfleet - Haven, Anchorage and Sand&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Essex Review&lt;/em&gt;, LX (1951), pp.203-06.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 10:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24236 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Barton&#039;s Pans</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bartons-pans</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Barton&#039;s Pans lie immediately behind the line of the sea wall built by the Tendring Level Commissioners across the mouth of the Gunfleet estuary. They are located from just west of Chevaux de Frise point running east to Holland Gap towards Frinton. They take the form of rectangular pits, lagoons or pools, filled with water and overgrown with reeds. At least 24 separate pits were shown on an Ordnance Survey map of 1898, and although some have now disappeared or shrunk they are still a very prominent landscape feature. They are not modern because they were mentioned in the Tendring Level Commissioners Minute Book of 1782, as follows: &lt;em&gt;&quot;That part of the wall adjoining to a place called Bartons Pans wants strengthening and heightening and footing for near three hundred yards in length, and that water from the said pans ought to be drained at all times from out of the same.&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission&#039;s map of the Level from 1783 also marks the location of the Pans, while the Commissioners minutes from 1786 notes that the sea wall next to Barton&#039;s Pans was &quot;&lt;em&gt;by the violence of the sea becoming ruinous, defcetive and out of repair.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;The &#039;Pans&#039; are also depicted on a military survey of Holland Marsh in 1805 (part of the defence planning aginst the threat of invasion by Napoleon Bonaparte&#039;s French army), being shown as lying between Chevaux de Frise Point and Sandy Point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitherto the &#039;Pans&#039; do not appear to have been studied, and their origin and purpose is shrouded in mystery. One hypothesis proposed is that material for the earliest sea walls was excavated from them. However, this explanation has not appeared fully convincing. Would suitable material have been available for excavation at the mouth of the old estuary? Also some of the &#039;Pans&#039; depicted on maps also seem too regular in form (rectangular), and at the eastern and western ends do not precisely conform to the line of the sea wall. Other suggestions have been that they represent salt-pans (where salt was produced by heating or evaporation) or oyster-layings or tanks (where the young oyster brood were matured). However,no local documentary evidence has been found of either of these industries on such a large-scale as this site would imply. Also, before the sea wal, the &#039;Pans&#039; would have lain on the open coast in the mouth of the Gunfleet estuary, probably not a suitable site for either salt or oyster production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The explanation that currently seems most attractive is that the &#039;Pans&#039; are evidence of the Copperas industry which we know was locally important in the 17th and 18th centuries. Copperas was the name for green vitriol that was manufactured from nodules of bisulphide of iron (otherwise known as pyrites) washed out of the London Clay cliffs onto the shore. It was used for various purposes such as dyes, fixatives and inks. Copperas stones were collected by the local poor people all along the coast from Clacton, Frinton and Walton, and also dredged up from the Copperas Bank off the coast. There were several methods of production, but in one system the Copperas stones were heaped into large open vats or pits full of water and exposed to the elements for a period of time (sometimes several years) before being removed to undergo various manufacturing processes at Coppers Houses, of which there were important local ones at Walton and Brightlingsea, and possibly another one at Frinton. Perhaps Barton&#039;s Pans were established for the Copperas industry after the sea wall was built towards the end of the 17th century?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further evidence that may link Barton&#039;s Pans with the industry comes from the surviving Tokens with which the local poor - the &quot;Copperas pickers&quot; - were paid, and the names of the local landowners who issued them. Tokens survive that were issued by John Kirby at Walton dated 1736, and it seems probable that he was related to the Kirby family who through marriage obtained Great Holland Manor in the later 18th century. A map of 1777 indicates that a track led from Great Holland Hall directly to Barton&#039;s Pans. Copperas also appears to have been collected at Frinton from the mid 17th century onwards, and as early as 1637 the lord of the manor, Sir Harbottle Grimston, was involved in the industry. In 1746 the right to gather Copperas still belonged to Frinton manor, and the lessee of the manor named John Rice minted tokens to pay workers both at Frinton and at &#039;Minster&#039; - either Minster in Thanet or Minster in Sheppey (both in Kent). John Rice&#039;s local involvement is particularly revealing as he may only have taken the lease of the manor to acquire its Copperas rights, as he is probably the same John Rice of Deptford (Kent) who was a member of one of the leading families involved with the industry in Kent and Essex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/ST 2: Tendring Level Commission, Minute Book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 17: Map of the Tendringlevel by W. Cole (1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, T/A 15/2/2; ERO, D/DWv/T80; ERO D/UFw C9/23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, Map of Essex (1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, MPHH 1/548: Major Bryce&#039;s Survey of Holland Marsh, October 1805.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J.C. Shenstone, &#039;Copperas Industry&#039;, in W. Page and J.H. Round (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Victoria Historyof the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, Vol. II (1907), pp. 411-13.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T. Allen, M. Cotterill and G. Pike, &lt;em&gt;Copperas. An account of the Whitstable Works and the first industrial-scale chemical production in England&lt;/em&gt; (Canterbury Archaeological Trust, Occasional paper, No. 2, 2004), pp. 32, 37-8.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 12:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24107 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Tendring Level (Holland Haven)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/tendring-level-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for sea defence and drainage in coastal regions since the early thirteenth century had been allocated to &lt;em&gt;ad hoc &lt;/em&gt;Commissions of walls and ditches (&lt;em&gt;de walliis et fossatiis&lt;/em&gt;) appointed by the Crown. The commissioners were officers who had powers to enforce local communal responsibilities for the maintenance of sea walls, banks and drains, and thus attempt to prevent flooding and the inroads of the sea. They could make local by-laws and raise rates to ensure the essential work was undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such commissioners for Tendring Hundred (equivalent to the modern Tendring district) were first recorded about 1450, when the abbot of St Osyth, John Godmanston, esq., John Green and Robert Tanfield and others were appointed. The powers of such royal Commissions was consolidated by Statute in 1531 in A General Act concerning Commissions of Sewers. This was enacted &#039;considering daily great damages and losses which have happened in many and diverse parts ... by reason of the outrageous flowing surges and course of the sea in and upon marsh grounds and other low places&#039;. Under the 1531 At the Commissions initially only lasted three years, but another Commissions of Sewers Act of 1571 later extended the term to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the Tendring commissioners met infrequently for information about the 15th and 16th centuries is scant, and the extent of the sea defences around the Gunfleet estuary and on the coastline of Great Holland, Little Holland and Frinton remains unknown. A reference to &#039;le level de Gunfletehaven&#039; in 1542 may indicate that some drainage activity had taken place, for the word &#039;level&#039; was often used of partly reclaimed marshlands of the type protected by the activities of commissioners. Other examples of the use of the word are the Somerset Levels and the Gwent Levels of south-east Wales. A document concerning poaching at Little Holland in 1609 referred to &#039;a drowned land called the Flatts&#039;, and the same term was used as an alternative for the Tendring Level in 1703.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would seem that the gradual silting up of the Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook or River that fed it necessitated a response from the commissioners, probabaly stimulated by those whose livelihood was being affected by the flooding and perhaps the loss of trading opportunities. The response was a plan to make a sea wall across the estuary between Little Holland and Frinton, and thus reclaim by drainage the former estuary. It is not known precisely when the sea wall was first constructed, but it appears to have been sometime in the 17th century. A survey of the Tendring Level after the Great Storm of 1703 mentioned a &#039;breach&#039; that had been made, suggesting that the sea wall existed by that date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sluice was included in the new wall which could be opned at low tide to allow the river watre to escape, the sluice gate then being closed to prevent th rising tide from entering and flooding the newly won marshes. The original sluice was at Sandy Point near Frinton which seems to have been the natural outfall of the river water from the Holland Brook, although it was later moved east to the site of the present sluice at Holland Haven. As a result many hundreds of acres of land were reclaimed in the parishes of Great Holland, Little Holland, Frinton, Great Clacton, Little Clacton and Thorpe-le-Soken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K. Walker, &#039;The battle of the Clacton peninsula. Man versus the sea&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Essex Review&lt;/em&gt;, Volume LXIV (1955), pp.103-11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1935), p. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Yelloly Watson, &lt;em&gt;The Tendring Hundred in the Olden Time &lt;/em&gt;(1877), p. 70-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/DHw E14: A true survey of ye Levell or Flatts (1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, Q/SR 189/25: Quarter Sessions, pocahing case, 1609.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, Catalogue explanations under references C191, C225, C226.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 11:48:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24095 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland Brook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-brook-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Holland Brook, sometimes called the Holland River, has been rather overlooked as an important landscape feature of Tendring Hundred (the older name for Tendring district). Even the original name of the watercourse is uncertain, although as the Holland Brook fed into the Gunfleet estuary that may record the original name of the river - the Gunfleet. The names Gunfleet Haven and Holland Haven both seem to refer to the original estuary that was later permanently reclaimed from the sea by the Tendring Levels Commissioners in the 17th and 18th centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brook was regarded as important enough for its course to be described in versions of Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles dating from 1577 and 1587: &quot;Betwixt the Naze also and the mouth of the Colne, is another Ryll which riseth at Little Bentley, and thence goeth to Tendryng thorpe, thorow Clacten parke by great Holland, and east of little Holland into the deepe sea&quot;. The accurate description draws attention to the length of the watercoruse or &#039;rill&#039; from its source near Little Bentley and Little Bromley down to the sea at Little Holland, which virtually divided Tendring Hundred in half. Several features are worthy of note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the original Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook and its valley probably provided an important access route from the coast into the interior of Tendring Hundred both in prehistoric and later periods. There is considerable evidence from cropmarks for early settlement around the upper reaches of the brook in Tendring and neighbouring parishes. The brook may also have had an influence upon the later Anglo-Saxon and medieval patterns of settlement. It may, for example, be no coincidence that the brook leads to the parish of Tendring, which was the central place of the Hundred (the Hundred assembly met on Tendring Heath), and which name is probaby derived from a place-name in Germany transferred to this location by Anglo-Saxon migrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the Holland Brook and the Gunfleet estuary later provided a considerable barrier to east-west road communications. A number of bridges were therefore eventually established, presumably starting furthest inland where the watercourse could be more easily bridged. That at Rice bridge, between Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, seems to have been present by the 14th century. Further downstream that at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, was first recorded in 1509, and that at Holland bridge, between Great and Little Holland, in 1727 (after the former estuary had been reclaimed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the Holland brook and Gunfleet estuary were fed by a number of smaller streams in the parishes along their route, and the system effectively drained much of the centre of Tendring Hundred and many thousands of acres of farmland. Some of the tributary streams were quite small, but others like Picker&#039;s Ditch leading west from the Gunfleet towards Great Clacton were quite substantial. The potential for flooding was therefore very large, and after the Gunfleet or Holland Haven was reclaimed as marshland pasture by the Tendring Levels Commissioners they had to work hard expending money and enforcing maintenance upon local landowners to keep the channels clear so as to prevent major flooding incidents. Even in winter today the course of the brook and the old estuary is often marked by the flooded marshlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(Cambridge, 1935), 17, 325, 351-2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map of Tendring Hundred from P. Morant, &lt;em&gt;The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, I (1768).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles: http://www.english.ox.ac.uk/holinshed/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Explore Asset under this heading: Map of land liable to flood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See other Explore Items on Rice bridge; Fan bridge; Holland bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 10:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24091 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Holland bridge is the most recent bridge to cross the Holland River (or Holland Brook), and the furthest downstream. Maps of 1594 and 1603 indicate that there was no route at that time across the Gunfleet estuary which would therefore have still formed a major barrier to land communications along the coast. Then the first crossing point was at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, some one and a half to two miles inland from the sea. As a result, there was probably much communication in small boats across the Gunfleet estuary and along the coast in the sheltered waters of the Gunfleet Channel (now known as the Wallet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, probably sometime towards the end of the 17th century the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs decided to construct a sea wall across the mouth of the estuary which was becoming silted up. As the former Gunfleet estuary behind the sea wall was converted to marshland pastures (although still liuable to winter flooding), so the course of the Holland River became channelled into a water way, now known as the Holland Brook, that ran through its lowest part. The river water, resulting from the many thousands of acres draining into the Holland Brook, was discharged into the sea via a sluice built in the new sea wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the reclamation works were considered advanced sufficiently, a causeway was built across the reclaimed land and a new bridge, named Little Holland bridge, was built over the brook. The date of the bridge is uncertain, but it was first recorded in 1727. The bridge was locally significant for it was the first time that a direct road communication existed between the settlements of Little Holland and Great Holland on the two sides of the old estuary. Chapman and Andre&#039;s map of Essex in 1777 shows the nature of the land half a century after the bridge was first built. A road led from Little Holland Hall into the marhses and then crossed the Holland brook by the new bridge before travelling northwards through the marshes and up the valley side towards Great Holland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach road to the bridge through the marshes in 1777 was depicted as a series of dashes indicating that the route was rather impermanet or uncertain and liable to flood. Chapman and Andre often depicted roads in this way when they crossed common land or where routes were poorly demarcated; another example is their map of the route through the marshes east of Fan bridge. The present Holland bridge appears to date from the early 20th century and until rceent years it had a metal sign indicating where the Great and Little Holland parish boundaries met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map, 1&quot; (1838).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/ST 20 (Map of part of TendrinG level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tednring Levels Commissioners&#039; Map (early 20th century; in private ownership).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 18:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24008 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Estuary and Holland Haven</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-estuary-and-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet was the name of the large estuary fed by the Holland River or brook, which formerly ran into the sea between Frinton and Little Holland. The name is probably Anglo-Saxon in origin, as the second element ‘fleet’ is derived from the Old English word fleot meaning ‘stream’ or ‘creek’. A similar well known example is the River Fleet in London, a tributary of the River Thames which was fed by streams on Hampstead Heath and which used to have a tidal inlet and docks at its lower end. The origin of the first element of the name ‘Gun’ is currently unknown, but it possibly derived from an Anglo-Saxon personal name, so the meaning of the whole name could be something like ‘Gunna’s creek’. An alternative suggestion that has been made is that the first part of the name could be a corruption from the Count of Guisnes who possessed the manor of Little Holland in 1210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the name was not recorded until 1320 when a vessel was shipwrecked on ‘Gunfletsond’, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. It seems probable that a name originally applying to the estuary was appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary’s inlet. A map of 1584 in the British Library marks both the ‘Gonflet haven’ (the estuary) and the ‘ye gonflit’ (the sandbank). Other maps from that period, such as maps of Essex by Norden (1594) and Speed (1610) show the Gunfleet as a large, unreclaimed, estuary that was open to the sea at its southern end. The use of the name ‘haven’ would seem to imply the use of the estuary for trade, and the ‘Ganflete’ was also named as a port between Walton and St Osyth in Holinshed’s Chronicles (1586). The substantial marshlands along the estuary were also used by the inhabitants of surrounding parishes like Great and Little Holland as grazing for their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1542 ‘the level of Gunflete haven’ was recorded, perhaps indicating that estuary’s marshland later known as Holland Levels had started to be reclaimed. Although the estuary continued to be marked on coastal maps and sea charts for a long time, it was becoming blocked perhaps by the effects of coastal erosion and long-shore drift. In 1677 a whale was stranded in the narrows at what was probably the entrance to the Gunfleet estuary then described as a ‘creek’. Probably soon afterwards it was decided to reclaim the estuary by constructing a sea wall across its mouth, with a sluice provided to allow the river water to drain away to sea. The intention was to prevent salt water entering the marshes along the Holland River, and thus to improve their agricultural potential and value. It is not known when the first wall was built, but in 1703 a survey was taken of ‘ye Levell or Flatts being several pieces or parcells of land endamaged by a breach at, or near Gunfleet Haven’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The records of the Tendring Levels Commissioners, a type of local government body charged with flood defence, survive from 1727 and show how they maintained the drained marshlands of the level, the sea wall and the sluice through which the Holland River then emptied into the open sea. By the 1760s the area was sufficiently drained to allow a new road link to cross the former estuary from Holland on Sea to Great Holland, although the extensive tracts of land were still liable to flood as shown by the marshes depicted on the Chapman and André map of 1777 and the one inch Ordnance Survey map (1838 edition). The Commissioners continued to be responsible for maintaining the sea wall and the Levels until the 1930s, and their maps reveal the outline of the old estuary through the land that had to pay rates to maintain the sea defences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (1935), pp.13–17. K. Walker, various notes. Calendar of Close Rolls, Edw. II, A.D. 1318–23 (HMSO, 1895), p.249. Holinshed, An Historicall Description of the Iland of Britaine (1586), Book I, Chapter XVII: Of such ports and creeks as our sea-faring men doo note for their benefit upon the coasts of England. British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584) J. Norden, Speculi Britanniae Pars (1594), ed. H. Ellis (Camden Society, London, 1840), map. J. Speed, Map of Essex (1610) J. Chapman and P. André, A Map of Essex (1777). Ordnance Survey map, 1” to 1 Mile (1838) Essex Record Office, D/DHw E14, ‘A true Survey of ye Levell or Flatts’, 1703. ERO, D/ST 1 to 6, Tendring Levels Commissioners, minute books, 1727–1932 ERO, D/ST 17 to 20, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps, 1783 ERO, T/M 565/1, 2, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps c.1901–25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 13:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
