<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Devon</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/ancient-county/devon</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>South Molton workhouse</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/south-molton-workhouse</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Original 1837 entrance building in North Road, South Molton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the new poor law of 1834 workhouses were to be built for groups of parishes known as poor-law unions. The Devon Exmoor parishes were placed in the South Molton union. South Molton workhouse was built in 1837 for 230 inmates though it usually held less than half that number.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Poor and elderly people who could not support themselves went to the workhouse. The children of lone women were often born there and abandoned children were brought up in the institution, which had its own school. The mentally ill were often placed in workhouses like a young woman from Dulverton and a brother and sister from West Anstey housed in South Molton workhouse in 1881.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more information on poverty and workhouses see &lt;a href=&quot;http://explore.englandspastforeveryone.org.uk/items/dulverton-workhouse&quot;&gt;Dulverton workhouse&lt;/a&gt; on this site.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11819 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Tis the Sheep hath paid for all</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/tis-sheep-hath-paid-all</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rams heads over the entrance to South Molton market.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wealth of Exmoor lay in its sheep and wool. South Molton was a cloth making and market town, which depended on the moors to provide the raw materials for its trades. The seal and arms of the old borough of South Molton included a fleece. Until the 19th century the markets were held in Broad Street. The market hall was built in 1863 and when the railway opened sheep and cattle markets were held in a field by the station. Fat lambs were bought at Simonsbath by butchers and dealers or driven to South Molton between August and November for slaughter and carriage to London hung in special meat vans. Exmoor hill lamb was said to be of superior flavour. It was from South Molton station that the famous rabbit trains set out to supply London poulterers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11808 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>West Anstey church, Devon</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/west-anstey-church-devon</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;em&gt;Interior of West Anstey church&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The church of St Petrock, West Anstey, dates largely from the 14th and 15th centuries but was heavily restored in 1879 by William White. The pulpit, altar and reredos date from that restoration but fragments of medieval glass survive in the south chancel window, there are a few medieval tiles and some good benchends. The church may have originally been built in 1319 when its altars were dedicated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11806 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>West Anstey Village</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/west-anstey-village</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Road to the church, West Anstey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even in the 21st century West Anstey village seems very isolated and not easy to access. It sits in a hollow of improved sheep pasture beside one of the lanes to the Anstey commons on the high moors. Apart from the Vicarage and Church Town Farm behind the church the village consists of a handful of cottages known as Anstey Town. In 1881 the village had its own postman and school, although the teacher shared the premises with a labouring family. Two cottages had been abandoned by 1901 when the others were occupied by a tailor, a labourer and a pauper. The vicar was still resident in 1901 with his family, governess, cook, housemaid, gardener and an Indian born boy who may have been his pupil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11805 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>North Molton church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/north-molton-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;  &lt;em&gt;North Molton church. The modest exterior belies its fine interior.&lt;/em&gt;   The church was entirely rebuilt in the late fifteenth century, probably funded by the wool and cloth trade. North Molton was an important manor in the Middle Ages and included Twitchen. It was described as a borough in 1238 and obtained a grant of a market and a fair in 1270 but its status was refuted in 1316. By the early 16th century it had a flourishing cloth trade and cloth merchants like the Parkers amassed great wealth.   The core of North Molton is the Square, a large open space where the fairs would have been held and to one side of which stands the church, and the long straggling East Street. Here are several fine houses originally of the early 18th century including Frayne house, Zeals, Castle Hill, and Jarman’s. Clearly the place was prosperous at that period as the churchyard contains some fine 18th-century chest tombs including those to the Moorner, Frayne, and Flemen families. There are a few earlier houses of quality such as the Bampfylde’s grand 1553 Court House or 17th-century Hillside View. In the 1730s parishioners paid for nearly 8,000 sheep to graze in the Exmoor forest, far more than any other community and a fifth of all the sheep in the forest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11791 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Molland emigrants</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/molland-emigrants</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A memorial to the tragic deaths of the Pincombe family from Molland who had set sail for Canada hoping for a better life.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11788 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Molland Village</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/molland-village</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Molland together with Anstey and Withypool commons, create an escarpment which lies between the river Barle, and the Devon Yeo, straddling the county boundary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mid 11th century, Molland was a very important manor, perhaps due to its desirable location on the edge of a forest, which was ideal for hunting. At this stage the area was held by Earl Harold,  however the Domesday book reveals that by 1086, Molland village belonged to the king.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molland provides an example of the changes taking place in the mid-11th century. A royal manor, it gained in importance atfer it was granted to the all-powerful Harold Godwinson and became his principal holding in the area. By 1086 a hundred had also been based here, probably a recent creation though the division of South Molton hundred (with which it later re-merged). Molland&#039;s new importance was sustained when the manor passed to King William I. Its receipts included the earl&#039;s third penny, namely his share of the profits of justice derived from fines levied in the royal courts, in three neighbouring hundreds, including North Molton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the conquest in 1086, estates in Anstey and Molland were given to Bladwin the sheriff and Hugh of Avranches (Earl of Chester and William&#039;s nephew). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources for Molland (as well as North Molton and other manors in Devon) indicate that there was littrle change in settlement between the 11th and 13th centuries although the lowland population of England as a whole trebled between 1086 and 1300.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Molland, conventionary tenure may have affected farming. Conventionary tenants held short leases, usually seven years, secured by the highest bidder. This deterred long-term family interest and may have been a disincentive to investing in improvement. The manorial extents of Molland show a shift from villein to conventionary tenure between 1274 and 1302, when 26 conventionarii each held half a virgate, aroudn 15 acres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 14th century, it was recorded that Molland housed a ditchers and fishermen, as well as tailors, a soapmaker and a painter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molland parish contains many hamlets and farmsteads. The village consists of a cluster of cottages and a public house around a road junction between the &lt;a href=&quot;news://node/11785&quot;&gt;church&lt;/a&gt; on the east and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/great-champson-molland&quot;&gt;Great Champson&lt;/a&gt; farm on the west.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For information on Molland village band, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/molland-town-band&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2001 census recorded that just under one third of Molland&#039;s population was over 65, compared with less than 17 per cent in Exmoor parish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11787 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Molland Town Band</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/molland-town-band</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Molland Town Band&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Molland church had a band or ‘quire’ to accompany the singing in church. In the 1770s the overseers of the poor bought a violin for a poor boy of the parish and paid for his lessons. Perhaps he later played in church. About 1800 the churchwardens went to London to buy a bass viol for the church. Like most churches Molland installed an organ, donated by James Quartley of West Molland in 1887. On its first appearance it was accompanied by the ‘cheerful strains’ of the village band. Presumably the players who formerly served the church continued to entertain the villagers at secular entertainments, weddings and other celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11786 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Molland Church</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/molland-church</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Molland church (St. Mary) is of outstanding interest. It is a simple 15th to 16th century building, replacing an older structure of which the Norman font alone remains, together with two medieval bells. It contains a series of fine monuments to members of the Courtenay family of West Molland and a defaced medieval carving, probably of St Mary Magdalene. It is renowned for its unusually complete set of early 18th-century furnishings comprising altar with rails, pulpit, screen and box pews.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11785 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Great Champson, Molland</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/great-champson-molland</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Great Champson farm was renowned in the late 18th and 19th century for animal breeding. It was a large farm, occupied for several generations by the Quartley family. As with many Devon farms it was sometimes divided between father and adult sons living together. In 1881 John Quartley held 290 a. and his sonÂ Henry 115a. Each employed his own labour. Three labourers and two domestic servants shared the house with the family. In 1901 Henry&#039;s widow ran the farm with her son and daughter. Two young labourers lived with the family in the traditional Exmoor manner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1910 the farm had passed out of the Quartley family and was reduced in size to 289 a. despite taking over Smallacombe farm. It remained a good quality rearing farm with stone and slate shippons, bullock pens, calf houses and stable for 5 horses. The machinery was powered by an overshot waterwheel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ancient farmhouse was noted for its oak panelled rooms and carved screens.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11774 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
