<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Landscape</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/landscape</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Down Hatherley manorial</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/down-hatherley-manorial</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Down Hatherley is a rural parish to the west of Cheltenham&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 21:19:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JamesH</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25684 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Boundaries, landscape and communications of Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/boundaries-landscape-and-communications-overton-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article describes how the Anglo-Saxon manor of Overton included the valley of the River Test for habitation, pasture and mills as well as chalk downland for arable crops, woodland and heath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routes through the parish included the Harrow Way, a Neolithic era track, a Roman road on the northern boundary, the main east-west route, which became the preferred coach road from London to Exeter, and a north- south route connecting Winchester and Newbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach traffic declined almost immediately after the opening of the London to Southampton railway and Micheldever Station in 1840. Overton Station, on the line from London to Exeter, opened in 1854.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article traces how people travelled, on foot, by bicycle, bus and car in succeeding generations and continues with a summary of communication by post, telegraph and telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several estimates of the population of Overton prior to the first census are reviewed. In 1801, the population of the parish was 1,130 and there were 230 houses.  The population grew rapidly until 1841 when it began to decline by outward migration which coincided with loss of agricultural jobs and the closure of the silk mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1901, the population had been restored to the 1841 level with increasing industrial employment at Portals paper mills. It has risen in every decade since, with increasing numbers of people commuting to work outside the parish. The population was 4,315 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the fall in average household size, the numbers of houses doubled between 1911 and 1951, doubled again by 1991 and stood at 1,863 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCH Overton Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 15:37:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25226 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Boundaries, landscape and communications of Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/boundaries-landscape-and-communications-overton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article describes how the Anglo-Saxon manor of Overton included the valley of the River Test for habitation, pasture and mills as well as chalk downland for arable crops, woodland and heath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routes through the parish included the Harrow Way, a Neolithic era track, a Roman road on the northern boundary, the main east-west route, which became the preferred coach road from London to Exeter, and a north- south route connecting Winchester and Newbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach traffic declined almost immediately after the opening of the London to Southampton railway and Micheldever Station in 1840. Overton Station, on the line from London to Exeter, opened in 1854.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article traces how people travelled, on foot, by bicycle, bus and car in succeeding generations and continues with a summary of communication by post, telegraph and telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several estimates of the population of Overton prior to the first census are reviewed. In 1801, the population of the parish was 1,130 and there were 230 houses.  The population grew rapidly until 1841 when it began to decline by outward migration which coincided with loss of agricultural jobs and the closure of the silk mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1901, the population had been restored to the 1841 level with increasing industrial employment at Portals paper mills. It has risen in every decade since, with increasing numbers of people commuting to work outside the parish. The population was 4,315 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the fall in average household size, the numbers of houses doubled between 1911 and 1951, doubled again by 1991 and stood at 1,863 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCH Overton Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 15:37:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25225 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Estuary and Holland Haven</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-estuary-and-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet was the name of the large estuary fed by the Holland River or brook, which formerly ran into the sea between Frinton and Little Holland. The name is probably Anglo-Saxon in origin, as the second element ‘fleet’ is derived from the Old English word fleot meaning ‘stream’ or ‘creek’. A similar well known example is the River Fleet in London, a tributary of the River Thames which was fed by streams on Hampstead Heath and which used to have a tidal inlet and docks at its lower end. The origin of the first element of the name ‘Gun’ is currently unknown, but it possibly derived from an Anglo-Saxon personal name, so the meaning of the whole name could be something like ‘Gunna’s creek’. An alternative suggestion that has been made is that the first part of the name could be a corruption from the Count of Guisnes who possessed the manor of Little Holland in 1210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the name was not recorded until 1320 when a vessel was shipwrecked on ‘Gunfletsond’, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. It seems probable that a name originally applying to the estuary was appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary’s inlet. A map of 1584 in the British Library marks both the ‘Gonflet haven’ (the estuary) and the ‘ye gonflit’ (the sandbank). Other maps from that period, such as maps of Essex by Norden (1594) and Speed (1610) show the Gunfleet as a large, unreclaimed, estuary that was open to the sea at its southern end. The use of the name ‘haven’ would seem to imply the use of the estuary for trade, and the ‘Ganflete’ was also named as a port between Walton and St Osyth in Holinshed’s Chronicles (1586). The substantial marshlands along the estuary were also used by the inhabitants of surrounding parishes like Great and Little Holland as grazing for their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1542 ‘the level of Gunflete haven’ was recorded, perhaps indicating that estuary’s marshland later known as Holland Levels had started to be reclaimed. Although the estuary continued to be marked on coastal maps and sea charts for a long time, it was becoming blocked perhaps by the effects of coastal erosion and long-shore drift. In 1677 a whale was stranded in the narrows at what was probably the entrance to the Gunfleet estuary then described as a ‘creek’. Probably soon afterwards it was decided to reclaim the estuary by constructing a sea wall across its mouth, with a sluice provided to allow the river water to drain away to sea. The intention was to prevent salt water entering the marshes along the Holland River, and thus to improve their agricultural potential and value. It is not known when the first wall was built, but in 1703 a survey was taken of ‘ye Levell or Flatts being several pieces or parcells of land endamaged by a breach at, or near Gunfleet Haven’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The records of the Tendring Levels Commissioners, a type of local government body charged with flood defence, survive from 1727 and show how they maintained the drained marshlands of the level, the sea wall and the sluice through which the Holland River then emptied into the open sea. By the 1760s the area was sufficiently drained to allow a new road link to cross the former estuary from Holland on Sea to Great Holland, although the extensive tracts of land were still liable to flood as shown by the marshes depicted on the Chapman and André map of 1777 and the one inch Ordnance Survey map (1838 edition). The Commissioners continued to be responsible for maintaining the sea wall and the Levels until the 1930s, and their maps reveal the outline of the old estuary through the land that had to pay rates to maintain the sea defences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (1935), pp.13–17. K. Walker, various notes. Calendar of Close Rolls, Edw. II, A.D. 1318–23 (HMSO, 1895), p.249. Holinshed, An Historicall Description of the Iland of Britaine (1586), Book I, Chapter XVII: Of such ports and creeks as our sea-faring men doo note for their benefit upon the coasts of England. British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584) J. Norden, Speculi Britanniae Pars (1594), ed. H. Ellis (Camden Society, London, 1840), map. J. Speed, Map of Essex (1610) J. Chapman and P. André, A Map of Essex (1777). Ordnance Survey map, 1” to 1 Mile (1838) Essex Record Office, D/DHw E14, ‘A true Survey of ye Levell or Flatts’, 1703. ERO, D/ST 1 to 6, Tendring Levels Commissioners, minute books, 1727–1932 ERO, D/ST 17 to 20, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps, 1783 ERO, T/M 565/1, 2, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps c.1901–25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 13:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Land ownership in Buckminster and Sewstern</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/land-ownership-buckminster-and-sewstern</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The parish of Buckminster, which includes the two villages of Buckminster and Sewstern, is in north-east Leicestershire, and adjoins the county of Lincolnshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two manors of Buckminster and Sewstern were purchased in 1763 by Lord William Manners, a younger son of the second Duke of Rutland. His eldest son and heir John Manners married Lady Louisa Talmash, the eldest daughter of the 4th Earl of Dysart (in the Scottish peerage), who became Countess of Dysart in her own right following the deaths of her brothers Lionel (5th earl, died 1799) and Wilbraham (6th earl, died 1840). Land purchases by this family, especially in the late 18th and early 19th centuries, created a large estate, centred on Buckminster Park, the hall built by William Saxton for Sir William Manners in c. 1794. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 12:49:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23137 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Lutterworth Probate Material, 1681-1715</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1681-1715</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lutterworth is a small market town in south Leicestershire, bounded on the west by the Roman Watling Street, which is also the boundary between Leicestershire and Warwickshire. Transport links and trade have therefore always been important in its history. It was a coaching town, and much of its 18th century past has been preserved today, as the town went into decline in the 19th century when people turned to rail. Today it is again a transport hub, with easy access to the M1 and M6 motorways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volunteers in Lutterworth are working towards a VCH history of their town. The inventories here form only a small proportion of the surviving probate material for this town, and more documents will be added as work progresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following links will take you to other inventories for a specific date range:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1621-40&quot;&gt;Lutterworth Probate Material, 1621-1640&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1641-1660&quot;&gt;Lutterworth Probate Material, 1641-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1661-1680&quot;&gt;Lutterworth Probate Material, 1661-1680&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2013 10:15:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21695 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Lutterworth Probate Material, 1661-1680</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1661-1680</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lutterworth is a small market town in south Leicestershire, bounded on the west by the Roman Watling Street, which is also the boundary between Leicestershire and Warwickshire. Transport links and trade have therefore always been important in its history. It was a coaching town, and much of its 18th century past has been preserved today, as the town went into decline in the 19th century when people turned to rail. Today it is again a transport hub, with easy access to the M1 and M6 motorways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volunteers in Lutterworth are working towards a VCH history of their town. The inventories here form only a small proportion of the surviving probate material for this town, and more documents will be added as work progresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may also be interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1621-40&quot;&gt;Lutterworth Probate Material, 1621-1640&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1641-1660&quot;&gt;Lutterworth Probate Material, 1641-60&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lutterworth-probate-material-1681-1710&quot;&gt;Lutterworth Probate Material, 1681-1710&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2013 09:57:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21690 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Aylesford</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/aylesford</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The large village of Aylesford lies in the Medway Valley, Kent. The village grew up on the north bank of the river Medway, where a steep-sided knoll provided a strategic site for a church. The river also narrowed sufficiently at the point to allow for the construction of a stone-built bridge in the 14th century. Housing developed on the north bank of the river, its nucleus between church and bridge. Aylesford was once a distinct, seperated community, having very different traditions and peculiarities from it&#039;s neighbouring villages, despite their shared farming heritage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prehistoric landscape, surrounding Aylesford, was often given mythical significance through the identification of the barrows as the resting place of Catigern adn Horsa, believed to have been killed in battle between the Britons and Saxons nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two principal medieval estates in the parish. In 1240 a Carmelite priory had been established a quarter of a mile west of the church, close to the north bank of the Medway. The builings and lands of the Carmelites formed the post-Dissolution estate known as The Friars, owned from the later 16th century by the Sedley family,and in 1657 acquired by Caled Banks of Maidstone. Sir John Banks, Caleb&#039;s son, amassed great wealth as a merchant in London. Hus eldest daughter married Heneage Finch, son of the Earl of Nottingham. Finch inherited The Friars estate and was in 1714 created Earl of Aylesford. Successive earls continued to hold The Friars and lands in the northern half of the parish until 1882, but they never lived in Aylesford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aylesford grew wealthy in the late 17th century, due to it&#039;s importance as a bridging point over the river Medway. However, this growth was slow due to the control exercised over development by the two main landowning families.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Housing in the area was rather lacking, as the high number of lodgers suggests. In 1861, 12.1 per cent of the parish population was recorded as either boarding or lodging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the mid to late 17th century, Aylesford contributed very little to charity compared to the surrounding villages in the Medway Valley area. In 1865, the Parish Officers of Aylesford &#039;disposed of&#039; £6 4s. to the poor, sick, widows and infirm, after collecting a fine of one shilling from members who arrived late to their montlty meetings.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1851, Aylesford&#039;s population reached 1,487. However, over the next 50 years this number almost doubled, mostly moving into the new settlements built in Pratling Street and Forstal, as well as the new housing built beside the existing industry at Millhall. In the late 19th century, many of the parishioners of Aylesford found employment at the paper-mill and at the brick and pottery works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To view the 1st Edition Ordnance Survey map of Aylesford click &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/mapsheet.aspx?compid=55124&amp;amp;sheetid=4233&amp;amp;ox=0&amp;amp;oy=0&amp;amp;zm=1&amp;amp;czm=10&amp;amp;x=197&amp;amp;y=328&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2011 13:57:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20695 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Compton Park, Compton Chamberlayne</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/compton-park-compton-chamberlayne</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There has probably been a park at Compton Chamberlayne since at least the 14th century, possibly even earlier. The park was landscape and greatly altered by Capability Brown in the 18th century. Formal lakes and gardens that had lain to the east of Compton House were replaced as the park was given a more rustic, arcadian feel; two large, shapeless lakes were formed, and trees were planted on their slopes. The old carriageway which had run from Dinton through the park to the what is now the A30 was closed, and the cottages that lay along it were removed; a holloway and housing platforms are still visible in the park where they had lain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the middle ages, the park was maintained for the hunting of deer, and it continued to be a deer park in the 1860s, when there was a herd of 90 deer. The park continues to operate as a shooting park.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 03:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20596 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Deverill valley road</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/deverill-valley-road</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the 1850s, the road from Longbridge Deverill along the Deverill valley only went as far as the manor house of Hill Deverill. Beyond that, tracks ran south on either side of the river, and the river bed itself was also used at times. During the winter, when the river ran higher, the main route for heavy traffic was along a track that ran over Badbury Hill and on towards Warminster; it survives today as a bridleway. The modern road from Longbridge Deverill through Hill Deverill to Brixton Deverill was completed with public subscription in 1855.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 00:46:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20578 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
