<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Activities</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/activities</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Portals Paper Mills, 1718-1995: Papermakers to the Bank of England</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/portals-paper-mills-1718-1995-papermakers-bank-england</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Portals paper mills have had a profound economic and social effect on Overton parish. In the south of England, it is most unusual to find a single dominant industrial employer over such a long period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Henry Portal, a Huguenot refugee from France, was awarded the contract to make hard-wearing banknote paper for the Bank of England in 1724. The company grew steadily, eventually outgrowing the limited space at Laverstoke Mill, 1km beyond the boundary of Overton parish, and a new factory was built at Overton Station in 1924. Portals became the largest security paper company in the world, employing about 1,550 people in the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 18:14:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25258 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fulling and Finishing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fulling-and-finishing-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;After weaving, cloth had to be fulled to shrink and strengthen the fabric, providing greater resistance to wear and weather. The process originally involved immersing the cloth in a trough filled with water and chemicals (such as fuller’s earth and urine), which helped remove any grease or dirt, and compressing it by foot or hand. The introduction of water-powered fulling mills in the later 12th century mechanised and speeded up the process, with two wooden hammers replacing human effort.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 08:44:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20683 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sheep and wool processing</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sheep-and-wool-processing-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sheep farming was an important part of the Cotswolds economy by the Roman period. Medieval Cotswold sheep were a distinctive breed, producing fine white wool which was highly valued for cloth manufacture: in the 15th century, out of 50 grades of wool produced by English sheep that of the Cotswold ranked third. Probably they were smaller than modern breeds: long-necked and fine-limbed, with short curly fleeces and a woolly forelock from which the nickname ‘Cotswold Lion’ derived. Certainly their fleeces weighed far less than their modern counterparts, about 1½ pounds compared with 9 pounds or more. Medieval fleeces were sold by the sack, each of which weighed 364 pounds and contained the wool of some 240 sheep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 08:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20682 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Lammana</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/lammana</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lammana or Lamanna priory was a small Benedictine cell on the island of Lammana now called St George’s or Looe Island off the south Cornish coast near West Looe. It was one of the remotest possessions of Glastonbury Abbey in Somerset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it was probably not the first religious community on the island. During the 6th century a small Celtic monastery is said to have existed on Lammana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amphora fragments from the Aegean dated c500 AD have been found on the island possibly associated with a lann.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The place-name Lammana contains the Cornish place-name elements lann [early Christian enclosure] and manach [monk].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A broad ditch appears to surround the summit of the central knoll on the island, perhaps indicating an early enclosed site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The medieval chapel and cell were transferred to the mainland to a new site, also called Lammana, in the 12th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chapel on the island is shown on a map of the south coast of Cornwall in 1539 as a small rectangular edifice one-storey high, without a tower.  A partial excavation of the site in 2008 uncovered sections of the north and west walls, and revealed a burial within the chapelm probably of a cleric or layman of high status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two large carved stones preserved on the site may have been part of the chancel arch, subdividing the building inside. The chapel on the mainland stood on a small platform just below the top of the hillside, opposite the island chapel and immediately beneath a lane shown on the tithe map of 1839.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shape of the chapel was rectangular, internally measuring about 8.22 metres (27 feet) in length and 4.72 metres (15.5 feet) in width, perhaps having been extended at some time towards the east. It eventually included a chancel, nave, and a substantial south proch, while steps in the north wall opposite the porch suggest another doorway which may have been accessed from the lane above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 17th August 1548 &#039;the island of Lamane&#039; and the chapel and lands belonging to it were sold with other chantry property to Thomas Bell, knight, of Gloucester and Richard Duke, esquire, of London.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The footings of parts of the wall of the mainland chapel and preserved and may be visited, as many an 8-metre stretch of a wall of the Monks House. The site of the chapel on the island is identifiable, but nothing is visible there above the ground.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2011 13:09:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20655 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster&#039;s public houses</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunsters-public-houses</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dunster has always been well served with alehouses and inns. As a market and cloth town in the medieval and early modern periods there was much business for alehouses. The earliest named public houses were Jeollestavern and Trottstavern belonging to William Dodesham in 1436, the George in 1463 and the Wynseseller in the early 16th century. In 1555 William Edwards and his wife Elizabeth were licensed to keep a tavern and sell wines backdated to 1553.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were many tipplers or alehousekeepers in Dunster in the early 17th century. The two aletasters presented several for not sending for them to check their ale or their measures or for selling short. George Prolle and his wife were accused of keeping entertainment and drinking at their alehouse in service time in 1606. In Lent 1620 nine victuallers undertook not to sell meat and several tipplers in the 1620s were also butchers, a few were weavers, probably their wives ran the alehouses, certainly several widows were tipplers. In 1630 there were 13 in Dunster and one at Alcombe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numbers of licences remained high well into the 18th century although many inns closed with the decline in trade. Tourism created new demands. Tourism came early to Dunster and the Luttrell Arms was created with tourists in mind in 1779. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 11:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20635 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dunster and Minehead drapers and shopkeepers</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dunster-and-minehead-drapers-and-shopkeepers</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until the 19th century Dunster was more important as a retail centre than Minehead. Dunster mercers were recorded from the 15th to 19th centuries and haberdashers and linendrapers were in business there from the 16th and 17th centuries. Until the Parade was laid out in the mid 19th century there was no clear shopping street in Minehead and shops were scattered. There was usually a general shop in Quay Street serving the harbour area and another in Higher Town but the few specialist shops were in Bampton and Friday Streets in the Lower Town. In 1830 draper Thomas Atkins had a shop in Minehead and there were three other shopkeepers in the town. Dunster at the same date had ten drapers and grocers. Dunster had a long history of shopkeeping mainly in High and West Streets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2011 10:23:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20628 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Inns, Beerhouses and associated businesses 1851</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-inns-beerhouses-and-associated-businesses-1851</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Basingstoke Inns, Beerhouses and associated businesses in the 1851 census.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2011 13:02:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20620 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Poor Law Union</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-poor-law-union</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is part of ongoing study of Basingstoke Union and Workhouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very much a fairly rough work in progress, being the results of a study for the first ten years – hopefully these entries will be continually updated as the history progresses. Names are sometimes not clearly written or are phonetic, and we have no proof that the same name didn’t belong to different people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Lists of Paupers, Guardians and Named Officers from the start of the Union in 1835 to 1845 are posted here. Very little remains, except for Board Minute Books, correspondence with the Poor Law Commission and subsequent bodies, and a few miscellaneous documents. The building has completely disappeared under modern development&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2011 13:39:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20603 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Basingstoke Massagainian Riots</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-massagainian-riots</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The riots against the Salvation Army in Basingstoke in the early 1880s gave rise to questions in the House of Commons, led to the publication of a parliamentary paper, Basingstoke Disturbances, and made headlines in the national press. One London newspaper described Basingstoke as a town “that appears to be inhabited chiefly by a race of barbarians”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2011 11:54:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20503 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Castle Cary in the Civil War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/castle-cary-civil-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A coin hoard found in 2006 is a striking reminder of the terrible damage the Civil War did to ordinary people&#039;s lives. Castle Cary suffered from several incidents including a nearby assembly of 5,000 clubmen and the arrival of the New Model Army. Local people saw their church damaged and no doubt suffered looting of houses and shops, which led them to hide their valuables.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2010 08:37:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20300 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
