<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/exmoor</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton police station</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulverton-police-station</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dulverton has a had a series of police stations, the current building a purely utilitarian building but in 1904 a very grand building was designed and built in Lady Street to accommodate the police, their prisoners and the magistrates&#039; court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 13:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20615 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton hydro-electric plant</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulverton-hydro-electric-plant</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;While many remote farms on Exmoor had wind and oil powered generators for electricity in the 20th century, only Dulverton had an ambitious scheme to harness the power of water.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 12:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20613 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Probate Inventories, Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/probate-inventories-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the purposes of the inventory was to determine the probate fees, so the inventory was valued. Many west Somerset inventories survive for the 17th and early 18th centuries and provide us with a striking glimpse of the wealth of Exmoor’s farmers and craftsmen. Whilst less rich in worldly goods than lowland households, Exmoor yeoman farmers at the time were prosperous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In rural areas less attention was paid to the house and its contents except for items of pewter, silver, or brass. Country people’s wealth was usually in their livestock and crops, or for a widow or retired farmer, life savings let out at interest.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12690 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Place Names of Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/place-names-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most Exmoor place names are of Old English origin and represent features of the landscape. Valleys derive their names from their nature or from the animals there. Smallacombe in Molland was narrow and Liscombe in Dulverton had a &quot;loose&quot; (pigsty). Such names may be English translations of the older British. Many names refer to water, revered by Celtic peoples, such as Hawkwell (crooked stream), Dulverton, Wellshead, or Ludslade (valley of the torrent), Exford.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Names ending in &quot;cott&quot;, &quot;ley&quot; (leah, a glade) or &quot;worthy&quot; indicate Anglo-Saxon settlement or places taken over by them. &quot;Worthy&quot; names are often attached to large farms, believed to be early Anglo-Saxon, which may have utilised late prehistoric intakes from moorland. The &quot;ley&quot; names are mainly in Molland, a well-wooded parish, including Bremley (bramble glade), and around Winsford Hill.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12689 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Conservation in Action</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/conservation-action</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Exmoor National Park Authority bought the Simonsbath sawmill from the Fortescue estate in the 1990s to safeguard the character of the building and its site in the middle of Exmoor, to restore it as a building, and to restore its operation as part of a renewable energy strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;  This sawmill was damaged in 1952, from a major flood. The restoration of the mill building itself was carried out to the highest building conservation standards. It is more than a desire to ‘preserve’ an old structure to the Exmoor National Park Authority. It had always been seen as part of the National Park Authority’s approach to sustainable countryside management and promotion of the use of renewable energy.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12688 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Exmoor Farmyards</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/exmoor-farmyards</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The farming year on Exmoor required seasonal movement of animals to make maximum use of grass growth during the summer months and to provide the livestock and cultivated crops with shelter from Exmoor’s climate during the winter months. The farmyards were clearly influenced by the model farms of the mid-19th century whose buildings were arranged in a logical sequence to maximise output. The upland topography was utilised in the form of bank barns which were terraced into the hillside so that the upper floors could be entered from ground level and the lower floor from the yard. The steep slopes provided a sufficient head of water for waterpower to be harnessed to drive the threshing machines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12687 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Deserted Farmsteads on Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/deserted-farmsteads-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons why farmsteads become abandoned. In southern Exmoor, as elsewhere, the pressure for larger farms led to the amalgamation of farmsteads in the 19th century. A small unnamed farm on Holmoor at Exford was abandoned c.1840 as were Castle Farm in Hawkridge and Road Farm at Winsford. Other small farms became agricultural labourers’ cottages about the same date, including Slade in Hawkridge. Riscombe in Winsford was two farms in 1839, but shortly afterwards became two labourers’ cottage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12686 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Commons, Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/commons-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following disafforestation, manors gained control of their own commons yet, were not always successful in maintaining it. Disputes were taken to the courts, which maintained common rights and punished infringements. Individuals and groups of people were punished for abusing the commons. There was always a temptation to overstock to increase yields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The communities of southern Exmoor had to know the boundaries of their commons. Some bounds were clearly marked such as the &quot;Cornell&quot; ditch that divided common rights at Anstey in the 1530s. Others had stones or trees at intervals that needed to be memorised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12685 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Forest and Manor Courts; Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/forest-and-manor-courts-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In much of England in the Middle Ages, routine business relating to local communities was conducted at the appropriate manorial court, while serious crimes were generally dealt with by royal officials.  In manor courts, business included changes of tenancy, payment of heriots (an animal or money due to the lord after a tenant died), and cases between tenants. The jury or officers would present offences such as straying animals, houses in need of repair, pollution or diversion of watercourses, selling ale at excessive prices, or selling bad meat. A major exception to that were those areas that were under forest law, which imposed a wide range of exceptional fines and penalties and were operated through special courts with their own officials. It was largely implemented through royal itinerant courts called &quot;eyres&quot;, but local forest courts known as the &quot;swainmote&quot; or &quot;swanimote courts&quot; were held twice a year in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12684 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Norman Craftsmanship on Exmoor</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/norman-craftsmanship-exmoor</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the Conquest, there seems to have been much more activity as the parish structure emerged on Exmoor. In southern Exmoor seven churches have Norman fonts, a remarkable survival in a relatively small area which may mark the date at which those churches were founded or acquired parochial responsibilities such as baptism. In general, settlements now cluster around most churches, in which the church was customarily built next to the manor house. A great deal of expense would have been incurred on the building of the churches, they were probably the only substantial stone buildings on Exmoor and would have dominated the landscape.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12683 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
