<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Parham House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/parham-house</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>From Family House to Open House at Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/family-house-open-house-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major events in the life of a country house often leave little trace upon the building. The experience of those who have lived through them has to be recovered from diaries, letters, written recollections, and oral testimony. The transitory impact of the Second World War on Parham is recorded in photographs and in the memoirs of Veronica, one of the Pearson children who first knew the house as a family home but who returned during the war and stayed to welcome, with her mother, the first visitors to the house in 1948.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12681 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Walled Garden</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/walled-garden</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Structural features of gardens, such as buildings and walls, can be permanent and outlive plant life.  A detailed history of these gardens is preserved only with those who tended to, and experienced personally how these gardens evolved under their care.  The walled garden at Parham was probably created in the 18th century and paths and brick walls survive from that period. It must always have been a productive garden, supplying food and flowers for the household.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12680 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Country house design</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/country-house-design</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The desire to introduce fashionable features, such as a top-floor long gallery, into country houses demanded new solutions to make them possible. At Parham, the roof over the main range was designed to create an unobstructed attic with sufficient head room, so to be used as one of the most important and most visited rooms in the house. It was decorated in a style similar to that of the hall and great chamber. The original roof is a remarkable survival of Elizabethan carpentry, though the plaster ceiling decorated by Oliver Messel is 20th-century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12679 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Women of Parham House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/women-parham-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women have featured strongly in the succession of owners at Parham although, until the Married Woman&#039;s Property Act of 1882, a woman&#039;s property passed automatically to her husband on marriage. Parham was most recently descended through the female line to Lady Emma Barnard, who lives there with her family now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Women, and particularly heiresses, played an important part in the fortunes of landed estates such as Parham. Marriages between estate owners and  women from wealthy families brought new sources of finance to many estates. Sometimes such alliances contributed not only money but also land to the heiress&#039;s new family. When William Palmer, son of the first owner, married Elizabeth Verney of Fairfield, Somerset, he acquired her family estate, which soon after became the Palmers&#039; main home. In the 17th century the marriage of two Oxfordshire heiresses to Bisshopp owners provided new funds to draw on. Sometimes owners overestimated the wealth of their brides. Emily Wilmot-Horton unfortunately did not bring as much money to Parham as her husband, Robert Curzon junior, had expected when he married her in 1850. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to document female influence on the way that Parham developed and was used, as it is with most country houses . Most evidence survives in the form of diaries, letters and oral testimony. The diaries of Lady Catherine Pechell provide vivid pictures of life at Parham in the early 19th centuryand recollections about changes made to the house by her forebears.  The memories of Barabara Frankland and her brother recall what the house was like early in the 20th century when it was owned by their grandmother, Mary Frankland Curzon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can use written evidence and old paintings, photographs and architectural plans to assess how Parham changed as women&#039;s role in society evolved. For example, old photographs of a sitting room show its feminine character - a trait that can be seen in depictions of rooms in many other houses. The transfer of the kitchen from the basement to a more convenient position nearer the dining room on the ground floor indicates that there was more direct involvement by the mistress of the house in the preparation of meals after the Second World War, when fewer servants were employed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12619 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Coppicing at Parham</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/coppicing-parham</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The very best oak building timber at the end of the 16th century came from woods which were specifically managed to produce tall, straight trees for posts, beams, and rafters. Such oaks, known as ‘standards’, were grown in the company of species such as hazel which were cut almost to the ground on a regular, cyclical basis and used for necessities such as fuel and fencing. This system of regular cutting is known as coppicing. It not only ensures an almost constant supply of wood which can be harvested again and again as soon as it reaches an appropriate size, but also provides the perfect environment for growing trees suitable for building timber. Between harvests, the coppiced wood grows rapidly — as anyone who has pruned a young tree or shrub will know. The dense new growth forces the young standard timber trees to grow more swiftly than they would in the open, as they are competing for light. The oaks form a crown high above the level of the coppice, unable to throw out lower branches because of the surrounding undergrowth, so lessening the risk of knots which can weaken structural timbers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; [i]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;--------------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;[i] O. Rackham, Trees and Woodland in the British Landscape (London, 1976), 8.(Image courtesy of the Woodland Trust Picture Library) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12618 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parham and the Second World War</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parham-and-second-world-war</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Second World War had a great impact on the restoration of the country house.  A hiatus in the works planned by the Pearsons, combined with the use of the house by the army and as a home for evacuees, meant several steps back had to be taken before they could move forward. Work eventually began in earnest in 1949.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12617 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Pearsons</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/pearsons</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Pearsons came to Parham in 1922 neither as members of a nouveau riche ‘smart set’ nor from the old landed aristocracy. Clive Pearson, born on 12 August 1897, was the second son of the industrialist Weetman Pearson (who became the 1st Viscount Cowdray in 1917) and Annie Cass, daughter of a former lord mayor of Bradford. The Pearson family empire had its roots in Bradford in the firm of S. Pearson and Son, building contractors, in the mid-19th century. In the course of Clive’s lifetime the company grew to become the biggest of its kind in the world, famous for its harbours, railways, electrical plants, and oil installations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12616 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Specialist Research</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/specialist-research</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This section contains photographs of specialist research at Parham House.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12615 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Building in Stone</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/building-stone</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Palmers used several types of stone at Parham. A local sandstone called Amberley Blue was the main choice for the external walls. As it was not very durable it was rendered, with the render coloured and finished to give the impression either of a better quality stone or perhaps even brickwork. A more expensive but still local sandstone, Pulborough stone, was used for windows and doorways. For the corners of the building (the quoins), quantities of the hard-wearing Bath limestone were brought in. Inside the house, where there was no risk of rain or frost damaging the stone, the builders used a pale, hard chalk called clunch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12614 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>All Mod Cons</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/all-mod-cons</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Much of our knowledge about Elizabethan Parham comes from the work which the Pearsons and their architect Victor Heal carried out on the house from 1922 to the end of the 1960s. They not only repaired and consolidated a building that was in a neglected state when they came to it, but carefully and painstakingly restored or recreated many of the original features which had been modernised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12613 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
