<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Brixton Deverill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/brixton-deverill</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>St Michael&#039;s church, Brixton Deverill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-michaels-church-brixton-deverill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The church at Brixton Deverill occupies a site next to the manor house, at the heart of the medieval village. Originally built in the 13th century, the present building comprises of a chancel, a nave, and a west tower, and has been much restored and altered over the centuries. Of the original church, the lower part of the tower and an arch inside the church are 13th century; the belfry stage was added to the tower in the 15th century. The nave and chancel were rebuilt &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;. 1760, and again in 1862, when the chancel was lengthened to two bays and a vestry attached to its north-east side. The rector William Barnes added a spire to the tower in 1852, but this had to be removed in 1899 on account of its dangerous condition. Further restoration work was been carried out throughout the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 01:52:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20583 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Brixton Deverill schoolroom</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/brixton-deverill-schoolroom</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Built on the side of the rectory, the village schoolroom was opened in 1823 with the aid of a £40 grant from teh Treasury. Before that date, the children of the village had had to attend classes in neighbouring parishes with teh aid of charitable donations. There were 19 children attending - 11 boys and 8 girls - in 1835, which had risen to almost 50 by 1858, when the village was near its peak population. After that, the numbers of children attending the school declined, and it was closed in 1895, after which the village&#039;s children once again had to travel to neighbouring parishes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the schoolroom was in use as a village reading room during the early 20th century; by 1965 it was in disuse and infested with rats. It has now been re-incorporated into the house, which is now a private residence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2011 01:36:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20581 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
