<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Waterways</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/waterways</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Boundaries, landscape and communications of Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/boundaries-landscape-and-communications-overton-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article describes how the Anglo-Saxon manor of Overton included the valley of the River Test for habitation, pasture and mills as well as chalk downland for arable crops, woodland and heath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routes through the parish included the Harrow Way, a Neolithic era track, a Roman road on the northern boundary, the main east-west route, which became the preferred coach road from London to Exeter, and a north- south route connecting Winchester and Newbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach traffic declined almost immediately after the opening of the London to Southampton railway and Micheldever Station in 1840. Overton Station, on the line from London to Exeter, opened in 1854.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article traces how people travelled, on foot, by bicycle, bus and car in succeeding generations and continues with a summary of communication by post, telegraph and telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several estimates of the population of Overton prior to the first census are reviewed. In 1801, the population of the parish was 1,130 and there were 230 houses.  The population grew rapidly until 1841 when it began to decline by outward migration which coincided with loss of agricultural jobs and the closure of the silk mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1901, the population had been restored to the 1841 level with increasing industrial employment at Portals paper mills. It has risen in every decade since, with increasing numbers of people commuting to work outside the parish. The population was 4,315 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the fall in average household size, the numbers of houses doubled between 1911 and 1951, doubled again by 1991 and stood at 1,863 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCH Overton Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 15:37:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25226 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Boundaries, landscape and communications of Overton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/boundaries-landscape-and-communications-overton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This article describes how the Anglo-Saxon manor of Overton included the valley of the River Test for habitation, pasture and mills as well as chalk downland for arable crops, woodland and heath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Routes through the parish included the Harrow Way, a Neolithic era track, a Roman road on the northern boundary, the main east-west route, which became the preferred coach road from London to Exeter, and a north- south route connecting Winchester and Newbury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coach traffic declined almost immediately after the opening of the London to Southampton railway and Micheldever Station in 1840. Overton Station, on the line from London to Exeter, opened in 1854.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article traces how people travelled, on foot, by bicycle, bus and car in succeeding generations and continues with a summary of communication by post, telegraph and telephone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several estimates of the population of Overton prior to the first census are reviewed. In 1801, the population of the parish was 1,130 and there were 230 houses.  The population grew rapidly until 1841 when it began to decline by outward migration which coincided with loss of agricultural jobs and the closure of the silk mill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1901, the population had been restored to the 1841 level with increasing industrial employment at Portals paper mills. It has risen in every decade since, with increasing numbers of people commuting to work outside the parish. The population was 4,315 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the fall in average household size, the numbers of houses doubled between 1911 and 1951, doubled again by 1991 and stood at 1,863 in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCH Overton Team&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2017 15:37:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25225 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>An introduction to Holland Haven </title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/introduction-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, Holland Haven is the place where the Holland River (now the Holland Brook) once ran out into the North Sea between Clacton and Frinton in Essex.  This estuary was called the Gunfleet and it was once wide enough for boats to sail through it and in 1677 for a whale to become stranded there.  Towards the end of the 17th century a sea wall was built across the mouth of the estuary, the land behind the wall was reclaimed from the sea and converted to marshland pastures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geographically, the Essex coastline is characterised by a series of creeks, inlets and estuaries which in the past have allowed access for small boats to sail inland.  When the Gunfleet estuary was open to the North Sea, small boats may have been able to sail up river as far as Thorpe-le-Soken. Small wharves and landing places were built along the banks of Holland River allowing crops grown on nearby farms and other local produce to be loaded easily onto boats and carried along the river, out to sea, into the Thames estuary and into London. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote and out of the way landing places could also be used to avoid customs control and the isolated marshes at Holland were notorious in the past for smugglers even after the estuary was reclaimed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can get an idea of what it would have been like in the Gunfleet estuary by looking at nearby Beaumont Quay on Hamford Water which was used as a landing place for boats from the Middle Ages to the 1930s.  From here barges were loaded with produce such as corn, hay, cheese and timber, and brought return cargoes, mainly building materials or soil improvers such as manure and chalk from London, Kent and Essex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another feature in this landscape would have been tide mills, different to water mills or windmills as they use the ebb and flow of the tides to power the waterwheel.  The Essex coastline was dotted with this ancient type of mill with sites identified at nearby Thorrington, St Osyth and Walton-on-the-Naze.  The work of tide mills was often supplemented by a nearby windmill such as at Thorrington and Walton-on-the-Naze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know that alongside agriculture, the copperas industry was also important locally in the 17th and 18th centuries.  Copperas stones (which were actually iron pyrites) were washed out of the London Clay cliffs onto the shore and converted to copperas (green vitriol) at factories known as Copperas Houses.  Copperas was used for various purposes such as dyes and inks.  The stones were collected by local people all along the coast from Clacton, Frinton and Walton, and were also dredged up from the Copperas Bank off the coast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reclaimed estuary is now used for leisure pursuits, including the Holland Haven country park and Frinton Golf Links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	You can explore&lt;strong&gt; An introduction to Holland &lt;/strong&gt;Haven using the suggested activities and assets below.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use maps to introduce your study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a modern map to locate the Holland Haven area by first viewing Europe, UK, East Anglia, the Essex coastline (naming the North Sea, London and the Thames estuary), and finally Clacton, Walton and Frinton.  Use these key places to locate the course of the Holland Brook and notice the marshes, follow the length of the Brook - it looks a bit like a ladder.  Find other places of interest such as your school, local beaches and houses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use one or more of the maps &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/norden-map-1594&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Norden 1594&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/chapman-and-andre-1777&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chapman and André 1777 &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ordnance-survey-map-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OS 1838&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/ordnance-survey-map-1838&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;to find out what was it like here in the past.  Compare the historic map with your modern map.  You can use the map showing &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/land-liable-flood-holland-levels&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;land liable to flood on the Holland Marshes&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;as an indication of the size of the former estuary.  These are some suggestions to help you explore what is the same and different:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for local place names and spellings.  It might help to read them out loud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the shape of the roads&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the shape of the coastline and waterways&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Locate crossings over the river and if you are using more than one map check if they are on each one.  What does this tell us about when they were built?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you see any buildings? What are they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extend this activity by tracing or overlaying the maps chronologically to locate, describe and label the changes that have happened in the landscape including the shape of the estuary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was life like here for people in the past?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use images&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/copperas-pickers-shoreline-harwich&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; “Copperas pickers” on the shoreline at Harwich&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;/strong&gt;photos&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/thorrington-mill-1929&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thorrington Mill &lt;/a&gt;(1929), &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/beaumont-quay-1960-showing-rose-and-warehouse&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beaumont Quay &lt;/a&gt;(1960) &lt;/strong&gt;and documents&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/stranding-monstrous-whale-1677&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;‘A monstrous whale’&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/poaching-holland-marshes-1609-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Poaching on Holland Marshes &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;and&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-node&quot; href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/possible-landing-places-gunfleet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Possible landing places on the Gunfleet Estuary &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;and choose one or more&lt;strong&gt; maps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about what you would like to know and group your questions under headings (for example, work, food, events).  Look at each source for the information it gives you to answer your questions.  Move on to another source and add in more information.  Remember that there are additional assets for you to use on other parts of the VCH Explore site (link to home?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Go on a fieldtrip&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use a modern map and historic map together to plan a route for a walk or place to visit.  Aim to take in as many of the landmarks and features identified in the previous activities as possible.  Take photos or make sketches and use these to label a copy of the map.  Add labels with the answers from your previous activities, and explain the connections between past and present human and physical features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 10:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MattB</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24612 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Tendring Level (Holland Haven)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/tendring-level-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Responsibility for sea defence and drainage in coastal regions since the early thirteenth century had been allocated to &lt;em&gt;ad hoc &lt;/em&gt;Commissions of walls and ditches (&lt;em&gt;de walliis et fossatiis&lt;/em&gt;) appointed by the Crown. The commissioners were officers who had powers to enforce local communal responsibilities for the maintenance of sea walls, banks and drains, and thus attempt to prevent flooding and the inroads of the sea. They could make local by-laws and raise rates to ensure the essential work was undertaken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such commissioners for Tendring Hundred (equivalent to the modern Tendring district) were first recorded about 1450, when the abbot of St Osyth, John Godmanston, esq., John Green and Robert Tanfield and others were appointed. The powers of such royal Commissions was consolidated by Statute in 1531 in A General Act concerning Commissions of Sewers. This was enacted &#039;considering daily great damages and losses which have happened in many and diverse parts ... by reason of the outrageous flowing surges and course of the sea in and upon marsh grounds and other low places&#039;. Under the 1531 At the Commissions initially only lasted three years, but another Commissions of Sewers Act of 1571 later extended the term to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible that the Tendring commissioners met infrequently for information about the 15th and 16th centuries is scant, and the extent of the sea defences around the Gunfleet estuary and on the coastline of Great Holland, Little Holland and Frinton remains unknown. A reference to &#039;le level de Gunfletehaven&#039; in 1542 may indicate that some drainage activity had taken place, for the word &#039;level&#039; was often used of partly reclaimed marshlands of the type protected by the activities of commissioners. Other examples of the use of the word are the Somerset Levels and the Gwent Levels of south-east Wales. A document concerning poaching at Little Holland in 1609 referred to &#039;a drowned land called the Flatts&#039;, and the same term was used as an alternative for the Tendring Level in 1703.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would seem that the gradual silting up of the Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook or River that fed it necessitated a response from the commissioners, probabaly stimulated by those whose livelihood was being affected by the flooding and perhaps the loss of trading opportunities. The response was a plan to make a sea wall across the estuary between Little Holland and Frinton, and thus reclaim by drainage the former estuary. It is not known precisely when the sea wall was first constructed, but it appears to have been sometime in the 17th century. A survey of the Tendring Level after the Great Storm of 1703 mentioned a &#039;breach&#039; that had been made, suggesting that the sea wall existed by that date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sluice was included in the new wall which could be opned at low tide to allow the river watre to escape, the sluice gate then being closed to prevent th rising tide from entering and flooding the newly won marshes. The original sluice was at Sandy Point near Frinton which seems to have been the natural outfall of the river water from the Holland Brook, although it was later moved east to the site of the present sluice at Holland Haven. As a result many hundreds of acres of land were reclaimed in the parishes of Great Holland, Little Holland, Frinton, Great Clacton, Little Clacton and Thorpe-le-Soken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;K. Walker, &#039;The battle of the Clacton peninsula. Man versus the sea&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Essex Review&lt;/em&gt;, Volume LXIV (1955), pp.103-11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1935), p. 17.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Yelloly Watson, &lt;em&gt;The Tendring Hundred in the Olden Time &lt;/em&gt;(1877), p. 70-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/DHw E14: A true survey of ye Levell or Flatts (1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, Q/SR 189/25: Quarter Sessions, pocahing case, 1609.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, Catalogue explanations under references C191, C225, C226.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 11:48:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24095 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland Brook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-brook-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Holland Brook, sometimes called the Holland River, has been rather overlooked as an important landscape feature of Tendring Hundred (the older name for Tendring district). Even the original name of the watercourse is uncertain, although as the Holland Brook fed into the Gunfleet estuary that may record the original name of the river - the Gunfleet. The names Gunfleet Haven and Holland Haven both seem to refer to the original estuary that was later permanently reclaimed from the sea by the Tendring Levels Commissioners in the 17th and 18th centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brook was regarded as important enough for its course to be described in versions of Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles dating from 1577 and 1587: &quot;Betwixt the Naze also and the mouth of the Colne, is another Ryll which riseth at Little Bentley, and thence goeth to Tendryng thorpe, thorow Clacten parke by great Holland, and east of little Holland into the deepe sea&quot;. The accurate description draws attention to the length of the watercoruse or &#039;rill&#039; from its source near Little Bentley and Little Bromley down to the sea at Little Holland, which virtually divided Tendring Hundred in half. Several features are worthy of note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the original Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook and its valley probably provided an important access route from the coast into the interior of Tendring Hundred both in prehistoric and later periods. There is considerable evidence from cropmarks for early settlement around the upper reaches of the brook in Tendring and neighbouring parishes. The brook may also have had an influence upon the later Anglo-Saxon and medieval patterns of settlement. It may, for example, be no coincidence that the brook leads to the parish of Tendring, which was the central place of the Hundred (the Hundred assembly met on Tendring Heath), and which name is probaby derived from a place-name in Germany transferred to this location by Anglo-Saxon migrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the Holland Brook and the Gunfleet estuary later provided a considerable barrier to east-west road communications. A number of bridges were therefore eventually established, presumably starting furthest inland where the watercourse could be more easily bridged. That at Rice bridge, between Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, seems to have been present by the 14th century. Further downstream that at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, was first recorded in 1509, and that at Holland bridge, between Great and Little Holland, in 1727 (after the former estuary had been reclaimed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the Holland brook and Gunfleet estuary were fed by a number of smaller streams in the parishes along their route, and the system effectively drained much of the centre of Tendring Hundred and many thousands of acres of farmland. Some of the tributary streams were quite small, but others like Picker&#039;s Ditch leading west from the Gunfleet towards Great Clacton were quite substantial. The potential for flooding was therefore very large, and after the Gunfleet or Holland Haven was reclaimed as marshland pasture by the Tendring Levels Commissioners they had to work hard expending money and enforcing maintenance upon local landowners to keep the channels clear so as to prevent major flooding incidents. Even in winter today the course of the brook and the old estuary is often marked by the flooded marshlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(Cambridge, 1935), 17, 325, 351-2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map of Tendring Hundred from P. Morant, &lt;em&gt;The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, I (1768).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles: http://www.english.ox.ac.uk/holinshed/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Explore Asset under this heading: Map of land liable to flood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See other Explore Items on Rice bridge; Fan bridge; Holland bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 10:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24091 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Holland bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Holland bridge is the most recent bridge to cross the Holland River (or Holland Brook), and the furthest downstream. Maps of 1594 and 1603 indicate that there was no route at that time across the Gunfleet estuary which would therefore have still formed a major barrier to land communications along the coast. Then the first crossing point was at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, some one and a half to two miles inland from the sea. As a result, there was probably much communication in small boats across the Gunfleet estuary and along the coast in the sheltered waters of the Gunfleet Channel (now known as the Wallet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, probably sometime towards the end of the 17th century the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs decided to construct a sea wall across the mouth of the estuary which was becoming silted up. As the former Gunfleet estuary behind the sea wall was converted to marshland pastures (although still liuable to winter flooding), so the course of the Holland River became channelled into a water way, now known as the Holland Brook, that ran through its lowest part. The river water, resulting from the many thousands of acres draining into the Holland Brook, was discharged into the sea via a sluice built in the new sea wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the reclamation works were considered advanced sufficiently, a causeway was built across the reclaimed land and a new bridge, named Little Holland bridge, was built over the brook. The date of the bridge is uncertain, but it was first recorded in 1727. The bridge was locally significant for it was the first time that a direct road communication existed between the settlements of Little Holland and Great Holland on the two sides of the old estuary. Chapman and Andre&#039;s map of Essex in 1777 shows the nature of the land half a century after the bridge was first built. A road led from Little Holland Hall into the marhses and then crossed the Holland brook by the new bridge before travelling northwards through the marshes and up the valley side towards Great Holland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The approach road to the bridge through the marshes in 1777 was depicted as a series of dashes indicating that the route was rather impermanet or uncertain and liable to flood. Chapman and Andre often depicted roads in this way when they crossed common land or where routes were poorly demarcated; another example is their map of the route through the marshes east of Fan bridge. The present Holland bridge appears to date from the early 20th century and until rceent years it had a metal sign indicating where the Great and Little Holland parish boundaries met.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map, 1&quot; (1838).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/ST 20 (Map of part of TendrinG level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tednring Levels Commissioners&#039; Map (early 20th century; in private ownership).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 18:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24008 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Rice bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/rice-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rice bridge is the earliest recorded crossing point on the river now known as the Holland Brook, and one of the furthest inland. It was in existence by 1319 when an Agnes de Risbregge (Agnes of Rice Bridge) was recorded in a taxation return for Little Clacton. Her name probably meant that she lived at or near the bridge. The bridge also gave its name to the surrounding land as an estate called Risbridge or Rosebridge was recorded in the later 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bridge was built on a route that was probably locally important in the Middle Ages. Not ony did it connect the two parishes of Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, but also the manors on either side of the river that were owned by the bishop pf London and his cathedral church of St Paul&#039;s. In the Domesday Book of 1086 the bishop held the manor of Clacton (comprising both Great Clacton and Little Clacton)  while all of Thorpe-le-Soken, Kirby-le-Soken and Walton-le-Soken were held by the Dean and Chapter of St Paul&#039;s (the cathderal clergy). By 1127 on one side of the bridge lay Little Clacton park, a deerpark owned by the bishop, while on the other side lay Thope park, a deerpark owned by the Dean and Chapter. The road over Rice bridge therefore connected the two church estates and their hunting parks. Possiby the huntsmen ranged across both parks quite freely, otherwise the deer could have swum across the river to safety!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name Rice bridge is itself very informative, as it probably originates in the Old English words &#039;hris&#039; (meaning brushwood) and &#039;brycg&#039; (meaning bridge or causeway). The crossing may therefore have started out as a timber bridge or causeway and it probably continued in that form for many centuries. In 1612 the tenants of Thorpe Park and Clacton Park were ordered to &#039;make&#039; the bridge (perhaps from timber available in the deer parks), and it was still described as a wooden footbridge in 1783. County maps from 1594 and 1603 show a main road from Little Clacton and Weeley towards Thorpe, Kirby and Walton that crossed the Holland River at what must be Rice bridge, although it was not named. A survey of the Holland Levels by the Tendring Levels Commissioenrs in 1703 named Rice bridge, and many maps from the 18th century such as that by Chapman and Andre in 1777 show the same route. The present brick built Rice bridge dates from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (Cambridge, 1935), p. 336.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P. Morant, The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex (1768), Volume II, p. 475.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M. Gibbs (ed), The Early Charters of St Paul&#039;s (Camden Society, 3rd series, lviii, 1939), no. 60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777),&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;London Metropolitan Archive, Guildhall Library, MS. 25416/3; MS. 9531/6, f.192v.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), Q/SR 199/79, 154, 155 (Quarter Sessions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/DHw E14 (A true survey of ye Levll or Flatts ... several parcells of land endamaged at or near Gun-Fleet Haven, 1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 20 (Map of part of Tendring Level, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 17:23:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24006 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Fan bridge on Holland River</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/fan-bridge-holland-river</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fan bridge is the second earliest rcorded crossing point on the river now known as Holland Brook (formerly Holland River). Further downstream than Rice Bridge, the river valley here was broader in character and more liable to flood. Fan Bridge (often spelt &#039;Fann&#039; or &#039;Fenn&#039;) was first recorded in 1509 and it was also depicted on Norden&#039;s map of 1594; its name is likely to mean fen or marsh. The present flood plain of the Holland Brook probably indicates the width of the river in medieval times, and at Fan bridge it is nearly one tenth of a mile across. The site of the bridgemust therefore have been approached by a causeway through the marsh before a bridge spanned the main channel of the Holland Brook. Indeed, the original route may have been on a different alignment and changed when the bridge was built, which might explain the curious dog-leg in the approach road from Little Clacton (see map).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chapman and Andre map of 1777 shows that the fens still existed all around the bridge at that date. The same map reveals that the approach road through the marsh to the west of the bridge (Little Clacton side) was relatively short, but that on the other (Great Holland side) it was longer and shown as a series of dashes indicating that the route was impermanent and liable to flood. Chapman and Andre often depicted roads in this way  when they crossed common land where routes were poorly demarcated. A good example is the track through the middle of Cooks Green in Little Clacton, to the west of Fan Bridge. The name Fanbridge Common was recorded between about 1600 and  1800, revealing that the fens next to the bridge continued to be used for common grazing at certain times of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The probable later date of Fan Bridge, compared to Rice Bridge, may have several explanations. This was certainly a more difficult and marshy location for a bridge, and in earlier centuries when the Gunfleet estuary was more open to the sea it may have been an impractical location. In addition, Fan Bridge was located on a more minor local road linking the parishes of Great Holland and Little Clacton. On the west side between Clacton village and the bridge lay the hamlet of Cooks Geeen, while on the east between Great Holland village and the bridge lay Great Holland Common (or Jeffries Common). These greenside settlements were minot and traffic between them was probably not extensive; in the Middle Ages and later Little Clacton and Great Holland manors were also in different ownership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In later centuries the bridge was apparently maintained by the parishes of Little Clacton and Great Holland. In 1776 the Little Clacton parish surveyors (the parish officials in charge of highways) painted posts at the bridge, and in 1795 they built a new bridge of timber and brick (although it was not named). According to a survey of the Tendring Levels in 1783 the bridge was constructed of brick. In 1808 Great Holland&#039;s parish surveyors accounted for the demolition of the old bridge and the erection of a replacement. In 1821 the Little Clacton surveyors carried out work on &#039;Holland Bridge&#039;, presumably meaning Fan Bridge (rather than the true Holland Bridge between Little Holland and Great Holland). It is not known how long the 19th-century brick bridge lasted. The present brick bridge appears to date from the early 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (Cambridge, 1935).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Chapman and P. Andre, A Map of the County of Essex (1777)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office (ERO), D/DHw E14 (A true survey of ye Levell or Flatts .... several parcells of land endamaged by a breach at or near Gun-Fleet Haven, 1703).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/ST 19 (Map of part of TendringLevel, 1783).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/P 80/21/1, 2 (Little Clacton Parish Surveyors&#039; Accounts, 1769-1807, 1813-35).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERO, D/P 396/21/1 (Great Holland Paroish Surveyors&#039; Accounts, 1804-40).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 16:42:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24004 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Beaumont Quay</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/beaumont-quay</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The historic site known as Beaumont Quay is an important survival showing the nature of the small quays and wharves that were once very common and busy along the Essex coast. It is located right at the end of the tidal Landermere Creek, on the northern bank, which provided access for boats to Hamford Water and then to the North sea. The site is now owned by Essex County Council and is a scheduled ancient monument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological material has revealed settlement in this area in the Iron-Age, Roman and early medieval periods, as well as evidence for salt-making. There was probably also a landing place or wharf which served the large and valuable medieval manor of Beaumont Hall. In the Middle Age the overlords of the manor were the de Vere family, the earls of Oxford, while the local lords (manorial tenants) were the Berners family. In 1577 a list of all the ports, havens, creeks and landing places on the Essex coast recorded a creek, three landing places and four customs deputies at Thorpe-le-Soken and Beaumont. One of those landling places is likely to have been near Beaumont Quay and another one at Landermere Wharf in Thorpe. Such landing places were used to export agricultural produce such as corn, hay, and cheese from local farms like Beaumont Hall to London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 16th century the manor passed to the crown, and in 1551 King Edward VI granted it to Sir Thomas Darcy of St Osyth. Ownership of the estate then descended in the Darcy family, who became the earls Rivers, until it passed, probably by sale, to Francis North, 2nd Baron Guildford (d. 1729). Shortly before he died Francis sold the estate and the quay to the governors of Guy&#039;s Hosptal, London. The governors were investing heavily in Essex property having been left the enormous sum of £220,000 (about £28 million in today&#039;s money) by Thomas Guy as an endowment for their institution. In 1727 they commissioned a survey of Beaumont Hall prior to their purchase, which not only recommended it as a very good buy, but noted that there were two &quot;very convenient landing places for bringing chalk rubbish from Kent and carrying of corn or any other thing off to London&quot;. This neatly describes the two-way traffic to London, with corn being taken to market and soil improvers being brought back as the return cargo - in this case chalk but just as often horse manure and &#039;night soil&#039;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1727 survey had also noted that the two landing places could only be used at very high tides, probably because the natural water channel of the Creek was rather shallow and emptied too quickly on the ebb. By the early 19th century agricultural production and yields had improved and the governors decided to invest in creating a more efficient quay. In 1831 London bridge was demolished and replaced, and Thomas Guy&#039;s Hospital acquired some of the old stone blocks which it transported to Beaumont to build a new quay in the following year. The quay was about 80 metres long, partly of stone (unmortared) and partly of timber. In addition, the governors paid for the digging of a new channel or canal called Beaumont Cut, two metres deep and about 1km long which linked the quay to deeper water in Hamford Water. A basin at the quay allowed barges or other vessels to turn around, and in 1848 it was described as navigable for vessels up to 70 tons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heyday of the quay was in the mid and later 19th century, when it saw a busy trade. There were buildings at the quay by 1838, probably including an arcaded brick warehouse that survived until the later 20th century. The tenant of Beaumont Hall, Mr Sewell, also built a kiln besides the quay, for the production of lime for agricultural purposes. The kiln ceased production in the mid 1920s, and the last trading barge used the quay in the 1930s. A 42-ton barge called the &lt;em&gt;Rose&lt;/em&gt;, built in 1880, was towed to the basin in the early 1960s for conversion to a house boat, but later became derelict and damaged in a fire. Its wreck is still visible, slowly subsiding into the mud. Some of the buildings at the quay were demolished soon afterwards, but one store house has survived as does the kiln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Moore, &#039;Beaumont Quay&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Colchester Archaeological Group Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, 54 (2014), pp.8-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Buckley, &#039;Lost and Found: The Archaeology of the Essex Coast&#039;, in A. Aberg and C. Lewis (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Rising Tide. Archaeology and Coastal Landscapes &lt;/em&gt;(Oxbow Books, 2000), pp. 5-16 (pp.10-11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. White&#039;s, &lt;em&gt;History, Gazetteer and Directory of the County of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1848).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office, D/DGh E1. Survey, 1727.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, SP12/117 (31), Oct. 1577. John Lord Darcy of Chiche and others. List of all ports, havens, creeks and landing places and list of deputies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map 1&quot; (1838 edition).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 14:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23907 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Gunfleet Estuary and Holland Haven</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/gunfleet-estuary-and-holland-haven</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Gunfleet was the name of the large estuary fed by the Holland River or brook, which formerly ran into the sea between Frinton and Little Holland. The name is probably Anglo-Saxon in origin, as the second element ‘fleet’ is derived from the Old English word fleot meaning ‘stream’ or ‘creek’. A similar well known example is the River Fleet in London, a tributary of the River Thames which was fed by streams on Hampstead Heath and which used to have a tidal inlet and docks at its lower end. The origin of the first element of the name ‘Gun’ is currently unknown, but it possibly derived from an Anglo-Saxon personal name, so the meaning of the whole name could be something like ‘Gunna’s creek’. An alternative suggestion that has been made is that the first part of the name could be a corruption from the Count of Guisnes who possessed the manor of Little Holland in 1210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the name was not recorded until 1320 when a vessel was shipwrecked on ‘Gunfletsond’, that is to say the Gunfleet Sands. It seems probable that a name originally applying to the estuary was appended to the sandbank that lay directly off the coast and opposite the estuary’s inlet. A map of 1584 in the British Library marks both the ‘Gonflet haven’ (the estuary) and the ‘ye gonflit’ (the sandbank). Other maps from that period, such as maps of Essex by Norden (1594) and Speed (1610) show the Gunfleet as a large, unreclaimed, estuary that was open to the sea at its southern end. The use of the name ‘haven’ would seem to imply the use of the estuary for trade, and the ‘Ganflete’ was also named as a port between Walton and St Osyth in Holinshed’s Chronicles (1586). The substantial marshlands along the estuary were also used by the inhabitants of surrounding parishes like Great and Little Holland as grazing for their sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1542 ‘the level of Gunflete haven’ was recorded, perhaps indicating that estuary’s marshland later known as Holland Levels had started to be reclaimed. Although the estuary continued to be marked on coastal maps and sea charts for a long time, it was becoming blocked perhaps by the effects of coastal erosion and long-shore drift. In 1677 a whale was stranded in the narrows at what was probably the entrance to the Gunfleet estuary then described as a ‘creek’. Probably soon afterwards it was decided to reclaim the estuary by constructing a sea wall across its mouth, with a sluice provided to allow the river water to drain away to sea. The intention was to prevent salt water entering the marshes along the Holland River, and thus to improve their agricultural potential and value. It is not known when the first wall was built, but in 1703 a survey was taken of ‘ye Levell or Flatts being several pieces or parcells of land endamaged by a breach at, or near Gunfleet Haven’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The records of the Tendring Levels Commissioners, a type of local government body charged with flood defence, survive from 1727 and show how they maintained the drained marshlands of the level, the sea wall and the sluice through which the Holland River then emptied into the open sea. By the 1760s the area was sufficiently drained to allow a new road link to cross the former estuary from Holland on Sea to Great Holland, although the extensive tracts of land were still liable to flood as shown by the marshes depicted on the Chapman and André map of 1777 and the one inch Ordnance Survey map (1838 edition). The Commissioners continued to be responsible for maintaining the sea wall and the Levels until the 1930s, and their maps reveal the outline of the old estuary through the land that had to pay rates to maintain the sea defences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources: P.H. Reaney, The Place-Names of Essex (1935), pp.13–17. K. Walker, various notes. Calendar of Close Rolls, Edw. II, A.D. 1318–23 (HMSO, 1895), p.249. Holinshed, An Historicall Description of the Iland of Britaine (1586), Book I, Chapter XVII: Of such ports and creeks as our sea-faring men doo note for their benefit upon the coasts of England. British Library, Ms cott. Aug. I.1, f. 44 (map, 1584) J. Norden, Speculi Britanniae Pars (1594), ed. H. Ellis (Camden Society, London, 1840), map. J. Speed, Map of Essex (1610) J. Chapman and P. André, A Map of Essex (1777). Ordnance Survey map, 1” to 1 Mile (1838) Essex Record Office, D/DHw E14, ‘A true Survey of ye Levell or Flatts’, 1703. ERO, D/ST 1 to 6, Tendring Levels Commissioners, minute books, 1727–1932 ERO, D/ST 17 to 20, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps, 1783 ERO, T/M 565/1, 2, Tendring Levels Commissioners, maps c.1901–25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2015 13:45:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23677 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
