<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Cornwall</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/cornwall</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Robert Stephen Hawker</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/robert-stephen-hawker</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Revd R S Hawker is mostly known for his eccentricities like his vicarage at Morwenstow and as the author of the Cornish anthem &#039;The Song of the Western Men&#039;, better known as &#039;Trelawney&#039; but he was a compassionate parish priest with an especial regard for seafarers and a published poet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a 19 year-old student he married a fellow poet Charlotte I&#039;Ans, a lady much older than himself but beautiful and accomplished with whom he lived happily until she died in 1863. Several of her poems were included in his published volumes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In London in 1864 he married a young governess Pauline Kucynski, daughter of Vincent Kucynski of the State Paper Office and stepdaughter of Henry Stevens, book dealer for the British Museum and the Smithsonian. They had three daughters Morwenna, Rosalind and Juliot, who became a nun and died in 1950. Hawker fell ill and moved to Plymouth for treatment. Having fulfilled a long-felt desire to be received into the Catholic Church he died on 15 August 1875 and was buried in Pennycross cemetery in Plymouth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to his published works many of his papers are at the Bodleian Library, Pembroke and Worcester Colleges in Oxford and at the British Library.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 09:22:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23162 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Thomas by Launceston</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-thomas-launceston</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is one of the three Launceston parishes our volunteers are currently working in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2012 16:17:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>CoralP</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20797 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Medieval Monasteries: Launceston</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/medieval-monasteries-launceston-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;rteleft&quot;&gt;The best-preserved plan of a medieval monastery in Cornwall is that of the Augustinian priory of Launceston. The priory originally stood at St Stephen-by-Launceston but was moved to a new site, south of the present St Thomas church, in 1155. It was dissolved by Henry VIII in 1539, and the buildings were later demolished. The site was excavated between 1886 and 1893, and the footings of the walls were discovered over a wide area. This enabled the priory plan to be reconstructed as it was at the end of its history in the early 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 07:14:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20691 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Medieval Monasteries: Launceston</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/medieval-monasteries-launceston</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;rteleft&quot;&gt;The best-preserved plan of a medieval monastery in Cornwall is that of the Augustinian priory of Launceston. The priory originally stood at St Stephen-by-Launceston but was moved to a new site, south of the present St Thomas church, in 1155. It was dissolved by Henry VIII in 1539, and the buildings were later demolished. The site was excavated between 1886 and 1893, and the footings of the walls were discovered over a wide area. This enabled the priory plan to be reconstructed as it was at the end of its history in the early 16th century.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 07:14:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20690 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Piran</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-piran</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;St Piran is a typical example of a legendary Cornish saint. His name is first recorded in 960 at Perranzabuloe, a name that means ‘Piran in the sand’, where the church was later believed to contain his bones. In the 12th or 13th century a Life of him was written in Latin for the church or for Exeter Cathedral, to which it belonged. The author of Life believed that Piran was identical with a similarly named Irish saint, St Ciáran, so he took Ciáran’s Life and made it the basis of Piran’s. He stated that Piran was a saint from Ireland who became a bishop, eventually sailed to Cornwall, made his home there, did many miracles, and died on 5 March.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2011 07:06:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20689 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Friars in Cornwall</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/friars-cornwall</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Friars are often underrated in local history because they have left fewer records than monks, and hardly any of their buildings survived the Reformation. And whereas monks in a monastery came from the neighbourhood and rarely left it, friars had wider careers. Their Cornish recruits were sent to study or serve elsewhere, and other men were brought from elsewhere to Cornwall. Much still needs to be done to list the friars who lived and worked in the county, and to discover where they came from and went to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2011 07:16:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20687 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Prayer-Book Rebellion</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/prayer-book-rebellion</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &#039;Prayer-Book&#039; or &#039;Western&#039; rebellion, was one of the most important attempts in England to oppose the Protestant Reformation during the reign of Edward VI (1547-53).  Most of the demands of the rebels involved undoing the anti-Catholic church reforms of Edward VI; they wanted to restore the old Latin services, belief in transubstantiation, confession to priests, and the celibacy of the clergy. It is worth considering that many, perhaps most, Cornish men did not take part in the rising, and might not have subscribed to all these demands either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12665 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Medieval church iconography - devotion to Jesus</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/medieval-church-iconography-devotion-jesus</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Artwork in Cornish churches illustrates devotion to God in the medieval period, paticularly portraits of Jesus. The passion of Christ is depicted in a late 15th century stained glass window in the north-east chapel of the church of St James and St Kew .  Chapels were dedicated to him as Christ, Jesus, or the Saviour.  In Cornwall these included ones at Padstow and Poruan near Fowey.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12664 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>St Germans Parish</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/st-germans-parish</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Prior to the Norman Conquest, the Saxon church was the cathedral of Cornwall, and set in beautiful surroundings the present building has a special atmosphere. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:31:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12038 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Helston Parish</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/helston-parish</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;St Michael&#039;s church is built on a medieval site, therefore there are likely to be medieval footings/foundations.  (Extract from questionnaire)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:31:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12037 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
