<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Bolsover</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/bolsover</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Local Government since 1834</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/local-government-1834</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Between 1834 and 1894 local government at parish level was gradually reformed. The changes were piecemeal and conservative in approach, so that the traditional units such as counties, boroughs, and parishes survived, even if their powers and duties were altered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12676 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Railways in the North Derbyshire Coalfield</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/railways-north-derbyshire-coalfield</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The earliest scheme for a modern, locomotive operated railway in the Derbyshire coalfield, proposed in 1832, was for a line running down the Erewash valley in the south-east of the county to compete with the canals linking the coalfield with Nottingham, Derby and the Trent. This was not built for some years but The major wave of railway promotion in the mid-1830s included a line which ran north from Derby through the Derwent and Amber valleys before tunnelling beneath the watershed to enter the Rother valley south of Chesterfield, and from there continue to Rotherham and Leeds. As soon as the North Midland Railway opened in 1840, branches were built to nearby pits and the modern history of mining in Clay Cross and neighbouring villages began.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12675 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>What do we mean by Bolsover? From ancient parish to district council</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/what-do-we-mean-bolsover-ancient-parish-district-council</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Definition of administrative geography.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12132 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bolsover: A Medieval New Town</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bolsover-medieval-new-town</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the 12th and 13th centuries, as the population and economy of England expanded, a large number of new towns were laid out in most parts of the country by either the Crown or private landowners. Some of these were completely new settlements, whose names do not appear at all in Domesday; others represented a major enlargement of an existing settlement, including the establishment of a market (a necessary pre-condition for the successful creation of a town) as well as an expansion of the built-up area. In Derbyshire, which was among the poorest and most thinly populated counties of England in this period, there appear to have been only two new towns of this sort, at Bolsover and Castleton, both associated with the Peverel family and their two castles. Elsewhere, landowners obtained grants to hold markets and fairs, which may have led to some new building (as for example at Higham where a new settlement was established on the main road to Derby some distance from the older manorial centre at Shirland) but did not lead to the creation of a town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image above shows part of William Senior&#039;s plan of Bolsover, surveyed in the 1630s, showing the layout of the town centre. (Welbeck Estate Co. Ltd.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12131 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Railway Excursions, 1931</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/railway-excursions-1931</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leaflet is one of many that would have been produced giving details of specal trains, services and tickets. In this case the leaflet refers to holiday return tickets available from stations over the old Lancashire, Derbyshire and East Coast Railway (LD &amp;amp; EC), in 1931.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the grouping of railways in 1923 (where numerous small companies were grouped into four), the Great Central Railway, who had absorbed the old LD &amp;amp; EC, became part of the London and North Eastern Railway (LNER).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite competition from local bus services the railways were still well-placed to offer competitive journey opportunities to longer destinations. This leaflet details the type of facilities such companies could offer to the holiday maker. Dated June 1931, the  LNER were offering &#039;Period Excursions&#039; through their travel agents Dean and Dawson. These &#039;holiday return tickets&#039; allowed travel at reduced rates, on special trains. Leaflets like this would be printed in their hundreds, bundled up and hung on string in station booking offices throughout the area that they applied.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12130 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Coal Industry after 1945</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/coal-industry-after-1945</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When coal was king! A National Coal Board advertisement of 1973 extolling the apparently indomitable strengths of the North Derbyshire coalfield, whose area headquarters was then the biggest white-collar employer in Bolsover, and whose pits were still looking for more miners.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of Chesterfield Local Studies Library&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12129 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Prehistoric and Roman Bolsover</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/prehistoric-and-roman-bolsover</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bolsover lies on a plateau of magnesian limestone, which creates a soil that is lighter and easier to cultivate than the heavy clay of the coal measures immediately to the west. This contrast means that today there is far more arable land than on the coal measures; historically it means that there is far more evidence for early settlement in Bolsover and parishes immediately to the north and south than in those to the west. Apart from the important Ice Age remains at Creswell Crags, the caves a few miles away to the north-east, prehistoric finds are relatively numerous across the whole of the limestone plateau. In Bolsover itself evidence has been found over a number of years in a garden in the town for a Mesolithic `narrow blade&#039; industry, where flint brought from elsewhere was worked into tools. Excavations in the grounds of the district council offices at Sherwood Lodge in 1992–3 found slight traces of both Mesolithic and Neolithic occupation, while a rock shelter at Whaley in the east of the parish has produced what appears to be a Neolithic female skull and some 35 sherds of Neolithic pottery. From the Bronze Age twelve small settlement sites were located during fieldwork in 1976–7 around Bolsover.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12128 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Recreation in Bolsover</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/recreation-bolsover</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Brass bands often became the heart of a community&#039;s social life alongside sport (primarily football and cricket).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image courtesy of Picture the Past www.picturethepast.org.uk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12127 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mills in Bolsover</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mills-bolsover</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lime Kiln Fields Mill was built in 1793 from limestone with sandstone. It is a four storey structure and now located in a residential garden. The original machinery used to work the kiln is well preserved inside this derelict, listed building. Image courtesy of Pitcure the Past www.picturethepast.org.uk&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12126 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cavendish Chapel - Interior</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cavendish-chapel-interior</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The interior of the Cavendish chapel built in 1618 as a final resting place for the tomb of Sir Charles Cavendish and his wife, Catherine Ogle. Cavendish chapel remained a burying place of the lords of Bolsover until modern times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:34:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12125 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
