<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Roman (AD43-410)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/period/roman-ad43-410</link>
 <description>AD43-410</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Beaumont Quay timeline</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/beaumont-quay-timeline</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Clacton VCH Group&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Clacton VCH Group / University of London&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Office document icon&quot; title=&quot;application/msword&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/x-office-document.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2015/04/23/beaumont_quay_-_timeline.doc&quot; type=&quot;application/msword; length=39424&quot;&gt;beaumont_quay_-_timeline.doc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 19:57:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23932 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Beaumont Quay</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/beaumont-quay</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The historic site known as Beaumont Quay is an important survival showing the nature of the small quays and wharves that were once very common and busy along the Essex coast. It is located right at the end of the tidal Landermere Creek, on the northern bank, which provided access for boats to Hamford Water and then to the North sea. The site is now owned by Essex County Council and is a scheduled ancient monument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Archaeological material has revealed settlement in this area in the Iron-Age, Roman and early medieval periods, as well as evidence for salt-making. There was probably also a landing place or wharf which served the large and valuable medieval manor of Beaumont Hall. In the Middle Age the overlords of the manor were the de Vere family, the earls of Oxford, while the local lords (manorial tenants) were the Berners family. In 1577 a list of all the ports, havens, creeks and landing places on the Essex coast recorded a creek, three landing places and four customs deputies at Thorpe-le-Soken and Beaumont. One of those landling places is likely to have been near Beaumont Quay and another one at Landermere Wharf in Thorpe. Such landing places were used to export agricultural produce such as corn, hay, and cheese from local farms like Beaumont Hall to London.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 16th century the manor passed to the crown, and in 1551 King Edward VI granted it to Sir Thomas Darcy of St Osyth. Ownership of the estate then descended in the Darcy family, who became the earls Rivers, until it passed, probably by sale, to Francis North, 2nd Baron Guildford (d. 1729). Shortly before he died Francis sold the estate and the quay to the governors of Guy&#039;s Hosptal, London. The governors were investing heavily in Essex property having been left the enormous sum of £220,000 (about £28 million in today&#039;s money) by Thomas Guy as an endowment for their institution. In 1727 they commissioned a survey of Beaumont Hall prior to their purchase, which not only recommended it as a very good buy, but noted that there were two &quot;very convenient landing places for bringing chalk rubbish from Kent and carrying of corn or any other thing off to London&quot;. This neatly describes the two-way traffic to London, with corn being taken to market and soil improvers being brought back as the return cargo - in this case chalk but just as often horse manure and &#039;night soil&#039;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1727 survey had also noted that the two landing places could only be used at very high tides, probably because the natural water channel of the Creek was rather shallow and emptied too quickly on the ebb. By the early 19th century agricultural production and yields had improved and the governors decided to invest in creating a more efficient quay. In 1831 London bridge was demolished and replaced, and Thomas Guy&#039;s Hospital acquired some of the old stone blocks which it transported to Beaumont to build a new quay in the following year. The quay was about 80 metres long, partly of stone (unmortared) and partly of timber. In addition, the governors paid for the digging of a new channel or canal called Beaumont Cut, two metres deep and about 1km long which linked the quay to deeper water in Hamford Water. A basin at the quay allowed barges or other vessels to turn around, and in 1848 it was described as navigable for vessels up to 70 tons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heyday of the quay was in the mid and later 19th century, when it saw a busy trade. There were buildings at the quay by 1838, probably including an arcaded brick warehouse that survived until the later 20th century. The tenant of Beaumont Hall, Mr Sewell, also built a kiln besides the quay, for the production of lime for agricultural purposes. The kiln ceased production in the mid 1920s, and the last trading barge used the quay in the 1930s. A 42-ton barge called the &lt;em&gt;Rose&lt;/em&gt;, built in 1880, was towed to the basin in the early 1960s for conversion to a house boat, but later became derelict and damaged in a fire. Its wreck is still visible, slowly subsiding into the mud. Some of the buildings at the quay were demolished soon afterwards, but one store house has survived as does the kiln.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Moore, &#039;Beaumont Quay&#039;, &lt;em&gt;Colchester Archaeological Group Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, 54 (2014), pp.8-12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Buckley, &#039;Lost and Found: The Archaeology of the Essex Coast&#039;, in A. Aberg and C. Lewis (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Rising Tide. Archaeology and Coastal Landscapes &lt;/em&gt;(Oxbow Books, 2000), pp. 5-16 (pp.10-11).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;W. White&#039;s, &lt;em&gt;History, Gazetteer and Directory of the County of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(1848).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Record Office, D/DGh E1. Survey, 1727.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The National Archives, SP12/117 (31), Oct. 1577. John Lord Darcy of Chiche and others. List of all ports, havens, creeks and landing places and list of deputies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ordnance Survey Map 1&quot; (1838 edition).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 23 Apr 2015 14:57:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23907 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Highworth pot</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/highworth-pot</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This Roman Highworth ceramic pot was discovered in the village of Highworth in June 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its location is just 4 miles away from &quot;Ermin Street&quot; which was a main Roman road which was a vital connection between the settlements of Gloucester, Silchester and Circencester. The pot was found with other smaller Roman artefacts and was positioned in an upright position suggesting it had been placed in the pit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is of a significant heavy weight as it takes several people to lift. The pot measures 2ft tall by 1 1/2 feet wide, with a 12 inch diameter mouth. The pot was used for storing milk this has been proven by the residue. It is going to be put on display in the Swindon Museum and Art Gallery.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2013 18:57:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21548 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Sarum</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/old-sarum</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Old Sarum And The Cathedral Foundations. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Becky Rousell&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Wiltshire &amp;amp; Swindon History Centre&lt;p&gt;An detailed view of Old Sarum from above showing the foundations of the cathedral that occupied on the site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2013/02/20/salisbury_p4649.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2540404&quot;&gt;salisbury_p4649.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21321 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Sarum</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-sarum</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum in Wiltshire is well known as notorious rotten borough pre the 1832 reform act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum was the original site of the settlement of Salisbury but the population moved to a nearby site as the original site was not big enough to satisfy the local needs. The rotten borough had 7 votes for just 3 houses and 1 MP represented these voters despite no MP’s for many of the new industrial cities such as Birmingham, Sheffield and Manchester. In the last election of 1831 11 votes were cast all from land owners who didn’t live in the borough.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The settlement moved a mile and a quarter to the south away from the natural hill fortress so the site could be easily expanded. It was mentioned in the doomsday book and was owned by the bishop of Salisbury the books mentions 50 hides and land for 32 ploughs in 1086. Cathedral foundations were found within the hill fort. The settlement was named as Sorbiodunum and was one of ten British cities that had particular privileges such as a castle and good roads. The city was established in 1220 in this new location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:27:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21320 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Eccles</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/eccles</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eccles is a village in the English county of Kent, part of the parish of Aylesford and in the valley of the River Medway.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;It is the site of a Roman villa estate and pottery kiln excavated between 1962 and 1976. It replaced an Iron Age settlement and was occupied until the end of Roman rule. The name &quot;Eccles&quot; comes from the Latin word &quot;ecclesia&quot; meaning church and suggests that a post-Roman Christian community existed in the village beyond the Roman withdrawal and into the Saxon period.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are two pubs in Eccles, The Walnut Tree and Red Bull. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eccles Row &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Eccles Farm&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Victoria Street East&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12341 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Romans in the Sunderland area</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/romans-sunderland-area</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no firm evidence of Roman settlement in Sunderland, with the main sites of occupation in the region being the Roman forts at Newcastle, South Shields and Chester-le-Street. Nevertheless, that there was some form of Roman activity in Sunderland is borne out by finds of coins, pottery fragments and a probable burial site in the area. Although some coins were unearthed in central Sunderland, the more significant discoveries were made on the north bank of the Wear, in Southwick and Fulwell and at the Carley Hill quarry where, in 1820, a bronze figurine of Jupiter Dolichenus, a Romano-British god, was found. A far more potentially significant sign of Roman activity in the area may have existed further downstream, at Hylton, where, until their removal in the mid-19th century, a series of massive stone blocks, known locally as the Brigg Stones, straddled the river not far from the route of the medieval ferry. A few stones, thought to have been part of this group, still survive and these show signs of what may have been Roman methods of construction, leading to suggestions that they may once have formed part of a Roman causeway or ford, linking the northern and southern banks of the river.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12215 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Prehistory Archaeology</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/prehistory-archaeology</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the area later occupied by Paul and its neighbouring parishes, prehistoric settlement was concentrated in the upland areas away from the coast. Here there are stone circles, fogous (underground passages), menhirs and burial mounds. Extensive marshes in the central part of the land beside Mount&#039;s Bay deterred habitation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finds from the neighbourhood of later Mousehole include a greenstone pounder from Raginnis of Neolitic date and a copper axe head from Penolva of the late Neolithic or early Bronze Age.  Bronze Age burial urns of c.2500-1400 BC were dug up in the south-west of the parish at Tresvennack and Trevelloe. The most intriguing, but now lost find was a gold lunula (neck ornament) from a high status site in Paul or Madron.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first identifiable settlements in Paul parish were Iron Age or Romano- British settlements  of c.150 BC-400AD. There was a hill fort at Tredavoe with 14 rounds (circular defensive enclosures). There was also a courtyard house found near to Castallack round.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:32:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12087 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
