<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Dulverton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/dulverton</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Ashwick Theatre, Dulverton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ashwick-theatre-dulverton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ashwick Theatre, also known as the Green Room or Music Room, was built by Yorkshire businessman Frank Green (d. 1953) in the grounds of Ashwick House. He was said to have moved to Ashwick House on medical advice to escape the polluted air of the industrial north. He was a wealthy bachelor who gave his house in York, the Treasurer’s House, to the National Trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He possibly missed the cultural life of York and so &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt;.1930 he had a music room or theatre built. Frank Green’s relations and staff were entertained there. The timber-clad building had a tiled roof and stood on staddle stones near the drive. It had a stage and a green room and was decorated with paintings, most famously the trompe d&#039;oeil boxes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After falling into decay it was restored with new roof and cladding and is part of the Moorland Mousie Trust’s lease of Ashwick stables and grounds and not normally open to the public. The building can be seen from the outside when visiting the Exmor Pony centre.&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2012 10:55:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20805 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton police station</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulverton-police-station</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dulverton has a had a series of police stations, the current building a purely utilitarian building but in 1904 a very grand building was designed and built in Lady Street to accommodate the police, their prisoners and the magistrates&#039; court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2011 13:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20615 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton&#039;s Hotels and Public Houses</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulvertons-hotels-and-public-houses</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lion Hotel, Dulverton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lion, formerly the Red Lion, on the corner of Bank Square and Union Street, is a lone survivor among Dulverton&#039;s hotels. Dulverton had ten licensed premises in 1790 including the Red Lion, the White Lion, the Ram, and the Lamb. Inns also functioned as auction houses especially for the sale or letting of farms. In 1795 the White Hart at Dulverton was the venue for the sale of four farms and c. 540 a. of land in Exton. In Dulverton between 1810 and 1816 there many homeless paupers who were housed in inns, including the Ram and the White Horse, at parish expense. Many public houses were beerhouses only and did not provide for travellers. There were many of these but only the Rock, a former smithy, and the Bridge survive. The Lion, formerly the Red Lion, and the Lamb, formerly the Ram, were as much hotels as public houses. During the early 20th century there were several private hotels serving the growing tourist trade including people who came to hunt and fish. They included the Green, which offered free fishing. The trend towards self-catering or bed and breakfast accommodation in farmhouses or small guesthouses has seen the closure of several small hotels, most recently the Carnarvon Arms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;MsoFootnoteText&quot;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11760 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Dulverton Town Hall and former Market House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/dulverton-town-hall-and-former-market-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dulverton Town Hall&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Market House, later Town Hall was built in 1866 to replace a derelict and much smaller market house. The lower hall had arches closed by gates on non-market days. The upper hall was used by the magistrates and for entertainments. Competition from the cattle market at Brushford after 1873 was partly responsible for the Dulverton market&#039;s decline and the building became of greater value as a Town Hall. In 1927 A E Richardson converted the building for that purpose adding the freestanding double external stair with wrought iron rails and lamps and canopied entrance porch. The arches were glazed and the former market hall became shops. The upper hall was fitted with a stage for plays and lectures and the room was later used as a cinema. The Town hall and its steps became the venue of all the town&#039;s occasions and probably its most photographed building.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:26:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11750 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
