<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Prehistoric (before AD43)</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/period/prehistoric-ad43</link>
 <description>before AD43</description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Holland Brook</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/holland-brook-0</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Holland Brook, sometimes called the Holland River, has been rather overlooked as an important landscape feature of Tendring Hundred (the older name for Tendring district). Even the original name of the watercourse is uncertain, although as the Holland Brook fed into the Gunfleet estuary that may record the original name of the river - the Gunfleet. The names Gunfleet Haven and Holland Haven both seem to refer to the original estuary that was later permanently reclaimed from the sea by the Tendring Levels Commissioners in the 17th and 18th centuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brook was regarded as important enough for its course to be described in versions of Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles dating from 1577 and 1587: &quot;Betwixt the Naze also and the mouth of the Colne, is another Ryll which riseth at Little Bentley, and thence goeth to Tendryng thorpe, thorow Clacten parke by great Holland, and east of little Holland into the deepe sea&quot;. The accurate description draws attention to the length of the watercoruse or &#039;rill&#039; from its source near Little Bentley and Little Bromley down to the sea at Little Holland, which virtually divided Tendring Hundred in half. Several features are worthy of note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the original Gunfleet estuary and the Holland Brook and its valley probably provided an important access route from the coast into the interior of Tendring Hundred both in prehistoric and later periods. There is considerable evidence from cropmarks for early settlement around the upper reaches of the brook in Tendring and neighbouring parishes. The brook may also have had an influence upon the later Anglo-Saxon and medieval patterns of settlement. It may, for example, be no coincidence that the brook leads to the parish of Tendring, which was the central place of the Hundred (the Hundred assembly met on Tendring Heath), and which name is probaby derived from a place-name in Germany transferred to this location by Anglo-Saxon migrants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the Holland Brook and the Gunfleet estuary later provided a considerable barrier to east-west road communications. A number of bridges were therefore eventually established, presumably starting furthest inland where the watercourse could be more easily bridged. That at Rice bridge, between Thorpe-le-Soken and Little Clacton, seems to have been present by the 14th century. Further downstream that at Fan bridge, between Great Holland and Little Clacton, was first recorded in 1509, and that at Holland bridge, between Great and Little Holland, in 1727 (after the former estuary had been reclaimed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the Holland brook and Gunfleet estuary were fed by a number of smaller streams in the parishes along their route, and the system effectively drained much of the centre of Tendring Hundred and many thousands of acres of farmland. Some of the tributary streams were quite small, but others like Picker&#039;s Ditch leading west from the Gunfleet towards Great Clacton were quite substantial. The potential for flooding was therefore very large, and after the Gunfleet or Holland Haven was reclaimed as marshland pasture by the Tendring Levels Commissioners they had to work hard expending money and enforcing maintenance upon local landowners to keep the channels clear so as to prevent major flooding incidents. Even in winter today the course of the brook and the old estuary is often marked by the flooded marshlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.H. Reaney, &lt;em&gt;The Place-Names of Essex &lt;/em&gt;(Cambridge, 1935), 17, 325, 351-2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norden&#039;s Map of Essex (1594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Map of Tendring Hundred from P. Morant, &lt;em&gt;The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex&lt;/em&gt;, I (1768).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holinshed&#039;s Chronicles: http://www.english.ox.ac.uk/holinshed/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essex Explore Asset under this heading: Map of land liable to flood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See other Explore Items on Rice bridge; Fan bridge; Holland bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 10:41:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ChrisT</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24091 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Joan Couch, Administration Bond, 1807</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/joan-couch-administration-bond-1807</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft Office document icon&quot; title=&quot;application/msword&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/x-office-document.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2015/03/18/couch_joan_17_nov_1807_adm_ap-c-4490.doc&quot; type=&quot;application/msword; length=33792&quot;&gt;couch_joan_17_nov_1807_adm_ap-c-4490.doc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 12:33:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AliceI</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23521 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Sarum</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/old-sarum</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Old Sarum And The Cathedral Foundations. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Becky Rousell&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Wiltshire &amp;amp; Swindon History Centre&lt;p&gt;An detailed view of Old Sarum from above showing the foundations of the cathedral that occupied on the site.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2013/02/20/salisbury_p4649.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2540404&quot;&gt;salisbury_p4649.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21321 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Old Sarum</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/old-sarum</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum in Wiltshire is well known as notorious rotten borough pre the 1832 reform act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Old Sarum was the original site of the settlement of Salisbury but the population moved to a nearby site as the original site was not big enough to satisfy the local needs. The rotten borough had 7 votes for just 3 houses and 1 MP represented these voters despite no MP’s for many of the new industrial cities such as Birmingham, Sheffield and Manchester. In the last election of 1831 11 votes were cast all from land owners who didn’t live in the borough.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The settlement moved a mile and a quarter to the south away from the natural hill fortress so the site could be easily expanded. It was mentioned in the doomsday book and was owned by the bishop of Salisbury the books mentions 50 hides and land for 32 ploughs in 1086. Cathedral foundations were found within the hill fort. The settlement was named as Sorbiodunum and was one of ten British cities that had particular privileges such as a castle and good roads. The city was established in 1220 in this new location.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 14:27:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>BeckyR</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21320 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Church of St Stephen, showing tower, from west</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/church-st-stephen-showing-tower-west</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Eric Berry&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;Church of St Stephen, showing tower, from west&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/%5Bsite-date-yyyy%5D/%5Bsite-date-mm%5D/%5Bsite-date-dd%5D/Church%20of%20St%20Stephen%2C%20showing%20tower%2C%20from%20west.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=1105758&quot;&gt;Church of St Stephen, showing tower, from west.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 16:14:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>EmilyD</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21156 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bronze brooch of horse and rider, found at Cold Kitchen Hill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/bronze-brooch-horse-and-rider-found-cold-kitchen-hill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Bronze brooch of horse and rider, found at Cold Kitchen Hill&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;WANHS&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;WANHS&lt;p&gt;A bronze brooch of a horse and rider found at Cold Kitchen Hill, of blue and red enamel. It is now part of the collections of the Wiltshire Heritage Museum, accession number: DZSWS:1988.266.7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2011/04/07/RG113.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=75486&quot;&gt;RG113.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 16:34:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20577 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Cold Kitchen Hill</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/cold-kitchen-hill</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cold Kitchen Hill stands at the centre of the Deverill valley. This modern place name is derived from the Celtic &lt;em&gt;Col Cruachen&lt;/em&gt;, the &#039;Hill of the Wizard&#039;.  The rich array of archaeological finds, including building materials, painted wall plaster, human bone, coins, jewellery and votive objects suggests a great temple complex stood there within a rectangular enclosure. This was in use from late Prehistory to the Romano-British period. A fine bronze figurine of Mercury, c. 80 mm x 23 mm across the shoulders, was found nearby.  The evidence suggests that Cold Kitchen Hill was the focal point of early settlement in the Deverill valley.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 16:32:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>AlexC</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20574 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The bones at Banwell</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/bones-banwell</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;The bones at Banwell&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Mary Siraut&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;The bones in the cave date from the Ice Age and are about 70,000 years old. They include bison, reindeer, scavenging wolves, arctic hares and foxes, red foxes, otters and an enormous species of brown bear much larger than those alive today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2010/05/20/Banwell_bone_cave_016.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2670432&quot;&gt;Banwell_bone_cave_016.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2010 13:50:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20135 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bone display, Banwell</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/bone-display-banwell</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-body&quot;&gt;Bone display, Banwell&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Asset Author:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;Mary Siraut&lt;div class=&quot;label-inline&quot;&gt;Copyright:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;University of London&lt;p&gt;One of William Beard&#039;s arrangements of the prehistoric bones.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;label-above&quot;&gt;Asset File:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;file&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;file-icon&quot; alt=&quot;Image icon&quot; title=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; src=&quot;/explore/modules/file/icons/image-x-generic.png&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/sites/explore/files/explore_assets/2010/05/20/Banwell_bone_cave_015.jpg&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg; length=2360830&quot;&gt;Banwell_bone_cave_015.jpg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2010 13:42:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20133 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Banwell Caves</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/banwell-caves</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The village of Banwell in the Mendips is in an area rich in caves but the most famous is probably the Banwell bone cave discovered in 1824. Miners were trying to locate a stalactite cave, first discovered in 1757 but lost to a landslip, at the instigation of the vicar who thought paying visitors might produce much needed funds for a school in the parish.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The caves were on an estate owned by George Henry Law, bishop of Bath and Wells who seeing the vast number of ancient animal bones in the newly discovered cave thought they were the remains of the animals that died in Noah&#039;s flood.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cave attracted visitors and the bishop had the grounds laid out with follies and grottos labelled with tablets bearing religious verses. Many of the rich and famous as well as local people came to see the caves and accommodation was provided on the site, now a private house. Bishop Law retired to the house just before his death in 1845.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The caves were managed by William Beard until 1865 when he retired aged 93. It was he who was responsible for the elaborate arrangement of the bones within the caves. Many bones were given away or taken as souvenirs by visitors and have ended up in many collections.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The caves are occasionally opened to the public by the Banwell Caves Heritage Group and are still lit largely by candles as they were when first discovered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2010 13:36:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20132 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
