<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Gardens</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/gardens</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Ashcombe, Simonsbath</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ashcombe-simonsbath</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ashcombe, Simonsbath is the valley of a tributary stream of the Barle river on Exmoor. It contains the overgrown remains of a designed, romantic landscape about which little is known.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jul 2015 10:27:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24583 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Parham House Gardens</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/parham-house-gardens</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The gardens and grounds at Parham House are featured in this section. It includes quotations about the work of the gardeners in the 1920s and 1930s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Image supplied courtesy of English Heritage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12609 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Billo Crown and Bristol - The Huguenots</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/billo-crown-and-bristol-huguenots</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This brass crown dating from the early 1700&#039;s, was probably used as a ceremonial piece for trades processions in Bristol. It was made by Francis Billo, who was thought to be a Bristol Huguenot. The Huguenots were French Protestant refugees who fled from France from the 1680&#039;s to escape oppression by the French authorities who wished to force them to convert to Catholicism. Bristol welcomed some 400 Huguenots.Billo later went on to become well known in the West Country for his metal chandeliers. Another Huguenot refugee who came to Bristol and then went to America was Solomon Egare who became a renowned silversmith. Most Huguenots were mariners or weavers and some, like Billo, skilled metal workers. However, when they first arrived from France, having been smuggled out on illegal boats, many Huguenots were exhausted and often penniless and unable to speak English. Some, unable to find work, camped out in Bristol&#039;s streets, but sympathetic residents (including Quakers and some Anglicans) raised funds for them and they eventually found their feet or emigrated to London, Ireland or America.A few of these Huguenots, came from wealthy merchant families from La Rochelle and other French Atlantic ports (these includes families included the Peloquins, the Laroche and the Goizin families). Their trading contacts in America with other Huguenot and Dutch merchants ensured they quickly established themselves in the Atlantic economy and contributed substantially to the city&#039;s prosperity. The nature of the economy in the early eighteenth century meant much of their trade involved slave-produced goods and sometimes enslaved Africans themselves. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11865 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Queen Square</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/queen-square</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Queen Square has always been popular with rich merchants and traders. In 1775 seven merchants who traded with Africa, one merchant in the West Indian trade and a firm of tobacco merchants from Virginia in North America lived in the Square. Some interesting events in Bristol history have taken place in the square: for example many of the buildings in one section were burned down during the Bristol Riot in 1831, which began after protests about the refusal of the Government to allow ordinary men to vote in elections. During the Second World War (1939-1945) bombing in 1940 and 1941 during the Bristol Blitz destroyed a number of the buildings. Only recently has the road across the centre of the square been removed to restore the original design.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:29:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11833 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
