<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Taunton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/taunton</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>52 North Street, Taunton: grocer&#039;s shop</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/52-north-street-taunton-grocers-shop</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number 52 North Street, Taunton has been a grocery store for at least 180 years. The building has medieval origins but has been virtually rebuilt several times. It was kept by grocer John Christopher Easton, a member of the famous Easton family of Bradford on Tone, better known for engineering. By 1851 he was assisted by John Barter of Kingskerswell in Devon and by 1861 the business was a partnership of Easton and Barter with Mr Easton retiring to the Priory in Taunton St James parish and John Barter living over the shop with his family, assistants and servants. Following Easton’s death in 1865 John Barter took on another Kingskerswell man John Duder a farmer’s son who had worked as a grocer in his home village. By 1870 they were partners in the business and John Barter moved out of 52 to Mount Terrace leaving the accommodation over the store to John Duder and his family and the three male staff. In 1888 the premises were greatly altered to add warehousing accommodation. John Duder died in 1911.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2018 11:06:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25665 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>A Taunton vicar&#039;s letters from the front</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/taunton-vicars-letters-front</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A remarkable correspondence had begun by 1915 between parishioners and the vicar of Taunton St Mary Magdalene and other church officers. Although the originals are missing many were copied into the parish magazine or extracts were printed. There were letters about killed and missing men, appeals for food from prisoners of war and sometimes quite graphic accounts of life in the trenches. There were letters from France, Burma and naval ships.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jul 2018 13:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25527 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Julia Blackmore dentist of Taunton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/julia-blackmore-dentist-taunton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long before any woman formally qualified in dentistry Taunton had a female dentist. Most dentists learnt on the job assisting a dentist or serving an apprenticeship. The first woman to be licensed to practice dentistry in England was Lilian Lindsey in 1895, over half a century after Julia Blackmore began work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 09:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25251 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mary Sweet and her Hotel</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mary-sweet-and-her-hotel</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mary Sweet was the creator of the western side of the present Castle Hotel, Taunton in the 1830s. She gave Taunton probably its first luxury hotel. She was one of many female hoteliers in Somerset in the mid 19th century creating high-class family hotels often out of traditional inns or as  in Mary’s case creating a new business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 12:31:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25246 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Taunton St Mary non communicants</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/taunton-st-mary-non-communicants</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The post Reformation church was concerned that people attended church for political as much as for religious reasons. Non-attenders were regularly presented in the church courts and could be find heavily, especially those who stayed away for religious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At St Mary Magdalene, Taunton in the 1590s the authorities tried apparently unsuccessfully to enforce the taking of Easter communion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2015 10:38:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23555 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Somerset Heritage Centre</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/somerset-heritage-centre</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Somerset Heritage Centre was built in 2010 on a huge brownfield site in the Silk Mills area of Taunton in the parish of Norton Fitzwarren. The site is bounded by the main West Country railway line on the south, the present main Taunton to Wiveliscombe and Bampton road on the north, the Back Brook on the east and the former Taunton Cider Works, now being redeveloped for housing, on the west.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until the 20th century this was a largely agricultural area but the Back Brook, ancient boundary between the parishes of Norton Fitzwarren west and Staplegrove east was an ideal source of power for mills. Flowing down from the Quantocks hills and fed by many tributaries it has a good flow of water even in draught stricken 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best known mill on the watercourse was the Back Brook silk mill later the Staplegrove factory, which despite many changes of use, was popularly known as the silk mills, and gave that name to the adjoining road and the area around. The name survives although the mill buildings were demolished and the site now lies under the embankment of the new line of the Silk Mills Road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fields west of the mill site continued in agricultural use until the Second World War when they were cleared and levelled to create the largest military supply depot in South-West England. It took only two months to build and was known as 3 Supply Depot when in the care of the RASC, later the Royal Army Ordnance Corps. In 1942 it became the American Army’s G 50. It had its own railway sidings as did a smaller depot east of the Silk Mills Road and now the site of Bindon Road business and retail parks. Other depots and camps were situated to the north around Courtlands House and Norton Manor including a prisoner of war camp. Some of those properties still belong to the Ministry of Defence notably Norton Manor Camp, home of 40 Commando of the Royal Marines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the closure of the supply depot in 1966 its buildings were used as a trading estate, the enormous sheds, some of them triple units, providing cheap warehousing and storage for buses and lorries. In the early 21st century pressure for redevelopment led to the destruction and clearance of most of the site to create a large business and trading estate, c. 500 new homes, green areas and a new road system to bypass Norton Fitzwarren. By 2010 only about four wartime stores survived and a few other structures. One of the earliest new arrivals on the site was the Somerset Heritage Centre built on the site of the depot&#039;s railway sidings.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2010 08:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20229 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
