<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Health</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/item-category/health</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>Basingstoke Probate Material 1691-1700</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-probate-material-1691-1700</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this period the probate documents of 18 inhabitants of Basingstoke have been selected to reflect the range of occupations in the town, some show the move to brewing following the decline of the cloth industry. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;15 wills and 11 inventories have been transcribed by the Wills Group of the New Victoria County of Hampshire project based in Basingstoke. These transcriptions have been made from copies of original probate documents supplied by Hampshire Record Office and The National Archives. Words have been modernized and punctuation added to make reading easier but names have been transcribed as written. Words in italics indicate omissions in the original document which have been added to make sense of the text. Words in square brackets indicate that they have been transcribed as seen but where the meaning is unclear. Basingstoke is described as being in the county of Southampton, the old name for Hampshire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Links to the documents are below and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/Node/21292&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;glossary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is attached of unusual words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/inventory-john-browne-victualler-1691&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John  Browne, victualler (Inventory), 1691&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-inventory-and-renunciation-john-wareham-bricklayer-1691&quot;&gt;John Wareham, bricklayer (Will, Inventory and Renunciation), 1691&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-william-hall-clerk-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Hall, clerk (Will and Inventory), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-henry-stone-gunsmith-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Henry Stone, gunsmith (Will and Inventory), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-richard-watmorewattmore-clothier-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Wattmore/Watmore, clothier (Will and Inventory), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-samuel-astin-tanner-1692&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Samuel Astin, tanner (Will), 1692&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/inventory-richard-knight-yeoman-1693&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Knight, yeoman (Inventory), 1693&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-richard-jeyes-yeoman-1693-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Richard Jeyes, yeoman (Will and Inventory), 1693&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-bourneborne-scrivener-1694&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Bourne/Borne, scrivener (Will), 1694&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-box-innholder-1694&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Box, innholder (Will), 1694&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/renunciation-and-inventory-joseph-windover-collarmaker-1694&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joseph Windover, collarmaker (Renunciation and Inventory), 1694&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-edmund-cowdry-collarmaker-1695&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edmund Cowdry, collarmaker (Will and Inventory), 1695&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-thomas-edwards-tanner-1696&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Thomas Edwards, tanner (Will and Inventory), 1696&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-john-rogers-clerk-1696&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;John Rogers, clerk (Will), 1696&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-michaell-acton-clerk-1697&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michaell Acton, clerk (Will), 1697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-joseph-mooreing-gentleman-1698&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Joseph Mooreing, gentleman (Will), 1697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-and-inventory-robert-lancaster-glover-1699&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robert Lancaster, glover (Will and Inventory), 1699&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/assets/will-william-spencer-clothier-1699&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;William Spencer, clothier (Will), 1699&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2018 12:58:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25628 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Julia Blackmore dentist of Taunton</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/julia-blackmore-dentist-taunton</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long before any woman formally qualified in dentistry Taunton had a female dentist. Most dentists learnt on the job assisting a dentist or serving an apprenticeship. The first woman to be licensed to practice dentistry in England was Lilian Lindsey in 1895, over half a century after Julia Blackmore began work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 09:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">25251 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Feilding Palmer Cottage Hospital</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/feilding-palmer-cottage-hospital</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feilding Palmer Cottage Hospital in Lutterworth opened in 1899, and remains open as a hospital in 2015, providing heathcare services to the local community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2015 10:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>PamF</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">24659 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>BASINGSTOKE TOWN, SANITARY CONDITIONS AND INFECTIOUS DISEASE  IN 1866</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/basingstoke-town-sanitary-conditions-and-infectious-disease-1866</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;These pages were missing from the Minute Books of the Basingstoke Poor Law Union in 1866, where the reports for the outlying parishes were transcribed in full (see separate item on VCH Explore), but turned up in The National Archives inserted into the correspondence for September 1871, along with William Ranger&#039;s &lt;em&gt;Report to the General Board of Health on the Borough of Basingstoke&lt;/em&gt; of 1853 and Dr Ballard&#039;s &lt;em&gt;Report upon the Sanitary Condition of Basingstoke&lt;/em&gt; of 1871.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These three items were undoubtedly grouped together because in 1871 sanitary conditions in Basingstoke - as in many Victorian towns and cities - were particularly bad. With the new Local Government Board, the new Urban Sanitary Authority (the Town Council) and the Rural Sanitary Authority (Basingstoke Poor Law Union) were established, and they became involved in trying to deal with this; consequently these items co-exist along with copious amounts of correspondence relating to the problem, which inevitably involved bad conditions in the Basingstoke Canal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, on its own, is a subject for further study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TNA, MH 12/10683,  Correspondence between the Local Government Board and Basingstoke Union, 1871 to 1872 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2013 08:27:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22613 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Park Prewett Hospital, Basingstoke</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/park-prewett-hospital-basingstoke</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Victorian Asylum to Psychiatric Hospital&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Park Prewett Hospital has an interesting history, initially planned as an overspill for the Victorian asylum Knowle Hospital in Fareham. It took several years to get going from its original idea in 1898, and then nearly ground to a halt in 1914 due to war-induced lack of resources, finance and manpower. However, the Army took over and the buildings were in use as a military hospital, with its own railway spur from the town, by 1916.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the wars Park Prewett reverted to a mental hospital, enhancing and expanding until it held 1,300 patients in 1939. Its rather elegant, Italianate red brick buildings somewhat belied the grim, institutional interiors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the start of WW2, all mental patients were evacuated and the hospital again reverted to war work for the duration. Facilities were established in London hospitals and the famous plastic surgeon, Sir Harold Gillies, moved into Rooksdown House, Basingstoke where he remained until 1952. The hospital was a big clearing-station for the Normandy landings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story of Park Prewett then reflects the changes in mental health care, with new drugs and treatments, short-term and outpatient care, and eventually care in the community. By 1996 it had become obsolete, its campus became a conservation area, and it became the core of a new housing development, some of it using the old buildings themselves, including the iconic landmark Water Tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A timeline, pictures and references are attached.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2013 12:32:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21854 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>William White, apothecary of Basingstoke, died 1636</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/william-white-apothecary-basingstoke-died-1636</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;William White, an apothecary (pharmacist) made his own potions and remedies to sell to the people of Basingstoke and the surrounding villages. He kept a fascinating range of remedies and ingredients in his shop in 1636. Apart from items like raisins, which were clearly imported, a number of the items in Mr White’s shop appear in the list of imported drugs shown in the Act of Parliament (1656 ch.20) entitled, &lt;em&gt;A Book of Values of Merchandize imported, according to which Excise is to be paid by the first Buyer.&lt;/em&gt; This indicates that he was buying those items from merchants, almost certainly in London, and arranging for them to be transported to Basingstoke.The purpose of each has been researched in 17th century and modern sources. The full list is attached as an asset including references to Nicolas Culpepper who, in his &lt;em&gt;Complete Herbal&lt;/em&gt; published 1636, suggested that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-   hops were used for many complaints such as cleansing the blood, preventing and treating skin conditions such as ringworm, to get rid of intestinal worms, cure jaundice etc.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-   saffron was an excellent remedy when used to treat epidemical diseases such as plague, smallpox and measles.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-   liquorice was useful in a great number of complaints, including respiratory problems such as TB, urinary troubles and irritation of the eyes.  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2013 15:49:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21543 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sanitary Inspectors&#039; Reports in Basingstoke Union in the 1860s showing conditions and infectious disease</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sanitary-inspectors-reports-basingstoke-union-1860s-showing-conditions-and-infectious-disease</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a new initiative to prevent the spread of infectious diseases from dirty conditions following the Diseases Prevention Act of 1855; the link between dirty water and bad sanitation and diseases like cholera had been accepted, although the mechanism was not understood. Union Medical Officers all over England were sent out into their Districts to report on the sanitary conditions of the people in their parishes, and fortunately their reports are copied into the Minute Books of Basingstoke Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports give a revealing insight into the living conditions of ordinary people in much of this rural Union in 1866, some statistics on illness and mortality, and including odd bits of information on specific locations and parishes, distribution of cottages and their occupation, land drainage and sanitary conditions in Monk Sherborne and Worting village schools. Each doctor has his own style of reporting, but the resulting outcomes are basically the same - things were grim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reports for the town of Basingstoke are presented in a separate item. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reports for the Districts of the Union with their parishes are transcribed here, with an index page. Note that some place names are in contemporary spelling and are different from modern ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HRO,  PL3/5/12   Minute Book for Basingstoke Union  Apr 1865 to Jul 1869&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 14:13:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>JeanM</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21451 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Overton House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/overton-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Overton House, rebuilt in brick for the local surgeon in the early 19th century. It stands next to St Peter’s churchyard, probably on the site of a much older house, known as Hungerford House in the 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overton House was built almost entirely of red brick with stone quoins on the site of Hungerford House, which is mentioned in the 1776 manorial survey as being close to St Peter’s church. It seems to retain the cellar of the older house. It was almost certainly built for the Codford surgeon, Isaac Flower, and his family, residents wealthy enough to have needed the separate service wing, a gig house converted from a cob, and a stone outhouse.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:45:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12639 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Almshouses in Burford</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/almshouses-burford</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Great or Warwick Almshouses, founded 1455-6. (Photo by Mike Hesketh-Roberts, English Heritage)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most conspicuous charitable act in late medieval Burford was the foundation in 1455–6 of the &lt;strong&gt;Great Almshouse&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;Warwick Almshouses&lt;/strong&gt;) near the church, for eight poor persons. The founder was the Burford burgess and wool merchant Henry Bishop, acting in cooperation with the earl of Warwick (who was then lord of Burford). The initiative was part of a broader trend in late medieval England, which saw endowed almshouses founded in several small towns. A 19th-century datestone gives the date 1457.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After the Reformation’s townspeople continued to make charitable provision in a humanistic spirit. The mercer Simon Wisdom endowed &lt;strong&gt;Wisdom&#039;s Almshouse&lt;/strong&gt; on Church Lane in the 1580s, and in 1726 the prominent Burford physician John Castle (of The Great House) founded &lt;strong&gt;Castle’s Almshouses&lt;/strong&gt; in Guildenford, to house 4 poor widows. Most gifts for the poor were more modest bequests of money for investment, designed to supplement the parish’s poor rates. Donors often hedged their bequests with particular requirements, designed to target the so-called ‘deserving poor’.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In more recent times, &lt;strong&gt;Price&#039;s Almshouses&lt;/strong&gt; at the top of The Hill were founded in 1897 by Miss Charlotte Anne Price, a daughter of the solicitor James Scarlett Price. Three cottages were to be built  &#039;in the Elizabethan style&#039;, each one housing a &#039;suitable aged or infirm woman&#039;. &lt;strong&gt;Briggs’ Almshouses&lt;/strong&gt; in Sweeps Lane were endowed by Katherine M Briggs in 1966. Briggs was an eminent folklorist and long-term Burford resident, who lived in the Barn House to the rear of Calendars on Sheep Street). The building follows the Cotswold vernacular tradition, with uncoursed rubblestone and a stone slate roof. Features include a pair of three-light stone-mullioned windows under a drip moulding, and doorways with plain Tudor arches.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read more&lt;/strong&gt; in the EPE Book &lt;em&gt;Burford: Buildings and People in a Cotswold Town&lt;/em&gt; by A Catchpole, D Clark and RB Peberdy (2008)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See also: R and J Moody, A Thousand Years of Burford (2007), 10, 79, 82-3, 138.; RH Gretton, The Burford Records (1920), 200, 359–62, 484–508.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12558 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ledbury Community Health and Care Centre</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ledbury-community-health-and-care-centre</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ledbury Community Health and Care Centre was opened in 2002. It was built on the site of disused property on the corner of Bye Street and Market Street. This area had been used as a  market and for commercial purposes for centuries. While the site was being cleared archaeologists maintained a watching brief.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Health Centre replaced the Ledbury Cottage Hospital. is managed by the Herefordshire Primary Health Care Trust.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:39:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12300 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
