<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Watchet</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/locality/watchet</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>New war memorial Watchet</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/new-war-memorial-watchet</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The town of Watchet did not have its own war memorial recording the names of those killed in the First World War until 2014. As in some other communities it had been decided to create a recreation ground instead, the Memorial Ground. A sports pavilion and stand were dedicated to the memory of the fallen in July 1929.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, with the approach of the centenary of the start of the First World War the Watchet Remembrance Project began to create a memorial to the men of the town killed in both the First and Second World Wars. It was unveiled on the 28 June 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Appropriately it stands in a small paved garden beside the library facing the railway station from which most of the men would have left the town, never to return.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 08:40:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">23110 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Watchet&#039;s railways</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/watchets-railways</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watchet was formerly the terminus of two railway lines. The West Somerset Mineral Railway brought iron ore from the Brendon hills for shipment to South Wales replacing the laborious cart route to Minehead harbour. In 1862 the West Somerset Railway linked the reconstructed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/watchet-harbour&quot;&gt;harbour&lt;/a&gt; with Taunton and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 11:42:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22252 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Watchet Harbour</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/watchet-harbour</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=117145&quot;&gt;small town&lt;/a&gt; on the Bristol Channel has always looked to the sea and there has probably been a harbour here for centuries; the Danes attacked Watchet in the 10th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watchet&#039;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=117145#s4&quot;&gt;trade&lt;/a&gt; was mainly coastal but there were foreign shipments and in the 20th century substantial trade with Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The harbour today is largely as built in the 1860s by James Abernethy with a modern marina inserted in the eastern part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the late 19th and early 20th centuries the harbour was served by two &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/watchets-railways&quot;&gt;railway&lt;/a&gt; lines.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 13:06:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22113 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Watchet&#039;s industrial past</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/watchets-industrial-past</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like many harbour towns Watchet developed several small industries. The opportunity to bring in raw materials and export finished products gave entrepreneurs confidence. Among the varied industries were those like shipbuilding connected with the sea, milling using local produce and adding value before sending it to Bristol or South Wales and limeburning and metal working where the raw materials could be brought in cheaply to create products needed locally. The arrival of the railways in the mid 19th century encouraged further dreams of industrial wealth but the late 20th century saw the closure of many small businesses and the loss of the harbour and railway for commercial goods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly the paper mill closed on 24 December 2015. Efforts are being made to record it and its recent history and the archives are being assessed for long-term preservation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more about the economy of the area dip into volume five of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=117145#s4&quot;&gt;Victoria County History of Somerset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 10:16:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22108 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>The Ancient Mariner</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ancient-mariner</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fictional Ancient Mariner is among the most well-known English seamen and it is fitting that he should be rembered in the town that inspired his creation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 09:27:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">22103 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Watchet Alabaster</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/watchet-alabaster</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Walking, carefully, on the beach below the cliffs from Watchet&#039;s West Beach to Blue Anchor you can see huge falls of rock in which shine bright fragments of white, salmon pink and black rock. That is Watchet alabaster, a very fine-grained gypsum still prized by sculptors. In the 17th century it was sought after as a substitute for marble to build monuments and church fittings and large quantities must have been shipped from Somerset, possibly helping to destroy the cliffs that now face a losing battle with the sea and the rain that saturates the mudstone of which they are largely formed. By the 19th century only smaller blocks were available but it was still used to decorate fire surrounds as well as being ground for gypsum plaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2013 08:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21869 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Yankee Jack</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/yankee-jack</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watchet’s seamen included many characters of whom the fictional &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ancient-mariner&quot;&gt;Ancient Mariner&lt;/a&gt; is the most well known but Yankee Jack was a real mariner called John Short. His wonderful singing voice and amazing vocal memory, even as an old man, impressed Cecil Sharp. Thanks to Yankee Jack many of our best loved sea songs were published and preserved including versions of &lt;em&gt;Shallow Brown&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Shenandoah&lt;/em&gt;. He was one of the last of the shantymen who sang for his fellow sailors giving them the rhythms for turning the capstan and hoisting sails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about Watchet harbour in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=117145&amp;amp;strquery=watchet%20harbour#s1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Victoria County History of Somerset V&lt;/a&gt; and see local boats at the Watchet Boat Museum just a short walk from Yankee Jack&#039;s statue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2013 08:19:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>MaryS</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">21862 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
