<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore"  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel>
 <title>VCH Explore - Bristol</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/county/bristol</link>
 <description></description>
 <language>en</language>
<item>
 <title>29 Queen Square</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/29-queen-square</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;English Heritage now have their regional headquarters at number 29 and it is the best preserved of the original buildings in the square. This is illustrated by its forecourt gates and railings and internal panelling and staircase. The house was built in 1709 for Alderman Nathanial Day who part owned a number of slave ships and who later became Bristol&#039;s Mayor in 1737. Day petitioned against a proposed tax on slaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By mid century, number 29 was the home of Henry Bright, a prominent Merchant Venturer and slave trader. On his death in 1771 he left &quot;an annuity of £10 per annum, chargeable on the house where I now dwell, to my black servant, Bristol&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2010 10:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">20217 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Bristol&#039;s 18th-century Jewish community</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/bristols-18th-century-jewish-community</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;By 1766 Bishop Newton recorded a total of 42 Jews in the city, 40 of whom lived in Temple. Whilst the synagogue provided the focus for most of the community, there were others who must have assimilated into society at large. However, very few Jews seem to have formally converted to the Church of England, if the baptismal records are trustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the law, descendants of any mixed faith marriage would not be considered Jews.  Records indicate, however, exceptions were made and family names were not reliable means to trace families, thus making the task of tracing Jewish heritage in Bristol difficult. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12694 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Apprentices</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/apprentices</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the period 1532 to 1552 a total of 3,139 apprentices were registered, of whom 766 came from within Bristol, and 456 from Wales. Welsh apprentices therefore constituted 14.5 per cent overall, but 19.2 per cent of non-Bristolians. A large number of Welsh masters took on Welsh apprentices; these examples indicate some form of prior connection, either familial or commercial. In general, however, the lack of an exact correlation between the family and ethnic background of the majority of masters and apprentices strongly suggests that there was no general desire for Welsh youngsters to be apprenticed within an ex-patriot community: there was no Welsh ghetto in early-modern Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, many youngsters in hopes for an apprenticeship come from the smaller towns of South Wales.  Carmarthenshire contained one of the three largest towns in Wales, yet only 26 came to Bristol.  However, 84 came from Pembrokeshire in the far west.  Perhaps this is due to the good communications between Pembrokeshire and Bristol.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:46:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">12693 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Joyce Morris-Wisdom</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/joyce-morris-wisdom</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The March, 1963&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘Prior to the march, which started from City Road to Broadmead, Paul requested permission from the School, which in turn requested permission from my Mother, to be absent from school that day in order to participate in the march. [I wanted] ... to be marked present for lessons ... [as I felt] my involvement ... would help me when I became older [as it] would enable me to have a better understanding of public ... protests and where possible even help me to take part in public speak[ing] ...I was obviously nervous but excited as well and felt valued that I was asked to participate in such a life-changing event. [I] did not hesitate to agree, as a matter of fact I felt really honoured. I left as if I was attending school as usual, we met and were briefed about what we should and should not do and emphasised that all activity would be peaceful.I remembered holding a plac[ard] ... to the effect “END RACISM ON THE BUSES” with a Police Officer mounted on a chestnut coloured horse situated on my right hand and Paul and the others on my left and in the middle.  I felt frightened and intimidated even though the march was peaceful, because the crowd and on-lookers were hostile and I was unsure how and what the Police would [do] [or if they would] protect us if we were attacked. I even thought about that if we were attacked what would I do, run, stand still or take refuge with the elders.  I had no idea what would be the best idea to do and what the result would be.We marched from City Road passed Dockland Settlement Club into Broadmead to The Bay Horse Pub.  Although still overwhelmed by it all I felt proud and excited that I was able to do such a task, for myself and the community, and delighted that I held my nerves and took part in something so peaceful but changed the course of history for not only us as African Caribbeans but for our children and future non-white immigrants. My Mother and I talked about the outcome of the march as we did prior to the event and missing school.  She praised me and again I felt honoured by her praise and Paul’s faith in me that I could handle the situation.When I went back to school nothing much [was] said about being absent … [or about] the march particularly from the Teachers. I was glad because I am not sure what I would have said, because the school system was not much different from the public’s perception of us as Black people from the Caribbean born under the English rule and not as slaves.  I have from time to time told others including my children, grandchildren and young people whom I have worked with both commissioned and uncommissioned work as part of my role about the march.  I even devised a crossword puzzle with the information in it including Rosa Parks, Martin Luther King and others, particularly Paul Stephenson’s role in improving employment prospects especially people wanting to work on the buses.My family and I are delighted that Paul has finally been honoured for all the hard work he has done for the community and here in the City and County of Bristol.  I was fortunate to attend his Award for the Freedom of the City and County of Bristol as well as his OBE Celebratory Event [in 2009].Finally I believe there will be a photo of myself in the newspaper clippings of the march, although I am unable to find it … I have also seen a photo of a Black female in one of the March newspaper clippings but no other and … [there were] certainly more than 2 of us … females.’Joyce Morris Wisdom, who later trained in Youth Work under the guidance of Paul Stephenson, is currently studying Mandarin Chinese at the University of the West of England.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11917 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Ahmed Duale</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/ahmed-duale</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Ahmed Duale first arrived in Britain in 1991, he thought the war at home would be over in a few days, but as he observed, ‘everyone I knew was coming out’. He was luckier than most - he was well connected. His father was a chief, his uncle a head teacher and Ahmed had recently graduated with a good degree in English literature from Somalia National University. His promising career as a junior diplomat in the foreign office enabled him to leave war-torn Mogadishu for Abu Dhabi with a visa. He also had family in both Cardiff and in Bristol; he was related to Ahmed Issa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many well-educated refugees before him, his qualifications did not cut much ice in Britain. After eight months selling encyclopaedias in London, he came to Bristol, staying in a refugee hostel in Trelawney Road, Cotham. His paper qualifications were not recognised, and while the Home Office considered his application for ‘leave to remain’ he stacked shelves at a Safeway depot for two years, and attended Brunel College to become an electrical installation engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two years later, the Home Office offered him exceptional leave to remain; luck was with him again when two Somali academics came to England in time to provide the references he needed to enrol for an M.Phil. in International Development at Bristol University. His fiancée eventually arrived from Djibouti Jibui in 1995, and Ahmed Duale was able to find more congenial work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11916 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Somalis</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/somalis</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Somalis have come to British ports as seamen since at least the 19th century, but their presence in Bristol cannot be documented before1950. Perhaps only around 10 Somali men were working as general labourers in the city in 1960, when the British and Italian colonies on the Horn of Africa merged into an independent Republic of Somalia. Small numbers of marriage partners and other workers joined them, so that a community of around 100 people had been established by 1989.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet two years later this number is estimated to have jumped to 2,000. This sudden increase was caused by the collapse of Somalia into civil war in 1991. The Soviet-style regime of Dictator Siyad Barre, who had seized power in the military coup of 1969, was finally toppled after over a decade of clan-based infighting. In the murderous chaos that ensued, some clans in the north-west of the country (formerly under British rule) grouped together to declare the secession of an independent Republic of Somaliland, based on traditional clan structures. Although unrecognised by the international community, Somaliland has enjoyed relative peace and stability since 1997. By contrast, the rest of the country and the surrounding border areas in Kenya and Ethiopia, where ethnic Somalis reside, have descended into barbarous war-lordism. Even in the cities, basic services have been destroyed and rape and murder are routinely perpetrated by ‘khat-chewing young gangsters’ in a spiral of factionalism. The 1990s saw up to one third of Somalis facing starvation and the displacement of a million of the six million population. Some of them managed to escape to Europe, despite ever-tightening restrictions on immigrants and refugees. By 2001 as many as 10,000 Somalis had come to Bristol. Six years later the estimated number of Somalis in Bristol had doubled. Although ‘push’ factors clearly outweigh ‘pull’ factors in such extreme circumstances, some respondents expressed a preference for Britain over other European countries because of the historical links and the status of English as an international language. The existence of family networks was another draw, with Bristol preferred to Bath, for example, because of its ethnic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An estimated 16,000 Somalis now live in Bristol. Concentrated mainly in the Easton, Eastville, Barton Hill and Horfield areas, they have become a focus for public attention and sometimes hostility in the city.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11915 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Robert Londe</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/robert-londe</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robert Londe (d. 1462), master of Newgate School, Bristol, and one of the town’s later medieval Irish population, from his tomb in St Peter’s Church.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robert first appears in the records as a chaplain in St Peter’s parish in 1419. The following year he became warden of St Michael’s, or Bradeston’s, Chantry in Winterbourne. He left in 1425, and was employed at Newgate by September 1426, when the Bristol merchant Thomas Bewflour left him a small bequest in his will.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In 1430 Robert Londe had to buy a licence to remain in England when his fellow Irish were expelled by order of the king, Henry VI, and ten years later he was taxed as an alien, because of his Irish birth. He had lived in Bristol since at least 1419, and had attained the position of schoolmaster at Newgate by 1426; despite this, as far as royal officialdom was concerned, Robert was not a full subject of the king of England. By 1449 he may have taken the degree of Master of Grammar at Oxford or Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to Latin grammar, Robert may have had a particular interest in canon (church) law, since a book on this subject was listed in an inventory of the possessions of St John the Baptist Church (Broad St) in 1469, described as &lt;em&gt;‘given by Master Robert, sometime schoolmaster of this town’&lt;/em&gt;. Among his students may have been William Worcestre, the famous antiquarian, who was born in Bristol in 1415 and who wrote a detailed description of the town in 1480.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robert’s brass gives his date of death as 23 February 1462.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11914 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Jacob&#039;s Well - remains of Jewish Ritual Washing House</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/jacobs-well-remains-jewish-ritual-washing-house</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Jacob&#039;s Well Road a small rock-cut chamber with two stone steps contains a wellhead. The lintel above has part of an inscription, of which only one Hebrew character (chet) can be read with confidence. Given its proximity to the medieval cemetery, this is almost certainly a Jewish medieval monument. It has been suggested that the well was used as a mikveh, or ritual bath used principally for female purification, but its distance from the Jewry, some 1,600m, and the terrain on Brandon Hill, rule out its use by the women, as they would have been highly vulnerable to unwelcome attention, or even attack, on their regular monthly visits. More probably it was a bet tohorah, a ritual bath associated with burial rites. Jacob’s Well, it seems, offered provisions for ritual purification, whether of the corpse itself or of those who were deemed impure through contact with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In accordance with their religion and customs the Jews needed a secluded hillside for a separate cemetery together with two sources of water, one for the washing of their dead and the other for their purification rituals. The spring and chamber for preparing the dead for burial needed to be close to the cemetery and was known as the ‘Tahara’. A Mikveh could utilise either still or flowing water, however the rules for construction and use were different, and thus the distinction had to be clearly marked. After completing the work on the spring the final addition would have been a notice &#039;Sacholim&#039;, advising their brethren that it was a Mikveh with flowing water and to use it in accordance with the appropriate rules. Fortunately for posterity the important word was deeply carved into the massive lintel stone above the Mikveh chamber, where it remains today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11913 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Sabbath Lamp</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/sabbath-lamp</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excavations in 1975-6 in Peter Street uncovered an exceptionally well-preserved three-wick bronze lamp, one of the very few examples of the English medieval Jewry’s material culture to have survived. Identified as a Sabbath lamp, it would have been lit by the wife above the table on Friday evenings and the eve of festivals, to symbolise the light of religion that such occasions bring to the Jewish family. The precise find site would have fronted Narrow Winch Street, on the south side, whereas the documented buildings already referred to were on the north.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11912 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
<item>
 <title>Mary Carpenter</title>
 <link>https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore/items/mary-carpenter</link>
 <description>&lt;div class=&quot;item-body&quot;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now portrayed as one of Bristol&#039;s most revered adopted daughters, she is best remembered as pioneering educational provision for the poor. The Irish about whom she spoke were specifically the city&#039;s Irish Catholic poor (Bristol had no problem assimilating propertied Irish Protestants into the civic elite, and there were few affluent Irish Catholics in mid Victorian Bristol).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carpenter has been characterized as &#039;highly prejudiced&#039; toward the Irish. Her testimony to the 1861 Commons Select Committee on the Education of Destitute Children is cited as evidence for this. There she is recorded as condemning &#039;the low Irish&#039; in Bristol&#039;s Quayside as &#039;uncivilized&#039; and as criticizing Catholic authorities for promoting ignorance and sectarianism. It is tempting to discount her opinions and her offensive terminology without further analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
 <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2010 17:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DimaN</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">11911 at https://www.victoriacountyhistory.ac.uk/explore</guid>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
